<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>ascii.key</key><document><id>2133148</id><passage><infon key="article-id_pmc">2133148</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">10366599</infon><infon key="fpage">1277</infon><infon key="issue">6</infon><infon key="journal-title">The Journal of Cell Biology</infon><infon key="kwd">presenilins Alzheimer's disease calcium-binding protein myristoylation cell death</infon><infon key="lpage">1292</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Stabler;given-names:Stacy M.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ostrowski;given-names:Lisa L.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Janicki;given-names:Susan M.</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Monteiro;given-names:Mervyn J.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">145</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>0</offset><text>A Myristoylated Calcium-binding Protein that Preferentially Interacts with  the Alzheimer's Disease Presenilin 2 Protein </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>122</offset><text>It is well established that mutations in the  presenilin 1 and 2 genes cause the majority of early onset Alzheimer's disease (AD). However, our understanding of the cellular functions of the proteins they  encode remains rudimentary. Knowledge of proteins  with which the presenilins interact should lead to a better understanding of presenilin function in normal and  disease states. We report here the identification of a calcium-binding protein, calmyrin, that interacts preferentially with presenilin 2 (PS2). Calmyrin is myristoylated, membrane-associated, and colocalizes with PS2  when the two proteins are overexpressed in HeLa cells.  Yeast two-hybrid liquid assays, affinity chromatography, and coimmunoprecipitation experiments confirm  binding between PS2 and calmyrin. Functionally,  calmyrin and PS2 increase cell death when cotransfected into HeLa cells. These results allude to several  provocative possibilities for a dynamic role of calmyrin  in signaling, cell death, and AD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1117</offset><text>Alzheimer's disease (AD)1 is a degenerative disorder  characterized clinically by progressive dementia  and neuropathologically by the presence of senile  plaques and neurofibrillary tangles (NFT). Genetic studies  indicate the etiology of AD to be heterogeneous. Mutations in (amyloid precursor protein (betaAPP), presenilin  1(PS1), and presenilin 2 (PS2) (reviewed by Hardy, 1997;  Cruts and Van Broeckhoven, 1998) are linked to autosomal dominant inheritance of early onset familial AD (i.e.,  FAD before 65 years of age). Many other genes, including  some that act as modifiers or risk factors, appear to be associated with late-onset AD (&gt;65 yr; Corder et al., 1993;  Payami et al., 1997; Pericak-Vance et al., 1997; Blacker et al.,  1998; Montoya et al., 1998). Approximately 50% of all  FAD cases are linked to the presenilin genes where missense mutations are generally found in residues that are  conserved between the two proteins with the rare exceptions of in-frame splice deletions and premature truncations. The mechanisms by which mutations in PS and  betaAPP genes cause AD are not known, although mutations  in these genes appear somehow interconnected as they  increase amyloidogenic Abeta fragment accumulation (reviewed by Hardy, 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2369</offset><text>Human PS1 and PS2 genes are both ubiquitously expressed, but at low protein levels which have lead to difficulties and inconsistencies in their detection and localization. Upon overexpression, the presenilins have been  localized to the ER and nuclear envelope (see Kovacs et al.,  1996; Janicki and Monteiro, 1997 and references therein)  with one group reporting evidence also for cell surface localization (Dewji and Singer, 1997). Endogenous PS1 and  PS2 proteins, in turn, have been localized to a variety of  structures, including the ER, vesicular structures of the somatodentritic compartment, within axons, at centrosomes  and centromeres, and at the plasma membrane (Busciglio  et al., 1997; Capell et al., 1997; Li et al., 1997; Ye and Fortini, 1998).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3132</offset><text>Human PS1 and PS2 proteins are 67% identical, sharing highest similarity in their COOH-terminal sequence  and in multiple internal regions that are structurally predicted to form transmembrane domains (TMD). Assuming the presenilins are transmembrane proteins, their topography according to most models is of a protein that  weaves through membranes eight times with the NH2-  and COOH-terminal domains and the large &quot;loop&quot; spanning the putative sixth and seventh TMD all facing the cytoplasm (see Fig. 1; Hardy, 1997). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3657</offset><text>Several lines of evidence from a variety of species have  indicated presenilins play important roles during development. First, the Caenorhabditis elegans presenilin homologue, sel-12, facilitates Notch-based cell signaling of  lin-12, a gene involved in cell fate determination and vulva  development (see Levitan and Greenwald, 1995). Second,  PS1 knockout mice die shortly after birth with the embryos displaying central nervous system defects and abnormal patterning of the axial skeleton and spinal ganglia  (Shen et al., 1997; Wong et al., 1997). Third, disruption of  the Drosophila PS gene is lethal, causing Notch processing  defects as well as Notch-like phenotypes (Strul and Greenwald, 1999; Ye et al., 1999). Although these results clearly  allude to a role for presenilins in development, the mechanisms by which FAD mutations in presenilin genes cause  AD are unknown. Interestingly, mice disrupted of PS1 can  be rescued by human transgenes containing FAD-linked  PS mutations, indicating that the FAD mutations do not  affect PS functions related to embryo development in  mammals (Davis et al., 1998; Qian et al., 1998). In contrast,  the C. elegans sel-12 mutant is more able to discriminate  between wild-type and FAD bearing PS transgenes, being  functionally rescued by expression of wild-type human  presenilins but only partially by presenilins containing  FAD mutations (Levitan et al., 1996; Baumeister et al.,  1997). The FAD-linked PS mutations are thought to confer some unknown detrimental gain of function which correlates with altered betaAPP processing (see Davis et al.,  1998; De Strooper et al., 1998; Qian et al., 1998).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5313</offset><text>Presenilins have also been implicated in the regulation  of programmed cell death (apoptosis). Evidence for such a  role was first shown when a cDNA fragment encoding the  103 COOH-terminal amino acids of mouse PS2, termed  ALG-3, was isolated in a screen for cDNAs that could rescue T cells from receptor-induced apoptosis (Vito et al.,  1996a). This rescue appears to be a consequence of the  ALG-3 fragment acting in a dominant negative fashion,  since expression of full-length PS2 leads to apoptosis (Vito  et al., 1996b). Compared with the apoptosis induced by the  overexpression of wild-type PS2 in PC12 and HeLa cells,  the FAD PS2-N141I mutation causes even higher levels of  apoptosis (Deng et al., 1996; Wolozin et al., 1996; Janicki  and Monteiro, 1997). Likewise, PS1 overexpression also  sensitizes cells to apoptosis (Guo et al., 1996, 1997; Wolozin et al., 1998). The mechanisms by which presenilins  induce apoptosis are not fully understood, but perturbations in calcium, oxidative stress (Guo et al., 1996; Keller et  al., 1998), destabilization of beta-catenin (Zhang et al., 1998),  and increased signaling by heterotrimeric GTP-binding  proteins have been implicated (Wolozin et al., 1996; Smine  et al., 1998).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6546</offset><text>To gain a better understanding of presenilin function,  we used the yeast two-hybrid system to identify proteins  with which human PS2 interacts. Using the loop region of  PS2 as bait we have isolated and characterized a recently  identified calcium-binding protein that binds preferentially  to PS2 compared with PS1 loop sequence. This protein,  calmyrin, displays several interesting properties including  myristoylation, membrane-association, and colocalization  with PS2 in cotransfected cells. Like presenilin, calmyrin  causes cell death when overexpressed in HeLa cells, and  interestingly, coexpression of PS2 and calmyrin promotes  an additive increase in cell death. The interaction of this  calcium-binding protein with PS2 may therefore be important in presenilin function.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>7333</offset><text>Materials and Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>7355</offset><text>Primer List</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7367</offset><text>B3': 5'GCTGAGTACGCTCGAGGTAGGGGAGCTGGAGGGC3'; B5':  5'CGCTTCTGGAATTCCCCAAAGGGCCTCTGAG3'; C3': 5'GCTAGCATCGCTCGAGCCACACCATGGCAGATG3'; D5': 5'CGCTTCTGGAATT\\CCCCACGGTTGGCATG3'; E3': 5'TATCGCTTAAGTCGACGATGTAGAGCTGATGGG3'; E5': 5'CGGTACGTGAATTCAAGAAGGCGCTGCC3'; F3': 5'GCTAGCATCGCTCGAGATACTTGGAATTTTTGG3'; F5': 5'CGTCATCAGCGAATTCCCGAAAGGTCCACTTCG3'; G3': 5'CTCGCCTAGCCTCGAGCCACACCATTGTTGAGG3'; L3': 5'TCGTGAGGATCCTCGAGCTACTGGAGCCGCGACAGGC3'; L5': 5'CTAGACCTGAATTCCCAATGGCGACTGCGACCCC3'; M3': 5'CGAGTAGCATGTCGACCAGGACAATCTTAAAGGA3'; M5': 5'GCTACACTAGCCGCGGGAATTCGGCACGAGGCG3'; N3': 5'CGAGTAGCATGTCGACTCACAGGACAATCTTAAA3'; N5': 5'GCTACACTAGCCGCGGCCACCATGGAGCAAAAGCTCATTTC TGAAGAGGAC TT GAAT CGCGGCGGGGCGATGGG3'. Restriction enzymes sites incorporated into the primers to  aid in cloning are underlined.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>8253</offset><text>Yeast Two-Hybrid Library Screening</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8288</offset><text>The yeast two-hybrid screen for PS2 interacting proteins was performed  essentially as described by Golemis et al. (1996), with the necessary plasmids and cDNA library obtained from Dr. Roger Brent (Harvard Medical  School, Cambridge, MA). The PS2-loop bait (designated PS2-loop B, see  Fig. 1 A) was constructed by PCR amplification of the region from human  PS2 (Janicki and Monteiro, 1997) using primers B5' and B3'. The resulting 150-bp PCR fragment was double digested with EcoRI and XhoI and  ligated into the corresponding sites of the pEG202 LexA fusion plasmid.  This bait construct and the LacZ reporter plasmid pSH18-34 were  cotransformed into yeast strain EGY48 which was then transformed with  ~5 mug of human fetal brain cDNA library in pJG4-5. 1.5 x 107 of the resulting transformants were plated on Gal/Raf/CM-ura-his-trp-leu plates to  screen for transcriptional activation of the chromosomally integrated  LEU2 reporter gene. 100 Leu+ yeast colonies were picked to a Glu/CM-ura-his-trp master plate, then replica-plated to Glu/CM-ura-his-trp-leu,  Gal/Raf/CM-ura-his-trp-leu, Glu/Xgal/CM-ura-his-trp and Gal/Raf/Xgal/ CM-ura-his-trp plates to test for galactose-dependent leu2 and lacZ expression. Dual expression of the reporters was displayed by 15 colonies,  from which the library plasmids were recovered in Escherichia coli strain  JBe15 and subsequently transformed back into EGY48 containing  pSH18-34 and the pEG202LexA/PS2-loop B bait or one of several negative controls to test the specificity of the interaction with PS2-loop B. The  library plasmids that produced a strong and specific interaction with PS2-loop B were recovered in E. coli strain DH1 and the DNA sequence of  their inserts was determined.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10032</offset><text>DNA and protein sequences were analyzed using MacVector 6.5 (Oxford Molecular). Homology searches of the NCBI databases were performed using the BLAST program. Three of seven putative interactors  were independent clonings of the same cDNA which we named calmyrin.  For further experiments, clone 7, a library plasmid which contained full-length calmyrin cDNA was digested with EcoRI and XhoI and subcloned  into pBluescript KS(-) or pGST/His T1 vector (Pharmacia Biotech, Inc.).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>10514</offset><text>Yeast Two-Hybrid Liquid Assay</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10544</offset><text>The specificity of the calmyrin interaction was tested against three PS2-loop region constructs, two different PS1-loop constructs of which one was  further mutated to the corresponding PS2 sequence, one PS2 COOH-terminal construct, and a lamin control. A conserved 31-amino acid loop region (designated PS2-loop C) was obtained by using primers B5' and C3'  to PCR generate a 93-bp fragment. The more divergent region of the loop  (designated PS2-loop D) was generated using primers D5' and B3'. A  construct encoding the final 40 amino acids of PS2 (designated PS2-Cterm) was created using primers E5' and E3'. The corresponding loop B  and loop C regions in PS1 were PCR amplified using primers F5' with F3'  or G3', respectively, from a full-length PS1 clone obtained from Dr. S.S.  Sisodia (University of Chicago, IL). The PS1-loop C region, which differs  by only three amino acids from the corresponding PS2-loop (containing a  threonine instead of a proline at position 281 (see Fig 1 A, numbered according to PS1), a leucine in place of an isoleucine at position 282, and a  threonine for an alanine at position 291), was mutated at each of the three  divergent residues, singly, and in every possible combination to the corresponding PS2 sequence using appropriate PCR primers and the  QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis method (Stratagene). A control  bait construct which contained the first 31 amino acids of lamin B was obtained by PCR with primers L5' and L3' from lamin B cloned in pBluescript KS(-) (Mical and Monteiro, 1998).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12116</offset><text>All PCR-amplified regions were digested with EcoRI and XhoI, cloned  into pEG202, and confirmed by DNA sequencing. These various baits  were transformed into EGY48 and found by immunoblotting of yeast extracts to express appropriately sized lexA-PS fusion polypeptides. Three  isolates from yeast transformed with the calmyrin in pJG4-5 (clone 7) plus  each PS bait or the control lamin bait were assayed for beta-galactosidase enzyme activity in liquid cultures using ONPG (O-nitrophenyl beta-d-galactopyranoside) as a substrate (Reynolds and Lundblad, 1989).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>12673</offset><text>Northern Blot Analysis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12696</offset><text>32P-labeled DNA probes were prepared via standard random primer labeling of 100 ng of full-length calmyrin cDNA or human beta-actin cDNA  control. A human multiple tissue Northern (MTN) blot and a human  brain multiple tissue Northern blot II (CLONTECH Laboratories, Inc.)  were hybridized with the calmyrin probe at 68 C overnight, washed in  0.1x SSC at 50 C, and exposed to film. The blots were then stripped of the  calmyrin probe and reprobed with the beta-actin control (CLONTECH Laboratories, Inc.).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13202</offset><text>Bacterial GST Fusion Protein Expression</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13242</offset><text>The original pGST construct or the pGST construct containing the complete calmyrin sequence fused COOH-terminally and in-frame with GST  was transformed into CAG456 bacteria. Unfused GST and GST/calmyrin  fusion protein induction with IPTG, incubation with glutathione agarose,  and elution with reduced glutathione were as described in Janicki and  Monteiro (1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13609</offset><text>Cloning of Eukaryotic Expression Constructs</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13653</offset><text>The pGEM-CMV vector, a CMV-driven expression plasmid containing a  COOH-terminal myc-tag (described in Janicki and Monteiro, 1997), was  used for protein expression in HeLa cells. A calmyrin construct containing  an in frame COOH-terminal myc epitope was created by PCR amplifying  the calmyrin fragment from pBS-calmyrin with primers M5' and M3' resulting in a ~600-bp PCR product that was digested with SacII and SalI  and ligated into pGEM-CMV.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14107</offset><text>An NH2-terminal myc-tagged calmyrin construct was also created by  PCR using primer N5' with primer N3' to introduce eleven residues of the  myc epitope (Monteiro et al., 1994) followed by four residues encoded by  5' untranslated calmyrin sequence linked to the complete calmyrin coding  sequence. The resulting ~600-bp PCR product was digested with SacII  and SalI and ligated into pGEM-CMV.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14509</offset><text>An untagged full-length calmyrin expression construct was created by  digesting pBS-calmyrin with SacII and XhoI, gel isolating the ~650-bp  fragment, and ligating it to SacII/SalI linearized pGEM-CMV. The cloning and expression of both full-length PS2 and the PS2 construct deleted  of loop and COOH-terminal sequence [pPS2(268aa) + Myc] were described previously (Janicki and Monteiro, 1997). Expression of full-length  wild-type neurofilament light (NF-L) subunit was achieved using the  CMV-NF-L expression construct (Lee et al., 1993).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>15052</offset><text>Polyclonal Antibody Production</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15083</offset><text>Purified GST/calmyrin protein and GST/PS2(NH2-terminal) fusion protein (described in Janicki and Monteiro, 1997) were sent to Covance Research Products for inoculation into rabbits. The specificity of these rabbit  antibodies was determined by immunoblotting (Janicki and Monteiro,  1997) and immunofluorescent staining of HeLa cell transfected with  calmyrin or PS2. For immunoblotting, the anti-calmyrin and anti-PS2 antibodies were used at a 1/500-1/700 dilution and detected with horseradish  peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit secondary antibodies and SuperSignal Substrate (Pierce Chemical Co.).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>15691</offset><text>HeLa Cell Culture and DNA Transfection</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15730</offset><text>HeLa cells were grown in DME supplemented with 10% FBS and transiently transfected with appropriate plasmid DNAs as calcium phosphate  precipitates (Janicki and Monteiro, 1997). Alternatively, 20 mug of DNA  and 2 x 106 HeLa cells were electroporated at 960 muF and 0.3 kV.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16005</offset><text>Cell Staining and Immunofluorescence Microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16053</offset><text>HeLa cells were transfected directly on glass coverslips, fixed, and antibody stained as described in Janicki and Monteiro (1997). Antibodies  used were rabbit anti-calmyrin serum (diluted 1:250), goat anti-PS2(NH2-terminal) antibody (diluted 1:150; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), rabbit  anti-lamin serum (diluted 1:200; Mical and Monteiro, 1998), rabbit anti-NFL serum (diluted 1:250; generated in this lab using recombinant-purified, bacterially expressed, mouse neurofilament light chain), M30 CytoDEATH mouse anti-cytokeratin 18 antibody (diluted 1:50; Boehringer  Mannheim), fluorescein- and rhodamine-conjugated donkey anti-rabbit,  anti-goat, and anti-mouse antibodies (Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories, Inc.). Fluorescence staining of cells was visualized on an inverted  Leica DM IRB microscope and images were captured using a Photometrics SenSys camera and manipulated with IPLab Spectrum and Multiprobe software (Scanalytics) on a Power Macintosh. Confocal microscopy  and image processing was performed using the x100 objective of a Leica  confocal and imaging system (Leica Inc.) with the kind help of Dr. Timothy Mical and Dr. Joseph Gall (Carnegie Institution, Baltimore, MD).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>17259</offset><text>Mouse Tissue Lysates and Primary Cultures</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17301</offset><text>Spleen, brain, kidney, liver, heart, and skeletal muscle tissues were dissected from an adult mouse, chopped with a razor blade in 1-2 ml lysis  buffer (Monteiro and Mical, 1996), homogenized on ice, briefly sonicated  on ice, and centrifuged at 2,000 rpm for 5 min. Tissue lysate supernatants  were collected, their protein concentration was determined by the BCA  Protein Assay (Pierce), and 100 mug of each sample was separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred to nitrocellulose filters, and immunoblotted with the  rabbit anti-calmyrin antibody.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17845</offset><text>Kidney and heart tissues from 8-12 2-d-old mice were chopped with a  razor blade, resuspended in 2 ml 0.25% collagenase in PBS, vortexed, incubated at 37 C for 15 min, centrifuged, and washed 3x with PBS. Cells  were cultured in EGM medium supplemented with BBE (Clonetics) and  10% FBS for 2-7 d. For immunofluorescence, cells were cultured directly  onto coverslips and fixed and stained as described above.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18261</offset><text>Cell Fractionation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18280</offset><text>Nondetergent soluble and insoluble fractions of HeLa cells were prepared  essentially as described by Gerace and Globel (1980). HeLa cells (~1 x  106) were collected 24 h after transfection by scraping the cells in ice-cold  PBS and centrifugation at 10,000 g. The cells were resuspended in 0.25 ml  10 mM triethanolamine-HCL (pH 7.4), 10 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl2, 5 mM  iodoacetamide, and 1 mM Pefabloc (Boehringer Mannheim). After 10  min incubation on ice the cells were disrupted with 10 gentle strokes in a  0.5-ml Potter-Elvehjem homogenizer. Next, 0.25 ml 10 mM triethanolamine-HCL (pH 7.4), 270 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl2, 5 mM iodoacetamide,  and 1 mM Pefabloc were added and after mixing, the homogenates were  centrifuged at 100,000 g for 15 min in a Beckman TLX ultracentrifuge.  The supernatants were removed and the pellets resuspended in lysis  buffer (Monteiro and Mical, 1996) to a volume equal that of their respective supernatants.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19224</offset><text>Triton X-100-treated HeLa cell fractions were prepared by lysing the  transfected cells in 0.5 ml ice-cold 1% Triton X-100, 10 mM triethanolamine-HCL (pH 6.9), 140 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl2, 5 mM iodoacetamide,  and 1 mM Pefabloc. After 10 min incubation the lysates were centrifuged  at 140,000 g for 15 min. Supernatants were collected and the pellets resuspended in lysis buffer. Equivalent volumes of the supernatant and pellet  fractions of the detergent-treated and untreated cells were separated by  SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted using the rabbit anti-calmyrin antibody  or the rabbit anti-lamin antibody. The same cell fractionation procedure  was used on primary cell cultures prepared from mouse kidney.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>19932</offset><text>Myristoylation Experiments</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19959</offset><text>After transfection, sodium pyruvate to a final concentration of 1 mM and  0.1-0.2 mCi 3H-myristic acid (Amersham Life Science Inc.) were added to  the fresh media in each cell culture dish. At ~24 h after transfection, cells  were scraped off the bottom of the dish and the media was collected and  centrifuged 5 min at 3,000 rpm. The cell pellet was washed with PBS, centrifuged, resuspended in 400 mul lysis buffer (50 mM Hepes, 100 mM KCl,  0.3% NP40, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM EGTA, pH 7.5, + protease inhibitor  cocktail with aprotonin, leupeptin, and PMSF; Boehringer Mannheim),  and homogenized on ice. Insoluble material was pelleted and the supernatant was collected and diluted with an equal volume of dilution buffer (50 mM  Hepes, 1 mM EDTA, and 1 mM EGTA, pH 7.5). 150 mul of the lysates  were incubated with 5 mul of antibody (rabbit anti-calmyrin, rabbit anti-PS2, or rabbit control preimmune serum) for 2 h at 4 C. 45 mul of a slurry of  protein A-Sepharose beads (Pharmacia Biotech, Inc.) was then added to  the lysates and incubated with rotamixing for another 1 h. The beads were  pelleted by centrifugation, and after removal of the supernatant, the beads  were washed four times with lysis/dilution buffer. All of the immunoprecipitate and one-sixth of the supernatant sample were separated by SDS-PAGE. After Coomassie blue staining and destaining, the gel was soaked  for three 15 min changes in DMSO, immersed in 22% PPO (2,5-diphenyloxazole) for 90 min, washed in water, dried, and exposed to film by fluorography for 1 wk to 2 mo.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>21513</offset><text>Affinity Chromatography</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21537</offset><text>After ~24 h, mock or PS2-transfected HeLa cells (~1 x 106 cells) were  washed in ice-cold PBS, scraped into PBS, and pelleted by centrifugation  for 5 min at 3,000 rpm. The cells were resuspended in 400 mul of lysis buffer  (see myristoylation section), sonicated, and homogenized on ice. Insoluble  material was pelleted and the supernatant was collected and diluted with  an equal volume of dilution buffer. All of the soluble lysate was incubated  overnight at 4 C with CNBr-activated Sepharose beads (Pharmacia Biotech, Inc.) coupled with an equivalent amount (240 mug) of either purified  GST or GST/calmyrin. The Sepharose beads were then pelleted by centrifugation and supernatant containing unbound protein was removed.  The beads were washed with 2.5 M KCl, resuspended in Laemmli buffer,  and 1/2 of the sample was separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted  for the presence of PS2 using a goat anti-PS2(NH2-terminal) antibody.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>22479</offset><text>Quantification of Cell Death</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22508</offset><text>Duplicate dishes of HeLa cells (plated at ~3 x 105/100 mM dishes) were  transfected with various combinations of pGEM-CMV-calmyrin, pGEM-CMV-PS2, and control vector (a CAT basic expression vector; Promega).  After ~48 h, floating cells from each dish were harvested by collecting  all of the media, centrifuging 5 min at 3,000 rpm, and removing all but  ~0.5 ml of the supernatant. After vortexing, the exact volume of each cell  suspension was measured. Cell numbers were counted twice for each sample on a hemacytometer. These cell counts were adjusted according to the  initial resuspension volume to give the total number of floating cells per  dish. The counts for the two independent dishes of each transfection construct combination were averaged and graphed. There was a direct correspondence between floating cells and apoptotic cells, with ~85% of floating cells showing positive CytoDEATH staining.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>23427</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>23435</offset><text>PS2-Loop Interaction Trap Identifies a Calcium-binding Protein, Calmyrin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23508</offset><text>Using the yeast two-hybrid system, a human fetal brain  cDNA library was screened for proteins that bind the loop  region of PS2. Full-length PS2 was unsuitable as bait presumably because it could not be transported into the nucleus due to the presence of hydrophobic transmembrane  domains. In addition, as it is one of the most divergent regions between the presenilin proteins, we believed our  chances of finding PS2-specific interactors would be increased. After finding that our initial PS2-loop construct  (residues 270-361) self-activated transcription, we truncated the bait reducing it to the first 50 amino acids in order to eliminate several acidic residues and designated it  PS2-loop B (B for bait; Fig. 1 A). The PS2-loop B bait construct, the lacZ reporter plasmid, and human fetal brain  cDNA library plasmids were transformed into yeast, and  out of 1.5 x 107 primary transformants screened, 15 putative interactors were isolated. Isolated library prey plasmids were tested for their ability to reproduce the specific  interaction phenotype when coexpressed with the loop  bait but not with unrelated baits (such as human lamin B).  Clones that produced the specific interaction phenotype  were sequenced and identified via BLAST homology database search. Interestingly, three of the interactors were  independent cDNAs all containing the full coding sequence of a recently identified calcium-binding protein,  but with varying NH2-terminal untranslated extensions.  Two other groups have recovered this calcium-binding  protein in yeast two-hybrid screens and have named it  CIB, for its calcium- and integrin alphaIIb-binding ability  (Naik et al., 1997), and KIP, due to its interaction with eukaryotic DNA-dependent protein kinase, DNA-PKcs (Wu  and Lieber, 1997). Rather than pick between these two  names we have chosen to refer to this protein as calmyrin  (for calcium-binding myristoylated protein with homology  to calcineurin) because it describes its inherent properties  without bias towards its multiple binding partners.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25564</offset><text>To quantify the binding specificity of calmyrin to the  PS2-loop and to determine if this protein also interacts  with the PS1 loop which is 45% identical in amino acid sequence, we measured the beta-galactosidase activity in yeast  liquid assays. When cotransformed with calmyrin, the PS2-loop B bait produced an 8.5-fold increase in beta-galactosidase activity over the lamin B negative control, while the  corresponding region of PS1 (PS1-loop B) produced only  a 1.9-fold increase in activity (Fig. 1 B). A PS2-COOH-terminal construct, containing the COOH-terminal 39- amino acid sequence downstream of the eighth TMD also  did not appear to interact with calmyrin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26234</offset><text>To further map the binding site of calmyrin within the  PS2-loop, two new baits were constructed which divided  the loop into a conserved portion, loop C (28 out of the 31  amino acids are identical to PS1), and a divergent region,  loop D (only 33% identity to PS1; Fig 1 A). Since calmyrin  did not interact preferentially with the comparable loop  region of PS1 (PS1-loop B) we expected the calmyrin  binding site to be within the divergent region of the PS2-loop sequence (PS2-loop D). To our surprise, the PS2-loop D bait interacted very weakly with calmyrin, a 2.2-fold increase over control (Fig. 1 B). However, the highly  conserved region of the PS2 loop, PS2-loop C, produced a  74-fold increase in activity (Fig. 1 C). In comparison, the  corresponding PS1-loop C construct increased activity  only 5.8-fold.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27054</offset><text>Although the two PS-loop C baits are highly conserved  in sequence, they differ by three amino acids, with PS1  containing threonine residues at positions 281 and 291 instead of proline and alanine, respectively (see Fig. 1 A,  numbered according to PS1), and a leucine instead of an  isoleucine at position 282. We investigated how these  three divergent residues influenced calmyrin interaction  with the PS-loop C region in yeast two-hybrid assays by introducing the PS2 amino acids into the PS1 bait, so that  each of the three divergent residues were mutated singly,  and in every possible combination, to the corresponding  PS2 sequence. These data indicated that all three residues  contributed in different and complex ways towards the interaction (Fig. 1 C). Interestingly, calmyrin interaction was  restored to approximately half the PS2 level by single mutation of residue 281 to a proline, a residue which would be  predicted to introduce a kink in the loop. In comparison,  single mutation of residue 282 to an isoleucine did not increase binding to any significant extent, whereas mutation  of residue 291 to an alanine increased binding to a third  that of the PS2 level. Double mutants confirmed the importance of residues 281 and 291. When both proline and  alanine were present together (T281P, T291A) they increased binding substantially, producing an approximately  twofold higher level of binding compared with the wild-type PS2-loop bait. This mutant suggests that isoleucine at  residue 282 in PS2 may actually compromise binding, as  this would be equivalent to the triple substitution (T281P,  L282I, T291A; i.e., turning it back to the PS2 sequence).  Consistent with this expectation, isoleucine 282, when  present together with alanine 291, did not increase binding  above that of the latter alone, whereas paradoxically when  it was substituted together with proline 281 it increased  binding 1.7-fold higher than when proline was substituted  alone.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29034</offset><text>The 191-amino acid sequence of calmyrin has a number  of notable features (Fig. 2 A). Sequence comparison indicates that calmyrin is most closely related to human calcineurin B, the regulatory subunit of protein phosphatase  2B, sharing 25% identity and 44% overall similarity. The  protein contains two complete EF hands, a conserved motif involved in calcium binding, and in fact, was shown to  bind radiolabeled calcium in blot overlay assays (Naik et al.,  1997). The protein also contains an NH2 consensus myristoylation site, a cotranslational modification involved in  targeting proteins to membranes. To verify the size and  expression pattern of calmyrin transcripts, Northern blot  analysis of poly(A)+ RNA isolated from multiple adult  human tissues was performed (Fig. 2 B). The calmyrin  probe hybridized to an ~1.2-kb transcript that was ubiquitously expressed in the tissues examined, extending the evidence that it is widely expressed (Naik et al., 1997; Wu  and Lieber, 1997) and implying that it plays a common  function in most if not all cells. Although mRNA expression was relatively low in brain, a Northern blot of specific  brain regions showed that the expression of calmyrin transcripts was easily detectable and fairly uniform (Fig. 2 C). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>30305</offset><text>Tissue Distribution and Subcellular Localization of  Endogenous Calmyrin Protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30386</offset><text>To study further the calmyrin protein, rabbit polyclonal  anti-calmyrin antibodies were generated to affinity-purified GST/calmyrin fusion protein (Fig. 3 A, lane 7). By  immunoblotting, these antibodies appear to be highly  specific for calmyrin as they reacted only with the appropriately sized polypeptides (~22-25 kD) in HeLa cells  overexpressing calmyrin cDNAs (Fig. 3 B). Lane 1 of Fig.  3 B shows that at the depicted exposure time the antibodies failed to detect any endogenous calmyrin in untransfected lysate. Only after prolonged exposure did a faint  calmyrin band appear (data not shown), indicating that endogenous levels of this calcium-binding protein are relatively low in HeLa cells. However, consistent with our  Northern blot analysis, an endogenous immunoreactive  band at ~22 kD was detected in human adult brain lysate  (Fig. 3 C). The anti-calmyrin antibodies also successfully  detected the mouse form of this protein in several mouse  tissue lysates (Fig. 3 D) due to the high conservation between the human and mouse calmyrin proteins (only five  dissimilar residues; Saito et al., 1999). The significance of  the faster migrating immunoreactive band in mouse skeletal muscle (Fig. 3 D, lane 6) has not been determined. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31639</offset><text>Since the subcellular localization of calmyrin was unknown, we used the anti-calmyrin antibody to determine  its distribution in mammalian cells by indirect immunofluorescence microscopy. In primary cultures from mouse  heart tissue endogenous calmyrin localized to the nucleus  and in a reticular-like pattern throughout the cytoplasm  (Fig. 3 E). This staining was clearly distinguishable from  the nonspecific background produced when probing with  rabbit preinnoculation serum (data not shown), and moreover, this staining pattern was reproduced by overexpression of calmyrin upon transfection (see below).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>32250</offset><text>Calmyrin Is Myristoylated and Membrane Associated</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32300</offset><text>As PS2 is a transmembrane protein and our yeast two-hybrid findings indicated that calmyrin interacts with PS2,  the membrane targeting potential of the consensus myristoylation site in calmyrin especially intrigued us. To determine whether calmyrin is myristoylated in vivo, we added  3H-myristic acid to the media of HeLa cells transfected  with untagged calmyrin. For comparison, HeLa cells were  also transfected with calmyrin constructs that had myc tags  fused at either the NH2- or COOH-terminal ends of the  protein. The prediction was that the myc tag (MEQKLISEEDLN) fused at the NH2-terminal end would disrupt  myristoylation since it moved the glycine residue that is essential for myristoylation more downstream (Olshevskaya  et al., 1997). After 24 h, the cells were lysed and calmyrin  was immunoprecipitated with the anti-calmyrin antibody.  Myristoylated proteins were visualized by fluorography after SDS-PAGE (Fig. 4 A). The fluorograph of labeled  HeLa cell lysates indicated immunoprecipitated C-myc- tagged calmyrin and untagged wild-type calmyrin were  myristoylated as evident by incorporation of the radioactive 3H-myristic acid label (band in lanes 4 and 6 indicated  by an arrows) while, as expected, the N-myc tagging of the  protein prevented myristoylation (absence of band in lane  2). The lower panel of this figure contains an immunoblot  of these same HeLa cell lysates to show that both NH2-  and COOH-terminally tagged calmyrin proteins were  expressed efficiently and to equivalent levels, whereas  untagged calmyrin accumulated at lower protein levels,  explaining the fainter myristoylated calmyrin band seen in  lane 6 as compared with lane 4. In fact, when the ratio of  calmyrin protein to radioactive 3H-myristic acid labeling is  compared for C-myc-tagged and wild-type calmyrin proteins they are similar, which is expected since myristoylation is thought to occur cotranslationally (Wilcox et al.,  1987). The reason for higher expression of C- and N-myc- tagged calmyrin proteins is not known but perhaps fusion  of the myc epitope affects protein stability or toxicity, allowing the proteins to accumulate to higher levels. Similar  attempts to demonstrate myristoylation of endogenous  calmyrin in mouse and human cells were unsuccessful, presumably because of low protein expression or the slow  turnover of the protein. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34676</offset><text>Once we established that calmyrin was indeed myristoylated, next we determined whether this protein was associated with the membranes of fractionated cells. Transfected  HeLa cells were fractionated in the absence of any detergents into a soluble (cytosolic) supernatant and an insoluble (membrane and cytoskeletal) pellet. Equivalent  amounts of supernatant and pellet cell fractions were separated by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted for the presence of lamins and calmyrin (Fig. 4 B, lanes 1 and 2).  Lamins A and C, cytoskeletal components used as a control of the fractionation process, were detected as 68- and  66-kD polypeptides in the insoluble pellet as expected  (Gerace and Blobel, 1980; Mical and Monteiro, 1998). The  majority (&gt;85%) of the calmyrin was found in the insoluble fraction. Since this manner of cell fractionation does  not distinguish membrane components from other insoluble structures, the cells were also fractionated in the presence of 1% Triton X-100 which solubilizes membranes.  After this procedure, the calmyrin protein shifted to the  soluble (membrane) fraction whereas the lamins, as expected, remained insoluble (Fig. 4 B, lanes 3 and 4). The  same fractionation was performed on primary cultures of  mouse kidney and showed an analogous pattern of membrane localization for endogenous calmyrin (Fig. 4 B,  lower panel). Interpreted together, these cell fractionation  results provide strong biochemical evidence that calmyrin  is associated with cell membranes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>36174</offset><text>Calmyrin Accumulates in the Nucleus and Cytoplasm,  but When Coexpressed with PS2 these Two Proteins  Colocalize at the ER</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36297</offset><text>On account of the faint staining of endogenous calmyrin in  primary and established cell cultures, calmyrin was forcibly expressed in HeLa cells by transient transfection of  untagged and myc-tagged calmyrin constructs for further  immunofluorescent localization studies. As seen in Fig. 5  A, cells expressing untagged calmyrin had strong staining  in the nucleus and cytoplasm, a pattern very similar to the  subcellular localization of endogenous calmyrin detected  in mouse cells. At higher magnification, many of these  transfected cells showed clear calmyrin staining of thin  projections from the cell surface as well as a reticular  staining in the cytoplasm consistent with membrane targeting to the plasma membrane and ER (Fig. 5 C). Cells  expressing C-myc calmyrin had greater variation in staining with many showing prominent localization to the ER  and plasma membrane and often less staining in the nucleus (Fig. 5 D). Double immunofluorescence staining for  calreticulin, an ER marker protein, and calmyrin showed  that within the cytoplasm a notable portion of calmyrin  colocalized with calreticulin (data not shown), corroborating the impression that in these transfected cells calmyrin  localization includes, but is not limited to, ER membranes.  In contrast, cells expressing N-myc calmyrin showed predominant nuclear staining, more diffuse cytoplasmic staining, and less staining at the plasma membrane which was  especially evident in low expressing cells (Fig. 5 E). This  observed reduction in membrane association was not surprising considering our previous finding that this NH2-terminally tagged construct failed to be myristoylated. To  address whether the bright nuclear staining was due  to calmyrin localization within the nuclear envelope or  throughout the nucleoplasm, we double stained wild-type  calmyrin transfected HeLa cells for calmyrin and lamins  A/C. According to confocal microscopy, lamins A and C  had rim fluorescence (Fig. 5 G) consistent with their  known localization as a caged meshwork of filaments tethered to the inner nuclear envelope (see Mical and Monteiro, 1998). In the same confocal Z-section (1.0-mum  section) where lamins had rim fluorescence, calmyrin  immunoreactivity was present throughout the cell and  clearly within the nucleoplasm (Fig. 5 F). Overall, these  results indicated calmyrin localizes to many different cellular compartments, consistent with the protein having dynamic targeting properties. Of particular interest to this  study was the comparison of calmyrin and PS2 staining  patterns when overexpressed individually in HeLa cells.  Although the two staining patterns overlapped in part, especially the ER reticular staining of untagged and C-myc  calmyrin, PS2 staining was readily distinguishable by its  exclusive ER and nuclear envelope staining pattern (Fig.  5 H). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39155</offset><text>When calmyrin was coexpressed with PS2, its staining  pattern was dramatically altered such that it colocalized almost completely with PS2 (Fig. 6). As exemplified by the  two cells shown in panels A and B, the calmyrin protein  was less apparent in the nucleus in coexpressing cells than  in cells transfected solely with calmyrin (Fig. 5 A). Another indication that these two proteins bind each other  was seen in a small subset of cells where calmyrin and PS2  colocalized distinctively in unusual intranuclear spots (Fig.  6 C). The intranuclear spots did not colocalize with anti-centromere staining by double immunofluorescent microscopy (data not shown) suggesting that they are distinct  from the PS-immunoreactive structures observed by Li et al.  (1997). The shift in calmyrin localization and the nearly  identical staining patterns between PS2 and calmyrin (see  merged images) in these coexpressing cells provide persuasive evidence that these two proteins interact in vivo.  Furthermore, when calmyrin was cotransfected with a PS2  construct deleted of the loop and all sequence COOH-terminal of it, the staining patterns displayed significantly less  overlap; as seen by patchy aggregates of PS2 which excluded calmyrin (Fig. 6 D, indicated by arrows). The failure of this PS2 deletion construct to completely colocalize  with calmyrin in aggregates, which contrasts with the colocalization of the wild-type PS2 protein and calmyrin in nuclear inclusions, enhances our view that the PS2-loop region facilitates binding of calmyrin. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>40703</offset><text>Affinity Chromatography and Immunoprecipitation  Confirm Binding between Calmyrin and PS2</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40793</offset><text>Despite results from yeast two-hybrid assays, cell fractionation experiments, and histological colocalization, which  all consistently argue for an interaction between calmyrin  and PS2, our initial attempts at demonstrate binding of the  two proteins in vitro proved difficult. After trying various  combinations of affinity chromatography and immunoprecipitation with GST fusion proteins, in vitro translated  proteins, and HeLa cell-expressed proteins under several  different buffer conditions, two of these experiments provided further evidence for the binding of calmyrin and  PS2. First, HeLa cell lysates of overexpressed PS2 were  incubated with purified GST-calmyrin, or GST alone,  (shown in Fig. 3 A) that had been covalently coupled to  Sepharose. The two Sepharose columns were then washed,  and retention of PS2 was determined by immunoblotting  with anti-PS2 antibody. Fig. 7 A shows that GST-calmyrin Sepharose bound PS2 with approximately threefold  greater affinity (lane 4, see arrow) than control GST-coupled Sepharose (lane 3). The second verification of binding was the coimmunoprecipitation of myristoylated calmyrin protein from cotransfected HeLa cell lysates with  anti-PS2 antibodies (Fig. 7 B, lane 5). The myristoylated  calmyrin protein did not immunoprecipitate when the preimmune anti-PS2 serum was used (Fig. 7 B, lane 6) but,  as expected, could be immunoprecipitated with the anti-calmyrin antibody (Fig. 7 B, lane 4). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>42251</offset><text>Overexpression of Calmyrin Causes Apoptosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>42295</offset><text>Since we had previously shown that overexpression of PS2  in HeLa cells causes apoptosis (Janicki and Monteiro,  1997), we wished to determine what effect overexpression  of calmyrin would have on cell viability. To detect apoptosis we used the M30 CytoDEATH antibody. This mouse  monoclonal binds an epitope of cytokeratin 18 which is exposed only after caspase cleavage, an early event in apoptosis (Caulin et al., 1997; Boehringer Mannheim). Consistent with our previous findings, Fig. 8 A shows that a  subset (two out of three) of cells overexpressing PS2 appeared apoptotic (notably only those that had rounded  up) according to both CytoDEATH positive staining and  condensed nuclei. Similarly, when calmyrin was overexpressed, analogous apoptosis was observed (Fig. 8 B). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43076</offset><text>Cotransfection of PS2 and calmyrin induced even higher  apoptosis. To convey more clearly the high levels of apoptosis that resulted from overexpressing these two proteins,  example images captured at low magnification are provided. Fig. 8 C shows that at 16 h after cotransfection  almost 13% of PS2-expressing cells (which presumably  also expressed calmyrin since PS2 and calmyrin staining  showed a near 1:1 correspondence [data not shown]) on  coverslips were positive for CytoDEATH staining. By 40 h  the proportion of apoptotic cells had increased to ~50%  of the PS2-stained cells. The high level of apoptosis seen  on coverslips was striking, especially since this method  only captured a brief &quot;window&quot; of the cells progression  into apoptosis as during programmed cell death HeLa  cells lose their adherence on coverslips and float away into  the media. This phenomenon explains the reduction in total cells, and most notably PS-expressing cells (only 10  cells), remaining on the coverslip at 40 h after cotransfection (Fig. 8 D). In the examples shown in Fig. 8 only a subset of PS overexpressing cells were apoptotic, indicating a  time-dependent process, whereas the corollary that all  apoptotic cells were also overexpressors always held true.  In contrast when a control protein, the neurofilament light  (NF-L) subunit, was overexpressed in HeLa cells (Fig. 8  E), minimal apoptosis (&lt; 1%) was detected and total cell  counts and expression levels remained high even at 40 h. It  is remarkable that the single apoptotic cell in this field did  not stain for NF-L and that, conversely, there are several  rounded-up and highly expressing cells (presumably those  in mitosis), none of which appeared apoptotic. Fields of  cells overexpressing calmyrin or PS2 individually showed  levels of apoptosis above the neurofilament background,  but less than coexpressors. Unfortunately, due to variation  between (and even within) coverslips, this method did not  prove suitable for statistically significant quantification.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>45117</offset><text>Because CytoDEATH labeling on coverslips only captured a narrow &quot;window&quot; of cells undergoing apoptosis,  we decided to quantify the total amount of cell death accumulated over time by counting the total number of floating cells in the media after transfection with various  amounts of plasmid DNAs encoding calmyrin and PS2.  This simple method was more reliable in quantifying cell  death. As graphed in Fig. 9, transient overexpression of  PS2 increased cell death in a dose-dependent manner,  whereas cell death induced by calmyrin overexpression  reached a plateau at 10 mug of transfected DNA. More interestingly, when both proteins were coexpressed in the  linear cell death range of their respective DNAs, cell death  increased 5.9-fold over the control, compared with 2.7-  and 2.4-fold for the same respective transfection amounts  of calmyrin and PS2 individually, suggesting that these two  proteins have additive effects in promoting cell death.  When these floating cells were collected and stained with  the CytoDEATH antibody, ~85% of the cells stained  positive for this marker of apoptosis, bolstering our belief  that counting floating cells is a reliable measure of cell  death. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>46322</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46333</offset><text>In this study, we demonstrate by several criteria that human PS2 protein interacts with a recently discovered calcium-binding protein which we refer to as calmyrin. First,  calmyrin interacts with PS2-loop sequence in yeast two-hybrid assays. Second, the two proteins bind to each other  by affinity chromatography and can be coimmunoprecipitated. Third, the two full-length proteins colocalized when  coexpressed in vivo. The interaction of calmyrin with PS2  is also noteworthy since it is the first protein, to our knowledge, that interacts preferentially with PS2 (at least by  yeast two-hybrid analysis) suggesting distinct functions for  the highly homologous presenilin proteins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>47020</offset><text>Two lines of evidence favor the PS2-loop region as the  critical site of calmyrin interaction: reduced in vivo colocalization when calmyrin was coexpressed with a loop-deficient PS2 construct and increased yeast liquid culture  binding of calmyrin to the PS2-loop rather than the PS2- COOH-terminal domain. Deletion analysis indicated that  calmyrin binding was mediated primarily by the NH2-terminal 31 amino acids of the PS2-loop. Remarkably, despite only a three-amino acid difference, the comparable  loop region of PS1 interacted with less than one-tenth the  strength in similar yeast two-hybrid assays. Site-directed  mutagenesis in which the three divergent PS2 residues  were introduced singly and in double combinations into  PS1 indicated that, in fact, all three amino acids produce  variable affects on the specificity of calmyrin for PS2. Particularly interesting was the pronounced increased in binding conferred by the conversion of a threonine at positions  281 and 291 in PS1 to proline and alanine, respectively. In  contrast, the leucine at position 282 in PS1 when converted  to isoleucine as in PS2 caused pleotrophic effects, increasing, decreasing, and inducing no change in interaction depending on its context with the other two residues. These  data suggest that minor alterations in the sequence of the  PS loop induce conformational changes in this region with  dramatic consequences to protein-protein interactions.  Furthermore, the loop region is a site associated with  several PS-processing phenomena, including proteolytic  cleavage, caspase cleavage, as well as abnormal splicing  (Perez-Tur et al., 1995; Thinakaran et al. 1996; Kim et al.,  1997; Loetscher et al., 1997; reviewed by Hass, 1997).  Apart from calmyrin, several other proteins have been  found to interact with the PS-loop, namely, gamma-catenin, filamin, calselinin, mu-calpain, and armadillo protein p007  (Zhou et al., 1997; Buxbaum 1998; Murayama et al., 1998;  Shinozaki et al., 1998; Zhang et al., 1998; Stahl et al.,  1999). Our data showing that minor (single amino acid)  alterations in the loop sequence can produce dramatic  changes in protein binding not only has implications in  terms of calmyrin function, but may also have important  consequences for the other processing events and binding  partners associated with this region. Therefore, it is not  surprising that many FAD mutations map to the PS1 loop.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>49449</offset><text>In addition to the importance of protein-protein interactions for localization, our immunofluorescence microscopy and biochemical fractionation studies indicate that  the myristoylation of calmyrin is important for the dynamic targeting of this protein to several subcellular compartments including: the cytoplasm, long projections of the  plasma membrane, and the nucleoplasm. Elegant studies  of recoverin, a myristoylated calcium-binding protein involved in signaling in the retina, have established that this  protein alternates between conformations in which the  myristoyl group is exposed or sequestered, conformations  that are dependent on calcium binding (Kennedy et al., 1996;  Ames et al., 1997). These calcium-myristoyl switches are a  known mechanism for protein targeting and signal transduction. Radiolabeling and biochemical studies show that  calmyrin is myristoylated and associated with membranes.  At present, we cannot clearly tease apart the roles that  myristoylation and protein-protein interactions play in the  in vivo targeting of calmyrin to membranes. In fact, our  evidence suggests that both are important. Yeast two-hybrid assays with loop constructs containing site-directed  mutations clearly show the importance of protein-protein  interactions in mediating the association between calmyrin  and the integral membrane protein, PS2. Additionally, fusion of the Gal4-acidic blob sequence at the NH2-terminal  end of calmyrin in the yeast two-hybrid clones would be  expected to prevent this fatty acid modification suggesting  that myristoylation is not essential for the interaction.  Paradoxically, however, it is the myristoylated form of  calmyrin that we were able to show coimmunoprecipitated  with PS2. Perhaps insertion of the myristoyl group into the  lipid bilayer initiates a conformational change that enhances the affinity of calmyrin for PS2. Analogously, the  Gal4-acidic blob may have maintained calmyrin in the  conformation that was more prone to binding PS2.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>51467</offset><text>Cells overexpressing calmyrin proteins capable of being  myristoylated showed greater variation in staining patterns often with increased targeting of calmyrin to the cytoplasm and plasma membrane suggesting that myristoylation may be involved in this dynamic behavior. The  calmyrin that localized to the cytoplasm had a reticular-like staining pattern which colocalized with PS2 staining  when the two proteins were coexpressed. We believe that  the reticular staining represents targeting of calmyrin protein to the ER since we and others have shown that overexpressed PS2 was localized to the nuclear envelope and  ER (see Kovacs et al., 1996; Janicki and Monteiro, 1997).  Interestingly, in PS2-cotransfected cells relatively little  calmyrin was present in the nucleus, and instead, the entire population almost completely colocalized with PS2 at  the ER. This redistribution to the ER is consistent with  the stoichiometric change of binding sites available for  calmyrin once PS2 was overexpressed. However, the possibility that PS2 expression may alter processing or intracellular targeting of calmyrin can not be ruled out.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>52601</offset><text>As myristoylation is known to be important for membrane targeting, it is curious that a significant pool of  calmyrin is present within the nucleoplasm despite the  lack of a classical nuclear localization signal. Calmyrin is  small enough to passively diffuse through the nuclear  pores (proteins ~65 kD and larger must be actively transported) and may be sequestered within the nucleoplasm  by binding to nuclear resident proteins such as DNA-PKcs  which has also been shown to bind calmyrin in yeast two-hybrid assays (Wu and Lieber, 1997). The localization of  calmyrin to the long projections of the plasma membrane  may similarly represent binding to calmyrin's other known  interactor, alphaIIb-subunit of integrin. These results indicate  that calmyrin may traffic between several proteins and factors suggesting a role for calmyrin in complex signaling  processes. How these processes relate to AD, and/or  apoptosis is not known but it is interesting that Volado, a  novel integrin which dynamically mediate cell adhesion  and signal transduction, was recently identified as a new  memory mutant in Drosophila (Grotewiel et al., 1998).  Also DNA-PKcs is the only known eukaryotic protein kinase activated by DNA double-strand breaks which is a lesion induced during apoptosis (reviewed McConnell and  Dynan, 1996; Sheih et al., 1997). The possibility that  calmyrin, integrins, DNA-PKcs, and PS2 are in any way  connected or involved in human diseases is intriguing, yet  speculative.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>54095</offset><text>In hypothesizing a physiologic role for the interaction  between PS2 and calmyrin, we are especially interested in  exploring the involvement of calcium and apoptosis. It is  noteworthy that calsenilin, another Ca2+-binding protein  with sequence similarity to recoverin, binds to the COOH-terminal region of presenilin proteins and like calmyrin redistributes with presenilin proteins in cotransfected cells  (Buxbaum, et al., 1998). Calmyrin does not share a high  degree of amino acid similarity to calsenilin, instead the  protein sequence of calmyrin is most homologous to human calcineurin B, the regulatory subunit of the Ca2+-calmodulin-dependent protein phosphatase 2B, which  plays important roles in stress, apoptosis, cell calcium signaling, and signal transduction (see Guerini, 1997; Crabtree, 1999; Wang et al., 1999). The greatest homology is  found in the regions surrounding calcineurin B's four calcium-binding EF hand motifs and its NH2-terminal myristoylation site. Although these regions are relatively well  conserved, sharing 44% overall similarity, calmyrin appears to have only two functional EF hands as the two  NH2-terminal motifs contain several insertions that are  predicted to disrupt calcium binding. Naik et al. (1997)  have demonstrated that calmyrin can indeed bind calcium,  but it is unknown whether this property regulates phosphatase activity. If calmyrin behaves similarly to calcineurin B in phosphatase regulation, it may have some  relevance to AD where there is speculation that PHF formation and tau hyperphosphorylation occurs due to misregulation of protein phosphatases or kinases (Matsuo et al.,  1994; Gong et al., 1996; Kayyali et al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>55793</offset><text>Our cell death findings imply that the binding of calmyrin to PS2 may be related to PS2 function in apoptosis.  In a previous study we found that overexpression of PS2 in  HeLa cells induced apoptosis. The current finding that coexpression of calmyrin with presenilins in HeLa cells increased apoptosis suggests that the two act in concert in a  pathway or pathways regulating cell death. Although we  have not determined the pathway through which the two  proteins function during programmed cell death, the fact  that calmyrin is a calcium-binding protein (Naik et al.,  1997) raises some obvious possibilities. First, calmyrin may  &quot;sense&quot; Ca2+ changes and subsequently regulate PS2 function. Alternatively, PS2 proteins (including FAD mutants)  may alter calcium homeostasis resulting in a change in calcium binding by calmyrin which could then trigger a signal  transduction cascade. This latter possibility is attractive  since overexpression of presenilins has been shown to  cause perturbations in calcium homeostasis (Guo et al.,  1996; Keller et al., 1998). Interestingly, the apoptosis rescue screen in which the PS2 ALG3 fragment was isolated  (see introduction) yielded another cDNA named ALG2,  which caused antisense inhibition of a calcium-binding  protein (Vito et al., 1996). However, when ALG2 was expressed in the sense orientation, this calcium-binding protein induced apoptosis (Lacana et al., 1997). It could be argued that coexpression of any calcium-binding protein  with presenilins would cause increased cell death. This is  clearly not the case as overexpression of another calcium-binding protein, calbindin D28k, suppressed the proapoptotic functions of PS (Guo et al., 1998). An imbalance in  calcium regulation could be catastrophic to the cell due to  the central role calcium plays in cellular processes including its participation in the induction phase of apoptosis  (reviewed by McConkey and Orrenius, 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57743</offset><text>Although there is some disagreement as to whether AD  involves a perturbation of calcium regulation (see Etcheberrigaray et al., 1998), the consensus of research (opinion) is indicative of such a defect. The uncertainty is in  part complicated by lack of reliable and easy methods to  measure intracellular calcium, let alone compare them in  different individuals. Nevertheless, numerous studies have  shown that calcium levels are altered in cells cultured from  AD patients, especially those harboring (or transfected  with) presenilin genes containing FAD-linked mutations  (Ito et al., 1994; Gibson et al., 1997; Mattson et al., 1998).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>58384</offset><text>In summary, our results suggest that calmyrin, a calcium-binding myristoylated protein, may play dynamic  and diverse roles in intracellular signaling, and we propose  that it is important in the modulation of presenilin function. Understanding the complex interplay between calcium regulation, apoptotic signaling, and protein-protein  interactions will no doubt aid in deciphering the mechanisms through which the presenilins function which in turn  could provide insight into the pathogenesis of Alzheimer's  disease.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>58907</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>58926</offset><text>Presenilin loop  constructs and their interaction with calmyrin. (A) The  general topology of the multiple transmembrane presenilin protein is diagrammed  and the loop region amino  acid sequence comparison  between PS1 and PS2 is provided. The first 50 amino acids of the PS2-loop designated loop B (large dashed  line), were used as the bait in  the interaction trap. In the  liquid assay binding study  loop B was further subdivided into a conserved region  (loop C, solid line) and a  more divergent region (loop  D, small dashed line). Boxes  enclose identical (dark  shade) and similar (light  shade) residues. (B and C)  Results of yeast two-hybrid  liquid assay using the baits  described in (A) are graphed  with standard errors shown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>59671</offset><text>Calmyrin amino  acid sequence and transcript  expression pattern. (A) The  complete amino acid sequence of calmyrin is shown  in comparison to human calcineurin B. The two conserved calcium-binding EF  hands are circled and the two  EF hands that are disrupted  in calmyrin are noted by a  dashed line. (B) The human  multiple tissue Northern blot  and (C) the human brain  multiple tissue Northern blot  were first probed with 32P-labeled calmyrin cDNA,  stripped, and subsequently  probed with 32P-labeled  beta-actin cDNA as a control.  The ~1.2-kb hybridization  band corresponds to the expected size for calmyrin transcript.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>60301</offset><text>Expression and purification of GST/calmyrin  protein, characterization of  anti-calmyrin antibodies, and  detection of endogenous  calmyrin protein. (A) Coomassie blue-stained gel documenting the induction and  purification of GST (lanes  1-3) and GST/calmyrin (lanes  5-7). Uninduced bacterial lysate (lanes 1 and 5), induced  lysate (lanes 2 and 6), glutathione agarose affinity-purified proteins (lanes 3 and  7), and molecular mass  markers (4) are displayed.  The purified ~45-kD GST/ calmyrin fusion protein  shown in lane 7 was inoculated into rabbits for the production of polyclonal antibodies. (B) Immunoblot of  HeLa cell lysates probed  with rabbit anti-calmyrin serum. HeLa cells were transfected with C-myc calmyrin  (lane 2), N-myc calmyrin  (lane 3), and wild-type calmyrin (lane 4), or were mock transfected (lane 1). The anti-calmyrin antibodies react with the appropriate size  polypeptides only in calmyrin transfected cells. Note the absence of nonspecific background staining and the inability to detect any endogenous calmyrin in HeLa cells at this exposure. (C) Immunoblot of human brain lysate loaded at 100 mug total protein and probed  with rabbit anti-calmyrin serum. Please note endogenous calmyrin in brain migrates as a 22-kD protein. (D) Immunoblot of various  mouse tissues loaded at 100 mug total protein and probed with anti-calmyrin to detect endogenous levels of calmyrin. (E) Immunofluorescent localization of endogenous calmyrin in mouse heart primary cell culture indicates that this protein resides in the nucleus and  throughout the cytoplasm. Bar, 5 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>61907</offset><text>Immunoprecipitation of myristoylated calmyrin and localization of calmyrin to the membrane fraction. (A) Fluorography of myristoylated proteins immunoprecipitated with rabbit  anti-calmyrin from HeLa cells after transfection with N-myc  calmyrin (lane 1 and 2), C-myc calmyrin (lane 3 and 4), or wild-type calmyrin (lane 5 and 6) and 24 h incubation with 3H-myristic  acid. The cell lysates (L) and immunoprecipitated (IP) samples  are shown. The myristoylated calmyrin band is present in lanes 4  and 6 (indicated by the arrows), but absent from lane 2. The  lower panel shows an immunoblot of the supernatants (S) and  immunoprecipitants (IP) of these same transfected cell lysates to  confirm the expression level and successful immunoprecipitation  of calmyrin. (B) Immunoblotting of calmyrin-expressing HeLa  cell lysates for lamins A and C (68 and 66 kD) and calmyrin (22  kD) after fractionation in the absence (-) of detergent (lanes 1  and 2) or in the presence (+) of 1% Triton X-100 (lane 3 and 4)  into a soluble supernatant (S) and an insoluble pellet (P). The  lower panel shows the identical fractionation of endogenous  calmyrin in mouse kidney primary cell culture.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>63092</offset><text>Immunofluorescent localization of calmyrin protein in transfected HeLa cells. (A and B) Field of two cells transfected with  wild-type calmyrin and stained with anti-calmyrin (A) and DAPI (B) reveals that the calmyrin antibody is specific since the lower-right  untransfected cell (see arrow) has a bright DAPI stained nucleus but has no fluorescein calmyrin staining. In the cell overexpressing  calmyrin, the protein localizes to the nucleus and cytoplasm. Note that within the nucleus, calmyrin accumulation closely resembles the  DAPI chromatin staining. (C) Close-up from a calmyrin-expressing cell to highlight the localization of calmyrin to the plasma membrane projections. (D) The fluorescein staining pattern of cells overexpressing C-myc calmyrin appears slightly different from (A) with  less of the protein in the nucleus. (E) Contrastingly, N-myc calmyrin protein accumulates predominantly in the nucleus and produces a  more diffuse cytoplasmic staining. (F and G) Confocal images of a cell overexpressing wild-type calmyrin and stained with anti-calmyrin  (F) and anti-lamin (G) indicate that calmyrin localization is not restricted to the nuclear envelop. (H) An example of the ER staining  pattern of overexpressed PS2 is also shown. Bar, 5 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>64356</offset><text>Immunofluorescent colocalization of calmyrin with PS2 in transfected HeLa cells. (A-C) HeLa cells cotransfected with wild-type calmyrin and full-length PS2 were stained 24 h after transfection with rabbit anti-calmyrin and goat anti-PS2 antibodies. Green  (left-hand panels) is the fluorescein labeled calmyrin, red (center panels) is the rhodamine labeled PS2, and yellow (right-hand panels)  is a merged image indicating when the fluorescein and rhodamine signals colocalize. As exemplified by the three selected cells, when coexpressed calmyrin shows a pattern of localization nearly identical to PS2. While most cotransfected cells show a staining pattern consistent with ER localization (A and B), a small subset of cells appear to colocalize calmyrin and PS2 in punctuate intranuclear aggregates  (C). (D) Similar staining of HeLa cells cotransfected with wild-type calmyrin and loop/COOH-deleted PS2 show patchy aggregates (see  arrows) of PS2 (red) which exclude calmyrin (green). Bar, 5 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>65359</offset><text>Affinity chromatography and coimmunoprecipitation  provide further evidence for binding between calmyrin and PS2.  (A) Immunoblot of PS2-expressing HeLa cell lysates (L) which  were affinity purified (AP) over GST-sepharose or GST/ calmyrin sepharose probed with goat anti-PS2. The PS2 transfected lysate (1), untransfected lysate affinity purified over GST-sepharose (2), PS2 transfected lysate affinity purified over GST-sepharose (3), and PS2 transfected lysate affinity purified over  GST/calmyrin-sepharose (4) are shown. The arrow indicates the  PS2 band which appears three-fold more intense in lane 4 than in  lane 3. (B) Fluorography of myristoylated proteins immunoprecipitated with rabbit anti-calmyrin (lanes 1 and 4), rabbit anti-PS2 (lanes 2 and 5), or rabbit preimmune serum (lanes 3 and 6)  from C-myc calmyrin and PS2 cotransfected HeLa cells incubated for 24 h with 3H-myristic acid. Supernatants (S) and immunoprecipitates (IP) are shown. Arrows indicate a more prominent myristoylated calmyrin band in lanes 4 and 5 compared with  the control lane 6.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>66430</offset><text>Immunofluorescent staining with CytoDEATH indicates that overexpression of PS2 and calmyrin increases HeLa cell apoptosis. (A) An example field of four cells shows that two of the three cells overexpressing PS2 are apoptotic according to CytoDEATH  positive staining and condensed nuclei. (B) Similarly, an example field of eight cells shows that both cells which overexpress calmyrin  also appear apoptotic. (C) 10x field of calmyrin and PS2 cotransfected cells after 16 h. Total cells in the field are indicated by DAPI  staining, expressing cells are labeled with anti-PS2 antibody (staining for the presence of PS2 and calmyrin in cotransfected cells showed  a near 1:1 correspondence between the overexpression of these two proteins), and apoptotic cells are detected with the CytoDEATH  anti-cytokeratin 18 antibody. Note the presence of &gt;30 apoptotic cells which all also stain positive for PS2 expression. (D) 10x field of  calmyrin and PS2 cotransfected cells after 40 h. Note the reduction in total cells and the lower percentage of PS2-expressing cells at this  later time point. (E) 10x field of control neurofilament-transfected cells after 40 h. Please note that even at this later time point, a high  percentage of anti-neurofilament positive cells remain, while in contrast only one CytoDEATH apoptotic cell can be detected.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>67774</offset><text>Quantification of cell death due to overexpression of  PS2 and calmyrin. Floating cells from duplicate plates of HeLa  cells transfected with a total of 15 mug of DNA containing control  vector, increasing amounts of calmyrin, increasing amounts of  PS2, or both calmyrin and PS2, were collected after 48 h. The  number of floating cells per dish exceeding the mock transfection  background counts are graphed with standard errors shown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>68212</offset><text>Abbreviations used in this paper</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68245</offset><text>AD</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68248</offset><text>Alzheimer's disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68268</offset><text>FAD</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68272</offset><text>familial AD</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68284</offset><text>MTN</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68288</offset><text>multiple tissue Northern</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68313</offset><text>NF-L</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68318</offset><text>neurofilament light</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68338</offset><text>NFT</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68342</offset><text>neurofibrillary tangles</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68366</offset><text>PS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68369</offset><text>presenilin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68380</offset><text>TMD</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68384</offset><text>transmembrane domains</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>68406</offset><text>References</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">198</infon><infon key="lpage">202</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ames;given-names:JB</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ishima;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Tanaka;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gordon;given-names:JI</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Stryer;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Ikura;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9296500</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">389</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>68417</offset><text>Molecular mechanics of calcium-myristoyl switches</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">149</infon><infon key="lpage">159</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Baumeister;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Leimer;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Zweckbronner;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Jakubek;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Grunberg;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Haass;given-names:C</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9680315</infon><infon key="source">Genes Funct</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>68467</offset><text>Human presenilin-1, but not familial Alzheimer's disease  (FAD) mutants, facilitate Caenorhabditis elegansNotch signaling independently of proteolytic processing</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">357</infon><infon key="lpage">360</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Blacker;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wilcox;given-names:MA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Laird;given-names:NM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Rodes;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Horvath;given-names:SM</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Go;given-names:RC</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Perry;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Watson;given-names:BJ</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Bassett;given-names:SS</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:McInnis;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9697696</infon><infon key="source">Nat Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>68629</offset><text>Alpha-2 macroglobulin is genetically associated with Alzheimer disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5101</infon><infon key="lpage">5107</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Busciglio;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hartmann;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lorenzo;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Wong;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Baumann;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Sommer;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Staufenbiel;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Yankner;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9185547</infon><infon key="source">J Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>68700</offset><text>Neuronal localization of presenilin-1 and association with amyloid plaques and neurofibrillary tangles in Alzheimer's disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1177</infon><infon key="lpage">1181</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Buxbaum;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Choi;given-names:E-K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Luo;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Lilliehook;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Crowley;given-names:AC</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Merriam;given-names:DE</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Wasco;given-names:W</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9771752</infon><infon key="source">Nat Med</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>68826</offset><text>Calsenilin: a calcium-binding protein that interacts with the presenilins and regulates the levels of a presenilin fragment</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2432</infon><infon key="lpage">2440</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Capell;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Saffrich;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Olivo;given-names:JC</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Meyn;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Walter;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Grunberg;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Mathews;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Nixon;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Dotti;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Haass;given-names:C</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9375676</infon><infon key="source">J Neurochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">69</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>68950</offset><text>Cellular expression and proteolytic processing of presenilin proteins is developmentally regulated during neuronal differentiation</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1379</infon><infon key="lpage">1394</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Caulin;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Salvesen;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Oshima;given-names:RG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9298992</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">138</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>69081</offset><text>Caspase cleavage of keratin 18 and reorganization of intermediate filaments during epithelial cell apoptosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">921</infon><infon key="lpage">923</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Corder;given-names:EH</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Saunders;given-names:AM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Strittmatter;given-names:WJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Schmechel;given-names:DE</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Gaskell;given-names:PC</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Small;given-names:GW</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Roses;given-names:AD</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Haines;given-names:JL</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Pericak-Vance;given-names:MA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8346443</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">261</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>69190</offset><text>Gene dose apolipoprotein E type 4 allele and the risk of Alzheimer's disease in late onset families</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">611</infon><infon key="lpage">614</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Crabtree;given-names:GR</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10089876</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">96</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>69290</offset><text>Generic signals and specific outcomes: signaling through  Ca2+, calcineurin, and NF-AT</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">183</infon><infon key="lpage">190</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cruts;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Van Broeckhoven;given-names:C</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9521418</infon><infon key="source">Hum Mutat</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>69377</offset><text>Presenilin mutations in Alzheimer's disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">603</infon><infon key="lpage">609</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Davis;given-names:JA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Naruse;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Chen;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Eckman;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Younkin;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Price;given-names:DL</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Borchelt;given-names:DR</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Sisodia;given-names:SS</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Wong;given-names:PC</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9539132</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>69421</offset><text>An Alzheimer's disease-linked PS1 variant rescues the developmental abnormalities of PS1-deficient embryos</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">387</infon><infon key="lpage">390</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:De Strooper;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Saftig;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Craessaerts;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Vanderstichele;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Guhde;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Annaert;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Von Figura;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:van Leuven;given-names:F</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9450754</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">391</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>69528</offset><text>Deficiency of presenilin-1 inhibits the normal cleavage of amyloid precursor protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">50</infon><infon key="lpage">54</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Deng;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pike;given-names:CJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cotman;given-names:CW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8941712</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">397</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>69613</offset><text>Alzheimer-associated presenilin-2 confers increased sensitivity to apoptosis in PC12 cell</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">9926</infon><infon key="lpage">9931</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Dewji;given-names:NN</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Singer;given-names:SJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9275228</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">94</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>69703</offset><text>Cell surface expression of the Alzheimer disease-related presenilin proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">37</infon><infon key="lpage">45</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Etcheberrigaray;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hirashima;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Nee;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Prince;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Govoni;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Racchi;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Tanzi;given-names:RE</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Alkon;given-names:DL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9702786</infon><infon key="source">Neurobiol Dis</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>69780</offset><text>Calcium responses in fibroblasts from asymptomatic members of Alzheimer's disease families</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">277</infon><infon key="lpage">287</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gerace;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7357605</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="year">1980</infon><offset>69871</offset><text>The nuclear envelope lamina is reversibly depolymerized during mitosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">573</infon><infon key="lpage">580</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gibson;given-names:GE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Vestling;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Zhang;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Szolosi;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Alkon;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Lannfelt;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Gandy;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Cowburn;given-names:RF</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9461055</infon><infon key="source">Neurobiol Aging</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>69942</offset><text>Abnormalities in Alzheimer's disease fibroblasts bearing the APP670/671 mutation</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Golemis, E., J. Gyuris, and R. Brent. 1996. Interaction trap/two-hybrid system  to identify interacting proteins. In Current Protocols in Molecular Biology,  R.B.F.A. Ausubel, R.E. Kingston, D.D. Moore, J.G. Seidman, J.A. Smith,  and K, Struhl, editors. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York. 20.1.1-20.1.28.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>70023</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">95</infon><infon key="lpage">102</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gong;given-names:CX</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shaikh;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Grundke-Iqbal;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Iqbal;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9001710</infon><infon key="source">Brain Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">741</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>70024</offset><text>Inhibition of protein phosphatase-2B (calcineurin) activity towards Alzheimer abnormally phosphorylated tau by neuroleptics</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">455</infon><infon key="lpage">460</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Grotewiel;given-names:MS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Beck;given-names:CD</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Wu;given-names:KH</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Zhu;given-names:XR</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Davis;given-names:RL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9461212</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">391</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>70148</offset><text>Integrin-mediated short-term memory in Drosophila. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">271</infon><infon key="lpage">275</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Guerini;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9199180</infon><infon key="source">Biochem  Biophys Res Commun</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">235</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>70200</offset><text>Calcineurin: not just a simple protein phosphatase</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3227</infon><infon key="lpage">3232</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Guo;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Christakos;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Robinson;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Mattson;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9501245</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">95</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>70251</offset><text>Calbindin D28k blocks the proapoptotic actions of mutant presenilin 1: reduced oxidative stress and preserved mitochondrial function</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">379</infon><infon key="lpage">383</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Guo;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Furukawa;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sopher;given-names:BL</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Pham;given-names:DG</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Xie;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Robinson;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Martin;given-names:GM</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Mattson;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9051814</infon><infon key="source">Neuroreport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>70384</offset><text>Alzheimer's PS-1 mutation perturbs calcium homeostasis and sensitizes PC12 cells to death induced by amyloid beta-peptide</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4212</infon><infon key="lpage">4222</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Guo;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sopher;given-names:BL</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Furukawa;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Pham;given-names:DG</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Robinson;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Martin;given-names:GM</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Mattson;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9151738</infon><infon key="source">J Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>70506</offset><text>Alzheimer's presenilin mutation sensitizes neural cells to apoptosis induced by trophic factor withdrawal and amyloid beta-peptide: involvement of calcium and oxyradicals</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">687</infon><infon key="lpage">690</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Haass;given-names:C</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9182794</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>70677</offset><text>Presenilins: genes for life and death</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">155</infon><infon key="lpage">159</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hardy;given-names:J</infon><infon key="source">Trends Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>70715</offset><text>Amyloid, the presenilins and Alzheimer's disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">534</infon><infon key="lpage">538</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ito;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Oka;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Etcheberrigaray;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Nelson;given-names:TJ</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:McPhie;given-names:DL</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Tofel-Grehl;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Gibson;given-names:GE</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Alkon;given-names:DL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8290560</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci  USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>70764</offset><text>Internal Ca2+mobilization is altered in fibroblasts from patients with Alzheimer disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">485</infon><infon key="lpage">495</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Janicki;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Monteiro;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9334350</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">139</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>70853</offset><text>Increased apoptosis arising from increased expression of the Alzheimer's disease-associated presenilin-2 mutation (N141I)</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1668</infon><infon key="lpage">1678</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kayyali;given-names:US</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zhang;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Yee;given-names:AG</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Seidman;given-names:JG</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Potter;given-names:H</infon><infon key="source">Neurochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">68</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>70975</offset><text>Cytoskeletal changes in the brains of mice lacking calcineurin A alpha. J</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4439</infon><infon key="lpage">4450</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Keller;given-names:JN</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Guo;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Holtsberg;given-names:FW</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Bruce-Keller;given-names:AJ</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Mattson;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9614221</infon><infon key="source">J Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>71049</offset><text>Increased sensitivity to mitochondrial toxin-induced apoptosis in neural cells expressing mutant presenilin-1 is linked to perturbed calcium homeostasis and enhanced oxyradical production</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">26517</infon><infon key="lpage">26521</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kennedy;given-names:MT</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Brockman;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Rusnak;given-names:F</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8900120</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71237</offset><text>Contributions of myristoylation to calcineurin structure/function</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">373</infon><infon key="lpage">376</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kim;given-names:TW</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pettingell;given-names:WH</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Jung;given-names:YK</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kovacs;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Tanzi;given-names:RE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9219695</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>71303</offset><text>Alternative cleavage of Alzheimer-associated presenilins during apoptosis by a caspase-3 family protease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">224</infon><infon key="lpage">229</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kovacs;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Fausett;given-names:HJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Page;given-names:KJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kim;given-names:T-W</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Moir;given-names:RD</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Merriam;given-names:DE</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Hollister;given-names:RD</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Hallmark;given-names:OG</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Mancini;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Felsenstein;given-names:KM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8574969</infon><infon key="source">Nat Med</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">2</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71408</offset><text>Alzheimer-associated presenilins 1 and 2: neuronal expression in brain and localization to intracellular membranes in mammalian cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5129</infon><infon key="lpage">5135</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lacana;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ganjei;given-names:JK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Vito;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:D'Adamio;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9164928</infon><infon key="source">J Immunol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">158</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>71542</offset><text>Dissociation of apoptosis and activation of IL-1beta-converting enzyme/Ced-3 proteases by ALG-2 and the truncated Alzheimer's gene ALG-3</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1337</infon><infon key="lpage">1350</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lee;given-names:MK</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Xu;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Wong;given-names:PC</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Cleveland;given-names:DW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8376466</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">122</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>71679</offset><text>Neurofilaments are obligate heteropolymers in vivo</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">14940</infon><infon key="lpage">14944</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Levitan;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Doyle;given-names:TG</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Brousseau;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Lee;given-names:MK</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Thinakaran;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Slunt;given-names:HH</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Sisodia;given-names:SS</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Greenwald;given-names:I</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8962160</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci  USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">93</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71730</offset><text>Assessment of normal and mutant human presenilin function in Caenorhabditis elegans. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">351</infon><infon key="lpage">354</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Levitan;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Greenwald;given-names:I</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7566091</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">377</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>71816</offset><text>Facilitation of lin-12-mediated signaling  by sel-12, a Caenorhabdits elegansS182 Alzheimer's disease gene</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">917</infon><infon key="lpage">927</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Li;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Xu;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Zhou;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ma;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Potter;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9298903</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">90</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>71923</offset><text>Alzheimer presenilins in the nuclear membrane, interphase kinetochores, and centrosomes suggest a role in chromosome segregation</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">20655</infon><infon key="lpage">20659</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Loetscher;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Deuschle;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Brockhaus;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Reinhardt;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Nelboeck;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Mous;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Grunberg;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Haass;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Jacobsen;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9252383</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>72052</offset><text>Presenilins are processed by caspase-type proteases</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">989</infon><infon key="lpage">1002</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Matsuo;given-names:ES</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shin;given-names:RW</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Billingsley;given-names:ML</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Van deVoorde;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:O'Connor;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Trojanowski;given-names:JQ</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Lee;given-names:VM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7946342</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>72104</offset><text>Biopsy-derived adult human brain tau is phosphorylated at many of the same sites as Alzheimer's disease paired helical filament tau</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="lpage">14</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Mattson;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Guo;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Furukawa;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Pedersen;given-names:WA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9422341</infon><infon key="source">J Neurochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">70</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>72236</offset><text>Presenilins, the endoplasmic reticulum, and neuronal apoptosis in Alzheimer's disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">357</infon><infon key="lpage">366</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:McConkey;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Orrenius;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9344835</infon><infon key="source">Biochem Biophys Res Commun</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">239</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>72322</offset><text>The role of calcium in the regulation of apoptosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">325</infon><infon key="lpage">330</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:McConnell;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Dynan;given-names:WS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8743882</infon><infon key="source">Curr Opin Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>72373</offset><text>The DNA-dependent protein kinase: a matter of life and (cell) death</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3471</infon><infon key="lpage">3485</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Mical;given-names:TI</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Monteiro;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9811562</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">111</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>72441</offset><text>The role of sequences unique to nuclear intermediate filaments in the targeting and assembly of human lamin B: evidence for lack of interaction of lamin B with its putative receptor</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1327</infon><infon key="lpage">1343</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Monteiro;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hicks;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gu;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Janicki;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7962093</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">127</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>72623</offset><text>Determinants for intracellular sorting of cytoplasmic and nuclear intermediate filaments</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">443</infon><infon key="lpage">451</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Monteiro;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mical;given-names:T</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8601422</infon><infon key="source">Exp Cell Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">223</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>72712</offset><text>Resolution of kinase activities during the HeLa cell cycle: Identification of kinases with cyclic activities</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">211</infon><infon key="lpage">212</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Montoya;given-names:SE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Aston;given-names:CE</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:DeKosky;given-names:ST</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ilyas;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kamboh</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Lazo;given-names:JS</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Ferrell;given-names:RE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9500538</infon><infon key="source">Nat Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>72821</offset><text>Bleomycin hydrolase is associated with risk of sporadic Alzheimer's disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">73</infon><infon key="lpage">77</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Murayama;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tanaka;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Palacino;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Murayama;given-names:O</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Honda;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Sun;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Yasutake;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Nihonmatsu;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Wolozin;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Takashima;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9738936</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">433</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>72897</offset><text>Direct association of presenilin-1 with beta-catenin</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4651</infon><infon key="lpage">4654</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Naik;given-names:UP</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Patel;given-names:PM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Parise;given-names:LV</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9030514</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>72950</offset><text>Identification of a novel calcium-binding protein that interacts with the integrin alphaIIb cytoplasmic domain</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">14327</infon><infon key="lpage">14333</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Olshevskaya;given-names:EV</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hughes;given-names:RE</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hurley;given-names:JB</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Dizhoor;given-names:AM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9162068</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>73061</offset><text>Calcium binding, but not a calcium-myristoyl switch, controls the ability of guanylyl cyclase-activating protein GCAP-2 to regulate photoreceptor guanylyl cyclase</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Payami, H., G.D. Schellenberg, S. Zareparsi, J. Kaye, G.J. Sexton, M.A. Head,  S.S. Matsuyama, L.F. Jarvik, B. Miller, D.Q. McManus, et al. 1997. Evidence  for association of HLA-A2 allele with onset age of Alzheimer's disease.  Neurology. 49, 512-518.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>73224</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1237</infon><infon key="lpage">1241</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pericak-Vance;given-names:MA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bass;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Yammaoka;given-names:LH</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gaskell;given-names:PC</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Scott;given-names:WK</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Terwedow;given-names:HA</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Menold;given-names:MM</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Conneally;given-names:PM</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Small;given-names:GW</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Vance;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9333264</infon><infon key="source">JAMA (J Am Med Assoc)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">278</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>73225</offset><text>Complete genomic screen in late-onset familial Alzheimer disease. Evidence for a new locus on chromosome 12</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">297</infon><infon key="lpage">301</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Peruz-Tur;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Froelich;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Prihar;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Crook;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Baker;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Duff;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Wragg;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Busfield;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Lendon;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Clark;given-names:RF</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8742474</infon><infon key="source">Neuroreport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>73333</offset><text>A mutation in Alzheimer's disease destroying a splice acceptor site in the presenilin-1 gene</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">611</infon><infon key="lpage">617</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Qian;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Jiang;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Guan;given-names:XM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Singh;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Trumbauer;given-names:ME</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Yu;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Chen;given-names:HY</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Van de Ploeg;given-names:LH</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Zheng;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9539133</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>73426</offset><text>Mutant human presenilin 1 protects presenilin 1 null mouse against embryonic lethality and elevates Abeta1-42/ 43 expression</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Reynolds, A., and V. Lundblad. 1989. Yeast vectors and assays for expression  of cloned genes. In Current Protocols in Molecular Biology, R.B.F.A.  Ausubel, R.E. Kingston, D.D. Moore, J.G. Seidman, J.A. Smith, K. Struhl,  editors. John Wiley &amp; Sons, New York. 13.6.1-13.6.4.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>73551</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">315</infon><infon key="lpage">317</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Saito;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Seki;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hattori;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Hayashi;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Abe;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Araki;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Fujimori;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Fukumura;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Kozuma;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Matsuda;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10051332</infon><infon key="source">Mamm Genome</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>73552</offset><text>Structure, expression profile, and chromosomal location of a mouse gene homologous to human DNA-PKcs interacting protein (KIP) gene</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">629</infon><infon key="lpage">639</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Shen;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bronson;given-names:RT</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Chen;given-names:DF</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Xia;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Selkoe;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Tonegawa;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9160754</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">89</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>73684</offset><text>Skeletal and CNS defects in presenilin-1-deficient mice</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">325</infon><infon key="lpage">334</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Shieh;given-names:S-H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ikeda;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Taya;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Prives;given-names:C</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9363941</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>73740</offset><text>DNA damage-induced phosphorylation of p53 alleviates inhibition by mdm2</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">797</infon><infon key="lpage">799</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Shinozaki;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Maruyama;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kume;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Tomita;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Saido;given-names:TC</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Iwatsubo;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Obata;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9852298</infon><infon key="source">Int J Mol Med</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>73812</offset><text>The presenilin 2 loop domain interacts with the mu-calpain COOH-terminal region</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">16281</infon><infon key="lpage">16288</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Smine;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Xu;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_10">surname:Okamoto;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Nishiyama;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Katada;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Gambetti;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Yadav;given-names:SP</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Wu;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Shi;given-names:YC</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Yasuhara;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Homburger;given-names:V</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9632688</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">273</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>73892</offset><text>Regulation of brain G-protein Go by Alzheimer's disease gene presenilin-1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">9141</infon><infon key="lpage">9148</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Stahl;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Diehlmann;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sudhof;given-names:TC</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10092585</infon><infon key="source">J Biol  Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>73966</offset><text>Direct interaction of Alzheimer's disease-related presenilin 1 with armadillo protein p0071</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">522</infon><infon key="lpage">525</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Struhl;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Greenwald;given-names:I</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10206646</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">398</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>74058</offset><text>Presenilin is required for activity and nuclear access of Notch in Drosophila. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">563</infon><infon key="lpage">568</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Tanahashi;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tabira;given-names:T</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10208590</infon><infon key="source">Neuroreport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>74138</offset><text>Isolation of human delta-catenin and its binding specificity with presenilin 1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">444</infon><infon key="lpage">447</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Tanaka;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ames;given-names:JB</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Harvey;given-names:TS</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Stryer;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ikura;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7630423</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">376</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>74217</offset><text>Sequestration of the membrane-targeting myristoyl group of recoverin in the calcium-free state</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">181</infon><infon key="lpage">190</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Thinakaran;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Borchelt;given-names:DR</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lee;given-names:MK</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Slunt;given-names:HH</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Spitzer;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Kim;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Ratovitsky;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Davenport;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Nordstedt;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Seeger;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8755489</infon><infon key="source">Neuron</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>74312</offset><text>Endoproteolysis of presenilin 1 and accumulation of processed derivatives in vivo</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">521</infon><infon key="lpage">525</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vito;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lacana;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:D'Adamio;given-names:LD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8560270</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996a</infon><offset>74394</offset><text>Interfering with apoptosis: Ca2+-binding protein ALG-2 and Alzheimer's disease gene ALG-3</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">31025</infon><infon key="lpage">31028</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vito;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wolozin;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ganjei;given-names:JK</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Iwasaki;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lacana;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:D'Adamio;given-names:LD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8940094</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996b</infon><offset>74484</offset><text>Requirement of the familial Alzheimer's disease gene PS2 for apoptosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">339</infon><infon key="lpage">343</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wang;given-names:HG</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pathan;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ethell;given-names:IM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Krajewski;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Yamaguchi;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Shibasaki;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:McKeon;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Bobo;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Franke;given-names:TF</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Reed;given-names:JC</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10195903</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">284</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>74555</offset><text>Ca2+-induced apoptosis through calcineurin dephosphorylation of BAD</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1275</infon><infon key="lpage">1278</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wilcox;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hu;given-names:JS</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Olson;given-names:EN</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3685978</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">238</infon><infon key="year">1987</infon><offset>74623</offset><text>Acylation of proteins with myristic acid occurs cotranslationally</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">S23</infon><infon key="lpage">S27</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wolozin;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Alexander;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Palacino;given-names:J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9562463</infon><infon key="source">Neurobiol Aging</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>74689</offset><text>Regulation of apoptosis by presenilin 1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1710</infon><infon key="lpage">1713</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wolozin;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Iwasaki;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Vito;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ganjei;given-names:JK</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lacana;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Sunderland;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Zhao;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Kusiak;given-names:JW</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Wasco;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:D'Adamio;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8939861</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>74729</offset><text>Participation of presenilin 2 in apoptosis: enhanced basal activity conferred by an Alzheimer mutation</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">288</infon><infon key="lpage">292</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wong;given-names:PC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zeng;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Chen;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Becher;given-names:MW</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Sirinathsinghji;given-names:DJS</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Trumbauer;given-names:ME</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Chen;given-names:HY</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Price;given-names:DL</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Van der Ploeg;given-names:LHT</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Sisodia;given-names:SS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9153393</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">387</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>74832</offset><text>Presenilin 1 is required for Notch1 and Dll1 expression in the paraxial mesoderm</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">13</infon><infon key="lpage">20</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wu;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lieber;given-names:MR</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9372844</infon><infon key="source">Mutat Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">385</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>74913</offset><text>Interaction between DNA-dependent protein kinase and a novel protein, KIP</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">199</infon><infon key="lpage">211</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ye;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Fortini;given-names:ME</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10349633</infon><infon key="source">Mech Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">79</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>74987</offset><text>Characterization of DrosophilaPresenilin and its colocalization with Notch during development</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">525</infon><infon key="lpage">529</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ye;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lukinova;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Fortini;given-names:ME</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10206647</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">398</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>75081</offset><text>Neurogenic phenotypes and altered Notch processing in DrosophilaPresenilin mutants</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">914</infon><infon key="lpage">922</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zhang;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Han;given-names:SW</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:McKeel;given-names:DW</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Goate;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Wu;given-names:JY</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9437013</infon><infon key="source">J Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>75164</offset><text>Interaction of presenilins with the filamin family of actin-binding proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">698</infon><infon key="lpage">702</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zhang;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hartmann;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_10">surname:De  Strooper;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_11">surname:He;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_12">surname:Yankner;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Do;given-names:VM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Abramowski;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Sturchler-Pierrat;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Staufenbiel;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Sommer;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:van de Wetering;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Clevers;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Saftig;given-names:P</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9790190</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">395</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>75241</offset><text>Destabilization of beta-catenin by mutations in presenilin-1 potentiates neuronal apoptosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2085</infon><infon key="lpage">2090</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zhou;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Liyanage;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Medina;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ho;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Simmons;given-names:AD</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Lovett;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Kosik;given-names:KS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9223106</infon><infon key="source">Neuroreport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>75331</offset><text>Presenilin 1 interaction in the brain with a novel member of the  Armadillofamily</text></passage></document></collection>
