<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>sentence.key</key><document><id>z</id><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Hottiger;given-names:Michael</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Rowe;given-names:Martin</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hasan;given-names:Sameez</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">11967287</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Subramanian;given-names:Chitra</infon><infon key="fpage">4699</infon><infon key="issue">10</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc"></infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">0140</infon><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1128/JVI.76.10.4699-4708.2002</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">76</infon><infon key="journal-title">Journal of Virology</infon><infon key="lpage">4708</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Robertson;given-names:Erle S.</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Orre;given-names:Rama</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Epstein-Barr Virus Nuclear Antigen 3C and Prothymosin Alpha Interact with the p300 Transcriptional Coactivator at the CH1 and CH3/HAT Domains and Cooperate in Regulation of Transcription and Histone Acetylation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>211</offset><text>The Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C (EBNA3C), encoded by Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), is essential for mediating transformation of human B lymphocytes. Previous studies demonstrated that EBNA3C interacts with a small, nonhistone, highly acidic, high-mobility group-like nuclear protein prothymosin alpha (ProTalpha) and the transcriptional coactivator p300 in complexes from EBV-infected cells. These complexes were shown to be associated with histone acetyltransferase (HAT) activity in that they were able to acetylate crude histones in vitro. In this report we show that ProTalpha interacts with p300 similarly to p53 and other known oncoproteins at the CH1 amino-terminal domain as well as at a second domain downstream of the bromodomain which includes the CH3 region and HAT domain. Similarly, EBNA3C also interacts with p300 at regions which include the CH1 and CH3/HAT domains, suggesting that ProTalpha and EBNAC3C may interact in a complex with p300. We also show that ProTalpha activates transcription when targeted to promoters by fusion to the GAL4 DNA binding domain and that this activation is enhanced by the addition of an exogenous source of p300 under the control of a heterologous promoter. This overall activity is down-modulated in the presence of EBNA3C. These results further establish the interaction of cellular coactivator p300 with ProTalpha and demonstrate that the associated activities resulting from this interaction, which plays a role in acetylation of histones and coactivation, can be regulated by EBNA3C. Furthermore, this study establishes for the first time a transcriptional role for ProTalpha in recruitment or stabilization of coactivator p300, as well as other basal transcription factors, at the nucleosomes for regulation of transcription.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1981</offset><text>Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) is a lymphotropic virus associated with numerous human cancers including Burkitt's lymphoma, nasopharyngeal carcinoma, gastric carcinoma, and, more controversially, breast carcinoma (4, 21, 24, 32, 45). EBV belongs to the Gammaherpesvirinae subfamily of viruses, all having similar colinear genomic organizations (24). Genetic analysis of the EBV genome has demonstrated that EBV nuclear antigen 3C (EBNA3C; also referred to as EBNA6) is critical for EBV-mediated immortalization of human primary B lymphocytes. Introduction of a stop codon inserted at position 365 of the open reading frame of EBNA3C rendered the recombinant EBV transformation incompetent (24, 34, 40). Biochemical studies have now linked the role of EBNA3C to regulation of transcription through down-modulation of EBNA2-mediated transactivation (35, 36). EBNA2 is tethered to the major EBV latent promoters through RBP-Jkappa, a known cellular transcription repressor (18, 25, 47). EBNA3C disrupts RBP-Jkappa binding to its cognate sequence by competing with EBNA2 for binding, thereby regulating the interaction of EBNA2 with RBP-Jkappa (28, 33, 35, 36). EBNA3C is a large transcription factor encoded by EBV which belongs to a family of proteins transcribed about 110 kb from the major latent promoter (24, 37). EBNA3C is similar to the c-Jun and c-Fos transcription factors, with leucine zipper domains, acid-rich regions, and glutamine-rich domains. These molecules are known to be involved in transcription activation and contain nuclear localization signals important for mediating translocation to the nucleus (43) (Fig. 1). These domains are known to be involved in the repression and activation activities associated with EBNA3C (3, 28, 33, 46).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3723</offset><text>Previous studies have demonstrated that, when tethered to promoters through fusions of specific domains in frame to the GAL4 DNA binding domain, EBNA3C contains two domains with potential for repression of transcription (3). Additionally, the glutamine-rich domain was shown to be capable of activating transcription through EBV latent promoters (28). Recent experiments have shown that the activation functions of EBNA3C are linked through its interactions with transcription factors SpiA and SpiB, which bind to the cognate sequences on the latent membrane protein 1 (LMP1) major latent promoter (46).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4327</offset><text>Studies with Raji cells, which contain an EBV genome with a deletion in the EBNA3C open reading frame, indicated that EBNA3C expression in these cells could reverse the block of these cells at the G0/G1 transition point of the cell cycle (2). LMP1 levels in these cells were also increased, suggesting that EBNA3C enhances transcription of LMP1 (1). Additionally, in vitro binding assays have demonstrated that EBNA3C can interact with the retinoblastoma protein (Rb) (2). Studies so far have not demonstrated this interaction in cells expressing these proteins under the control of heterologous promoters or in EBV-infected cells. However, the interaction data are intriguing, and further studies will be crucial for delineating the ability of EBNA3C to interact with Rb. Other studies have shown that the repression function of EBNA3C is associated with its ability to complex with histone deacetylase 1 in deacetylating histones (31).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5265</offset><text>Prothymosin alpha (ProTalpha) is a small, acid-rich, nonhistone nuclear protein, which was shown to be highly up-regulated in cells where the c-myc oncogene, induced under the control of a regulatable heterologous promoter (11, 16, 17). Moreover, ProTalpha is capable of transforming Rat-1 cells in culture, inducing the formation of foci in monolayers and foci in soft-agar assays (30). ProTalpha localizes to regions of the nucleus actively involved in transcription and associates with cellular histones, including nucleosome linker protein histone H1 (23, 41, 42). Moreover, ProTalpha removes histone H1 from the nucleosomes, which allows access to micrococcal nuclease (23). These activities suggest that ProTalpha may be similar to the human high-mobility group (HMG) proteins and that it may be HMG-like in its functions in the nucleus (5, 6, 8, 9, 23). Additionally, ProTalpha was shown to be associated with PML and cleavage bodies associated with gene regulation and transcriptional activities in the nucleus (41). These studies suggest that ProTalpha is involved in chromatin unwinding and remolding to allow access to transcription or replication factors. Recent studies in our laboratory have shown that ProTalpha also interacts with acetyltransferase p300 and that it is involved in regulating the acetylation of core histones through interactions with the p300 acetyltransferase (7). This interaction and the resulting acetylation activity are further regulated by the interaction of these complexes with EBNA3C, as EBNA3C interacts with both p300 and ProTalpha (7). It is possible that these interactions form part of a larger mega-activation complex involved in regulating chromatin remodeling.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6950</offset><text>Studies investigating the role of EBNA3C in regulating transcription have demonstrated that EBNA3C is involved with acetylases as well as deacetylases (31). These studies have also demonstrated the direct interaction of EBNA3C with these cellular targets, which results in acetylation or deacetylation of core histones (7, 31, 35). Therefore EBNA3C is capable of regulating cellular events requiring acetylation or deacetylation of the core histones localized to promoters of specific viral and cellular genes potentially involved in regulation of cell cycle events.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7517</offset><text>In this study we show that the interaction of ProTalpha and EBNA3C with p300 occurs at two distinct regions, the CH1 region and a region downstream of the bromodomain, which includes the CH3/HAT domain. These interactions are similar to the interactions of p53 with p300. The affinity for the amino-terminal CH1 domain of p300 is less than that seen with the CH3/HAT domain. Moreover, we show that the interactions of ProTalpha with EBNA3C are downstream of amino acid (aa) 365, a region potentially important for EBV-mediated transformation of human primary B lymphocytes. Additionally, p300 interacts with EBNA3C at the amino-terminal 207 aa, which includes the RBP-Jkappa binding site and the leucine zipper motif, and at the carboxy terminus, which includes the proline-rich and glutamine-rich domain, which is known to be involved in transcriptional activation. We also show that ProTalpha can activate transcription when tethered to its promoter by fusing the entire ProTalpha cDNA (encoding 112 aa) to the GAL4 DNA binding domain and testing its activity on a multimerized GAL4-responsive reporter construct. Additionally, we have shown that p300 enhances the transcriptional activity mediated by ProTalpha on this GAL4-targeted promoter, indicating that ProTalpha complexed with p300 can functionally increase the activity of the basal transcriptional machinery. Moreover, EBNA3C modulates this effect on transcription and on HAT activity, demonstrating that in this context EBNA3C regulates the activity of ProTalpha and p300.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>9029</offset><text>MATERIALS AND METHODS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>9051</offset><text>Cell lines.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9063</offset><text>Burkitt's lymphoma-derived cell line BJAB was obtained from Elliott Kieff and was cultured in RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco-BRL, Gaithersburg, Md.) supplemented with 5 mug of penicillin/ml, 5 U of streptomycin/ml, and 10% fetal bovine serum purchased from Gibco-BRL. Human embryonic kidney (HEK) fibroblast cell line 293 was also obtained from Elliott Kieff and was grown in Dulbecco modified Eagle medium (Gibco-BRL) supplemented as described above.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>9508</offset><text>Plasmids.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9518</offset><text>The p300 expression construct was a generous gift from Gary Nabel (12, 20). All glutathione S-transferase (GST)-p300 constructs were made by fusing the specific regions to the GST prokaryotic vector and are described below. The coding sequences for p300 fragments P1 to P5, corresponding to aa 1 to 672, 672 to 1193, 1069 to 1459, 1459 to 1892, and 1893 to 2414, respectively, were amplified by PCR and cloned into pGex6P2 (Clontech). The primers used were 5'-TAGCTAGCTCGAGGAATGGCCGAGAATGTGGTGGAACC-3' and 5'-ATCGATCAAGCTTTTACCCTGGATTCATGGAAACTGGAACC-3' for GST-p300-1, 5'-TAGCTAGCTCGAGGAGGGCCTAACATGGGACAGCCGC-3' and 5'-ATCGATCAAGCTTTTAACTGTAATAAGTGGCATCACGAGG-3' for GST-p300-2, 5'-TAGCTAGCTCGAGGAGATCCAGAATCCCTTCCCTTTCG-3' and 5'-ATCGATCAAGCTTTTACTTGGGTATCTTCTGGTCAGGAG-3' for GST-p300-3, 5'-TAGCTAGCTCGAGGAAAGCCCAAGCGACTGCAGGAATG-3' and 5'-ATCGATCAAGCTTTTAAGCTTGAGTCCTGGGCAAGTAGG-3' for GST-p300-4, and 5'-TAGCTAGCTCGAGGAGCTGCTGGCCCTGTGTCCCAG-3' and 5'-ATCGATCAAGCTTTTACTAGTGTATGTCTAGTGTACTCTGTG-3' for GST-p300-5. The coding sequence for GST-p300-HAT (aa 1197 to 1674) was amplified by PCR and cloned into pGex6P2. The primers used were 5'-CTCGATCGTCGACAGGTATCATTTCTGTGAGAAGTG-3' and 5'-GATCGAGGTCGACTCACTTGCATTCATTGCAGGTGTAG-3'.</text><annotation id="0"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0096</infon><location offset="9594" length="147"/><text>All glutathione S-transferase (GST)-p300 constructs were made by fusing the specific regions to the GST prokaryotic vector and are described below.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10801</offset><text>The full-length EBNA3C construct was described previously (35, 37). Truncated versions of EBNA3C, made with pSG5 under the control of the simian virus 40 promoter, including those in which the arginine-rich region was deleted, the leucine zipper region was deleted, the amino terminus 365 aa were deleted, and the carboxy terminus from aa 366 to 992 was deleted. The truncated EBNA3C with the leucine zipper deletion was constructed by deleting the region corresponding to bp 99061 to 99548 (aa 207 to 368), which includes the basic region. This deletion was created by digesting the EBNA3C pBluescript clone with an HpaI-SpeI fragment, blunting with mung bean nuclease, and religating the fragments. The deletion of the arginine-rich region corresponding to bp 98402 to 99062 (aa 12 to 207) involved deletion of the polyarginine motif and was performed by digesting the EBNA3C coding fragment with XbaI, end filling the fragment with Klenow fragments, digesting the fragment with HpaI, and religating the fragment and vector. EBNA3C Delta5' construct is truncated at the 5' end up to EBV bp 99537 with the first in frame codon. This clone was created by digestion with SpeI and religation of the largest fragment. The EBNA3C Delta3' SpeI construct has a truncation at the 3' end from bp 99537 (corresponding to amino acid 368) and was created by digestion of the EBNA3C pBS clone with SpeI and religation of the largest fragment. The EBNA3C Delta3' HpaI construct has a truncated 3' end from EBV bp 99061 (corresponding to amino acid 207) and was created by digesting the EBNA3C cDNA clone with HpaI and HindIII, end filling with Klenow fragments, and ligating the largest fragment.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12488</offset><text>The GAL4-ProTalpha construct was made by fusing the ProTalpha cDNA amplified by Vent polymerase into the pM-GAL4 expression plasmid. Sense and antisense primers were purchased from Gibco-BRL. Sense primer 5'-GAAGGATCCATGTCAGACGCAGCCGTAGAC-3' and antisense primer 5'-AGCGATATCCTAGTCATCCTCGTCGGTCTT-3' contained BamHI and EcoRV restriction sites, respectively. ProTalpha was amplified from the cDNA clone in pA3M vector with Vent polymerase from New England Biolabs (Beverley, Mass.), digested with BamHI and EcoRV, and ligated into the pM vector prepared by digestion with HindIII, blunting with T4 polymerase, and further digestion with BamHI. The cloned product was sequenced with the Thermocycle Sequenase sequencing system (Amersham Inc.).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13230</offset><text>Preparation of GST fusion proteins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13266</offset><text>GST fusions were prepared as described previously (7). Briefly, TP10 cells were transformed with the plasmid constructs for each fusion, and single colonies were selected and grown in Luria-Bertani (LB) medium with 100 mug of ampicillin/ml. Five hundred milliliters of LB medium was inoculated at a dilution of 1:200 and allowed to shake at 30 C until mid-exponential growth phase. Cells were then induced with 1 mM IPTG (isopropyl-beta-d-thiogalactopyranoside) for 12 h with continuous shaking. Cells were harvested and sonicated, and the proteins were solubilized in the presence of protease inhibitors. Solubilized proteins were incubated with GST-Sepharose beads for 4 h at 4 C with rotation and then collected by centrifugation and washed three times in NETN buffer with protease inhibitors (7). GST fusion proteins bound to beads were used for binding assays and stored in NETN buffer with protease inhibitors and 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride at 4 C.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>14230</offset><text>In vitro binding assays.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14255</offset><text>To determine binding of GST-p300 fusions to EBNA3C and ProTalpha, proteins were translated in vitro with [S35]Met-Cys translabel from NEN-Dupont by using the TNT system (Promega Inc.) in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, labeled EBNA3C and ProTalpha proteins were incubated with equivalent amounts of GST-p300 fusions bound to beads and rotated at 4 C for 4 h, followed by four washings in 1 ml of NETN with protease inhibitors. Bound proteins were eluted from the beads in sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) lysis buffer by heating at 95 C for 10 min and then fractionated by SDS-10% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. All binding experiments were done essentially as previously described (39).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14966</offset><text>For competition assays in vitro-translated ProTalpha or EBNA3C was incubated with a GST-p300 fusion protein for 1 h at 4 C and placed on ice and increasing amounts of EBNA3C or ProTalpha were added to the reaction mixtures. The reaction was then allowed to proceed for an additional 2 h, and then the bound products were collected by cenrifugation, washed four times in binding buffer, solubilized in SDS lysis buffer, dried, and electrophoresed on an SDS-15 or 8% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis system. Dried gels were analyzed with a PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics Inc.), and signals were quantified with ImageQuant software.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>15597</offset><text>Transfections and luciferase assays.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15634</offset><text>Ten million 293 cells were transfected with the pFr-GAL4-luciferase reporter, the pM-GAL4 DNA binding domain fusion protein, or the pM-GAL4-ProTalpha fusion protein expression plasmid. Mock transfection (no DNA) was used as a control, using a Bio-Rad electroporation apparatus at 210 V and 975 muF. Cells were resuspended in 10 ml of Dulbecco modified Eagle medium prepared as described above. Cells were washed once in 1x phosphate-buffered saline (PBS). All transfections were balanced for amounts of DNA and normalized for transfection efficiency. Increasing amounts of pM-GAL4-ProTalpha, from 5 to 20 mug in 5-mug increments, were added. Alternatively, increasing amounts of p300- and EBNA3C-expressing plasmids were added to the pM-GAL4-ProTalpha reaction to determine the effects on the GAL4-responsive luciferase reporter. All transfectants were incubated for 20 h, harvested, washed in 10 ml of PBS, and then resuspended in reporter lysis buffer and counted in a luminometer (MGM Instruments Inc.). All transfections were performed three times, and the means were plotted.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16707</offset><text>In vivo HAT assay.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16726</offset><text>Immunoprecipitates were collected with antibodies to ProTalpha or to the region of p300 encoded by the 5' region of p300 from lysates of EBV-infected LCLs (LCL1 and LCL2) and B cells expressing EBNA3C or no EBNA as a control. For transient transfections BJAB cells were transfected at 210 V and 960 muF with a Bio-Rad electroporator. Expression constructs containing EBNA2 or EBNA3C were mixed with BJAB cells, electroporated, and then incubated for 24 h. Cells were collected by centrifugation and lysed in radioimmunoprecipitation assay (RIPA) buffer. Protein complexes containing acetylases were obtained by immunoprecipitation with polyclonal antibodies against the 5' region of p300 or ProTalpha. Immunoprecipitates were washed twice in RIPA buffer (same as that used above except that it contained 0.5% Nonidet P-40) and then twice in histone acetyltransferase (HAT) assay buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl [pH 8.0], 10 mM sodium butyrate, 10% glycerol, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride). Immunoprecipitates were incubated in HAT buffer with 25 mug of crude histones (Sigma) and 500 nCi of [3H]coenzyme A for 1 h at 30 C. After brief centrifugation to pellet protein A-Sepharose beads, the supernatant was spotted onto p-81 filters (Whatman) and washed in 0.2 M sodium carbonate three times by using vacuum filtration. Filters were allowed to dry under a heat lamp before being placed in ScintiVerse scintillation cocktail and counted in a Beckman LS3801 scintillation counter.</text><annotation id="1"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="16726" length="225"/><text>Immunoprecipitates were collected with antibodies to ProTalpha or to the region of p300 encoded by the 5' region of p300 from lysates of EBV-infected LCLs (LCL1 and LCL2) and B cells expressing EBNA3C or no EBNA as a control.</text></annotation><annotation id="2"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="17280" length="147"/><text>Protein complexes containing acetylases were obtained by immunoprecipitation with polyclonal antibodies against the 5' region of p300 or ProTalpha.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>18221</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18229</offset><text>ProTalpha activates transcription when targeted to a GAL4-responsive promoter.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18305</offset><text>To determine if ProTalpha can affect the transcriptional activity of the basal transcription machinery, we cloned ProTalpha in frame with the GAL4 DNA binding domain as a fusion and tested its ability to influence transcription. HEK 293 cells were transfected with a GAL4-responsive luciferase reporter alone or in the presence of GAL4-ProTalpha. The transfections were incubated for 24 h then harvested. The harvested cells were lysed, and the cell lysate was clarified by centrifugation. Twenty-microliter aliquots were measured in a luminometer for 10 s and plotted.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18866</offset><text>ProTalpha activated the GAL4-responsive promoter in a dose-responsive manner with increasing amounts of ProTalpha transfected in HEK 293 (Fig. 2). The total DNA was balanced for all transfections and normalized for transfection efficiency. Increments of 5 mug of DNA resulted in a gradual increase in activity up to approximately fivefold that for the reporter alone. This increase in activity continued as increasing amounts of pM-ProTalpha were introduced into the system (data not shown). The results suggest that ProTalpha is capable of associating with the basal transcription machinery to activate transcription when targeted to promoters by tethering to the GAL4 DNA binding domain. The activity observed was consistent with ProTalpha having activation functions, as increasing amounts of GAL4-ProTalpha resulted in a general increase in transcription activity (Fig. 2). Western blotting shows the increasing levels of ProTalpha, as indicated by the increasing intensity of the signal compared to the protein level.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>19868</offset><text>The p300 coactivator enhances transcriptional activation mediated by ProTalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19945</offset><text>Previous studies by our group have shown that ProTalpha interacts with the acetyltransferase p300 and can recruit the activity mediated by p300 for acetylation of crude histones in vitro. Immunoprecipitation of complexes associated with ProTalpha using antibodies against ProTalpha contained molecules capable of acetylating histones (7). Additionally, we showed that ProTalpha interacts with linker histone H1 in uninfected and infected cells as well as in vitro, suggesting that there is a direct link to ProTalpha and its association with cellular histones and regulation of transcriptional activity in EBV-infected cells. Therefore we wanted to determine the effects of p300 on the ability of ProTalpha to activate transcription in a transient luciferase reporter assay.</text><annotation id="3"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="20133" length="150"/><text>Immunoprecipitation of complexes associated with ProTalpha using antibodies against ProTalpha contained molecules capable of acetylating histones (7).</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20702</offset><text>A p300 expression construct under the control of a heterologous promoter was transfected with pM-ProTalpha in HEK 293 cells. In this assay we show that the transcription activity mediated by ProTalpha was enhanced in the presence of p300 and that this activity gradually increased when increasing amounts of p300 were introduced in the system. Specifically, the activity was increased by threefold, fourfold, and sixfold with increments of 5 mug of p300 (Fig. 3, left). These results suggest that p300 cooperates with ProTalpha in enhancing basal transcription activity when targeted to the GAL4 promoter. Additionally, p300 by itself does not dramatically enhance the levels of activation, as it does when cooperating with ProTalpha, suggesting that the increased activity is dependent on the association of ProTalpha with p300 (Fig. 3, right). Western blots showing increasing levels of ProTalpha and p300 suggest that the activity is dependent on the levels of protein expressed compared to background level of a nonspecific protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21721</offset><text>Previous work showed that EBNA3C is capable of activating and repressing transcription when targeted to promoters (3, 28). Additionally, it was shown that EBNA3C also modulated the transactivation activity of EBNA2 on the LMP1 promoter and thus that EBNA3C can be a modulator of transcription activation mediated by ProTalpha and p300 (35). Therefore we introduced EBNA3C in the transient reporter assay to determine its effects on transcription mediated by ProTalpha and p300. As expected, EBNA3C down-modulated the increased activity of ProTalpha and p300 when ProTalpha was tethered to promoters (Fig. 4). A slightly lower pM-ProTalpha activity than in the previous experiment was seen in this assay. However, the activity always increased with increasing amounts of ProTalpha expressed. EBNA3C did not produce any detectable changes in activity when introduced alone in the assay, suggesting that the modulatory activity observed is most likely due to the interaction with ProTalpha and p300. The levels of protein expression based on the transfected amounts are shown in Fig. 4.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>22784</offset><text>ProTalpha and EBNA3C interact with regions of p300 similar to those of other known cellular and viral oncoproteins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22897</offset><text>We previously demonstrated that ProTalpha bound to the regions of p300 encoded by 3' and 5' regions of the associated gene but that the affinity for the product of the 5' region was much less than that for the product of the 3' region (7). We therefore wanted to map more closely the binding sites for ProTalpha to determine if the sites were similar to those observed for the known regulators of transcription and cellular oncoproteins. ProTalpha was translated in vitro and incubated with five GST-p300 fusion proteins mapping to distinct domains, including the CH1, CH2, and CH3 domains; the bromodomain; and the HAT domain. Based on our results we show that ProTalpha interacts with two distinct regions of p300. The affinity of the observed interactions at the amino terminus of p300 at the CH1 domain was lower than that of those at the CH3/HAT domain downstream from the bromodomain and that of those at the CH2 domains (Fig. 5A). These sites map to similar regions known to bind transcription regulators, including NF-kappaB, c-myb, CREB, HIF-1, c-Jun, and STAT-2, which are associated with the amino terminus of p300 and the large T antigen of simian virus 40, E1A, and human papillomavirus E6, c-Fos, and E2F, which bind within the CH3 and HAT domains (Fig. 5A and C) (13, 14, 22, 26, 38). These data show that ProTalpha binds to domains of p300 similarly to those bound by known cellular and viral oncoproteins associated with human malignancies.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24345</offset><text>Since we also previously demonstrated that ProTalpha and EBNA3C bound strongly to the 3' region-encoded end of p300 as well as to the 5' region-encoded 1,100-aa region (7), we wanted to map more closely the regions involved in binding with EBNA3C to determine if similar regions of p300 were involved in the interactions with ProTalpha and with EBNA3C.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24696</offset><text>EBNA3C was translated in vitro with [S35]Cys-Met label from NEN-Dupont and then incubated with the five fusions of GST with p300 described above, which represent the different regions of the p300 molecule. We demonstrate that EBNA3C interacts with similar affinity to a region of p300 downstream of the bromodomain, which includes a portion of the HAT domain and the CH3 region. Additionally, we observed interaction again with the amino-terminal CH1 region of p300. These regions were similar to the regions that bound with ProTalpha shown above (Fig. 5A and B). Interestingly, EBNA3C and ProTalpha bind to p300 at the 5' CH1 domain similarly to EBNA2, NF-kappaB, STAT, c-myb, and c-Jun (22, 38, 44) and to the CH3/HAT domain of p300, as seen in previous studies with E1A, E6, and c-Jun (Fig. 5) (22, 38).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>25496</offset><text>ProTalpha and p300 interact with EBNA3C at distinctly separate domains.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25565</offset><text>To demonstrate more precisely the domains of EBNA3C interacting with p300, we translated in vitro truncated versions of specific domains of EBNA3C and incubated these truncated polypeptides with GST-p300-1 and with GST-p300-4, which was shown above to interact with the full-length EBNA3C polypeptide. The binding assays were performed as described above. Here we demonstrated that the CH1 domain of p300 interacts with amino-terminal aa 1 to 207 of EBNA3C (Fig. 6A). In addition, the CH3/HAT domain of p300 interacts with the carboxy-terminal 370 aa, a region which includes the proline-rich and glutamine-rich domains of EBNA3C (Fig. 6A and C).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26212</offset><text>Our previous work mapped the interacting domain of ProTalpha with EBNA3C downstream of aa 365 (7). Moreover, fusion proteins downstream of aa 393 did not associate with ProTalpha. Here we show that a short 34-aa stretch from aa 366 to 400 interacts with ProTalpha in vitro (Fig. 6B and C). This region lies just downstream of aa 365, which was shown to be critical for EBV-mediated transformation of primary B lymphocytes (40). These results indicate that ProTalpha and p300 interact with EBNA3C at distinctly different domains.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26729</offset><text>We were curious as to whether or not the interactions of EBNA3C and ProTalpha with p300 were independent or if EBNA3C and ProTalpha can compete for binding with the specific domains as shown in the above binding experiments, since previous experiments suggest that they may be in a complex with p300. We show that ProTalpha can possibly compete with EBNA3C for binding to the P4 region of p300 more efficiently than for binding to the P1 amino-terminal region of p300. EBNA3C, however, competes with ProTalpha for binding to p300 at the amino-terminal CH1 domain and P4 domain, which includes the CH3/HAT region, with similar efficiencies (Fig. 7). EBNA3C appears to be able to compete with greater efficiency than ProTalpha (Fig. 7, left), suggesting that EBNA3C may have a higher affinity for p300.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>27515</offset><text>EBNA3C modulates ProTalpha- and p300-enhanced HAT activity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27572</offset><text>To determine if the transactivation effects seen above correlated with acetylation of nucleosomes, we wanted to determine the levels of acetylation mediated by complexes associated with ProTalpha. Burkitt's lymphoma cells lines overexpressing EBNA3C, human primary B lymphocytes transformed by EBV expressing the latent EBV nuclear antigens, and an EBNA3C- and EBV-negative cell line (as a control) were used. Cells were harvested and lysed to solubilize the nuclear proteins. Complexes associated with ProTalpha were immunoprecipitated with a polyclonal antibody against ProTalpha, washed in RIPA buffer and in HAT buffer, and then incubated with crude histones. The results demonstrate that there was a five- to sevenfold-greater level of HAT activity in EBV-infected cells than in cells overexpressing EBNA3C (Fig. 8), suggesting that other factors including other latent nuclear antigens expressed by EBV during establishment of latency may play a role in enhancing the HAT activity associated with ProTalpha. Little or no increase in HAT activity was seen in the B-cell lines overexpressing only EBNA3C compared to that for the control EBV-negative cell line, which does not express EBNA3C or any other EBV latent antigen (Fig. 8).</text><annotation id="4"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="28049" length="186"/><text>Complexes associated with ProTalpha were immunoprecipitated with a polyclonal antibody against ProTalpha, washed in RIPA buffer and in HAT buffer, and then incubated with crude histones.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28797</offset><text>To demonstrate that EBNA3C modulates HAT activity when exogenously expressed in HEK epithelial cells, we transiently transfected HEK 293T cells with expression constructs containing ProTalpha, ProTalpha plus p300, and ProTalpha, p300, and EBNA3C into 15 million cells. The transfected cells were incubated for 24 h, harvested, and washed once in PBS. The cells were then lysed in RIPA buffer, and incubated with an anti-ProTalpha polyclonal antibody for 4 h. The complexes were collected and incubated with crude histones to determine the acetylation activity of the complex. We show that coimmunoprecipitation of protein complexes with ProTalpha resulted in activity 3.5-fold greater than that with the vector control alone (Fig. 9). When p300 was transfected under the control of a heterologous promoter, the activity was enhanced to a level 4.6-fold greater than that with the vector (Fig. 9). This enhancement of activity was abolished when EBNA3C was introduced into cells exogenously expressing ProTalpha and p300 (Fig. 9). These results suggest that EBNA3C can modulate the HAT activity when complexed with ProTalpha and p300. When p300 alone was transiently transfected, there was an increase in HAT activity, sometimes as much as the increase seen with ProTalpha, indicating that some level of endogenously expressed ProTalpha can associate with the exogenously transfected p300, resulting in increased activity. However, it is clear that no further HAT activity is obtained when EBNA3C alone is expressed from a heterologous promoter. These results suggest that modulation of the HAT activity mediated by p300 and ProTalpha is through association of these cellular complexes with EBNA3C.</text><annotation id="5"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="29373" length="154"/><text>We show that coimmunoprecipitation of protein complexes with ProTalpha resulted in activity 3.5-fold greater than that with the vector control alone (Fig.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30465</offset><text>EBNA3C is a large transcription factor, which functions as an activator or a repressor of transcription (37). It was shown that two domains are involved in transcriptional repression and that the glutamine-rich domain can activate responsive promoters when targeted to that promoter (3, 28). In this regard we wanted to test the abilities of different domains of EBNA3C to modulate the HAT-associated activity of ProTalpha in a complex with EBNA3C. In this assay immunoprecipitation with an anti-ProTalpha polyclonal antibody demonstrated that as expected ProTalpha increased the HAT activity approximately sixfold over that with the vector alone and that p300 enhanced this activity when cotransfected with ProTalpha. Additionally, the full-length EBNA3C molecule again down-modulated this increased effect three- to fourfold. A truncated version of EBNA3C which contains the first 207 aa had little effect on the HAT activity, whereas truncated versions of EBNA3C containing the first 365 aa and the carboxy-terminal 727 aa reduced the effect by more than twofold (Fig. 10). These results indicate that both the amino terminus (which lies between aa 207 and 365) and the carboxy terminus (aa 365 to 992) of EBNA3C contain domains that are involved in modulating HAT activity and can associate with p300 complexed with ProTalpha in these transfected cells.</text><annotation id="6"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="30914" length="269"/><text>In this assay immunoprecipitation with an anti-ProTalpha polyclonal antibody demonstrated that as expected ProTalpha increased the HAT activity approximately sixfold over that with the vector alone and that p300 enhanced this activity when cotransfected with ProTalpha.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>31808</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31819</offset><text>Previous studies have demonstrated that EBNA3C interacts with ProTalpha in regulating histone acetylation (7). ProTalpha was shown to interact and associate with histone H1 in EBV-infected cells (7, 8). Moreover, ProTalpha also interacted with acetyltransferase p300 in EBV-infected cells, suggesting that these interactions are important for transcriptional regulation and gene expression of the transformed cells. Here we further demonstrate these interactions and more precisely map the binding domains for each interaction. Our results show that ProTalpha interacts with p300 at two specific domains, a region downstream of the bromodomain, the CH3/HAT domain, and another region at the amino terminus of p300, referred to as the CH1 domain. Additionally, EBNA3C, an essential EBV molecule, interacts with p300 at the same amino-terminal domain interacting with ProTalpha. These interaction studies clearly indicate that EBNA3C exists in a complex with ProTalpha and p300 and that this complex may be critical for EBV-mediated regulation of viral and cellular gene expression.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32882</offset><text>To date the functional activity of ProTalpha at promoters has not been established. Here we show that ProTalpha can activate transcription of promoters when targeted to promoters using a GAL4-ProTalpha fusion on a GAL4-responsive promoter element. This result for the first time demonstrates that ProTalpha can affect the transcriptional machinery when tethered to promoters. Moreover, ProTalpha can interact with known transcriptional coactivator p300, which is well established as an effector of transcriptional activation (10, 29). ProTalpha interacts with histone H1 and removes H1 bound to the nucleosomes, suggesting that it is involved in chromatin remodeling to allow access to transcription and replication factors (8, 15, 23). If histone H1 promotes condensation of the chromatin into higher-order structures that are transcriptionally inactive, then association with ProTalpha can reverse this process and so allow for the decondensation of the chromatin as histone H1 is stripped from the nucleosomes, which allows for access by the transcriptional machinery. Similarly, this can be a mechanism by which the replication machinery can gain access to the chromatin structure. ProTalpha then is an antagonist of histone H1 by virtue of its ability to regulate the condensation of the higher-order structure of chromatin associated with histone H1 involved in gene regulation and possibly replication.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34268</offset><text>In our studies we also show that ProTalpha also interacts with transcription coactivator p300 and that this interaction results in the synergistic activation of transcription. The fact that ProTalpha interacts with p300 suggests that it may be in a complex with other transcription factors and that it may be an essential component of the larger basal transcription complex. We have now mapped the domains interacting with p300 to the amino terminus CH1 and the region downstream of the bromodomain, the CH3/HAT domain. These regions have been the subject of numerous investigations, which have shown that other known transcription factors associate with the CH1 domain and that viral and cellular factors including E6 and E1A associate with the CH3/HAT domain (14, 22, 38). This suggests that EBNA3C and ProTalpha are involved in regulating functions similar to those regulated by other cellular and viral factors, which include acetylation and transcription activation. Evidence provided in this study indicates that both ProTalpha and EBNA3C are involved in regulating the acetylation and transcriptional activity of p300. The modulation of these effects by EBNA3C is most likely important for regulation of cellular and viral gene expression required for the transformation process mediated by EBV. Based on this evidence we suggest a potential model whereby ProTalpha removes histone H1 from the nucleosomes and may be involved in the recruitment of other general transcription factors. ProTalpha may therefore be involved in the decondensation of the chromatin and the acetylation of core histones as it interacts with p300 at two specific domains complexed with other transcriptional activators including RNA polymerase II. This results in transcription activation. EBNA3C may not be a component of this complex during activation, or maybe it is sequestered by other transcription factors with access to the general transcription complex. However, when EBNA3C is recruited to this complex, the activity mediated by p300 and the general transcription activation complex is modulated by displacement of specific components and/or modification of the large transcription activation complex (Fig. 11).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36455</offset><text>Chromatin remodeling is a critical aspect of gene regulation (22, 27). ProTalpha is involved in the remodeling of chromosomes, is expressed ubiquitously in numerous cell types, and is up-regulated when the cell is undergoing oncogenesis induced by a known cellular oncogene (11, 30). Here we show that ProTalpha and EBNA3C interact specifically with p300 at regions identical to those at which E1A and E6, as well as c-Jun and E2F, all regulators of transcription, interact (22, 38). The fact that the interaction domains are the same suggests a role for ProTalpha in transcription regulation, possibly in recruitment and stabilization of complexes involved in activation or repression as they are brought to nucleosomes. EBNA3C, then, through its interaction with ProTalpha can regulate the resulting transcriptional activity generated by the activation complex. Importantly, more studies will be required to investigate the role of ProTalpha in chromatin remodeling and to identify other factors associated with this transcription complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>37482</offset><text>REFERENCES</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">74</infon><infon key="fpage">361</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8383171</infon><infon key="citation">Allday, M. J., D. H. Crawford, and J. A. Thomas.. Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) nuclear antigen 6 induces expression of the EBV latent membrane protein and an activated phenotype in Raji cells. :-369.</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">J. Gen. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37493</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">68</infon><infon key="fpage">3491</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8189488</infon><infon key="citation">Allday, M. J., and P. J. Farrell.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen EBNA3C/6 expression maintains the level of latent membrane protein 1 in G1-arrested cells. :-3498.</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37494</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">70</infon><infon key="fpage">2481</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8642676</infon><infon key="citation">Bain, M., R. J. Watson, P. J. Farrell, and M. J. Allday.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C is a powerful repressor of transcription when tethered to DNA. :-2489.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37495</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="fpage">1376</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10451442</infon><infon key="citation">Bonnet, M., J. M. Guinebretiere, E. Kremmer, V. Grunewald, E. Benhamou, G. Contesso, and I. Joab.. Detection of Epstein-Barr virus in invasive breast cancers. :-1381.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">J. Natl. Cancer Inst.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37496</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="fpage">431</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11440855</infon><infon key="citation">Bustin, M.. Chromatin unfolding and activation by HMGN(*) chromosomal proteins. :-437.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Trends Biochem. Sci.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37497</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="fpage">5237</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10409715</infon><infon key="citation">Bustin, M.. Regulation of DNA-dependent activities by the functional motifs of the high-mobility-group chromosomal proteins. :-5246.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37498</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="fpage">5722</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10891508</infon><infon key="citation">Cotter, M. A., II, and E. S. Robertson.. Modulation of histone acetyltransferase activity through interaction of Epstein-Barr nuclear antigen 3C with prothymosin alpha. :-5735.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37499</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">1296</infon><infon key="fpage">219</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8814229</infon><infon key="citation">Diaz-Jullien, C., A. Perez-Estevez, G. Covelo, and M. Freire.. Prothymosin alpha binds histones in vitro and shows activity in nucleosome assembly assay. :-227.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Biochim. Biophys. Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37500</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="fpage">5843</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9315642</infon><infon key="citation">Ding, H. F., M. Bustin, and U. Hansen.. Alleviation of histone H1-mediated transcriptional repression and chromatin compaction by the acidic activation region in chromosomal protein HMG-14. :-5855.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37501</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">377</infon><infon key="fpage">685</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8960368</infon><infon key="citation">Eckner, R.. p300 and CBP as transcriptional regulators and targets of oncogenic events. :-688.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37502</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="fpage">133</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1989881</infon><infon key="citation">Eilers, M., S. Schirm, and J. M. Bishop.. The MYC protein activates transcription of the alpha-prothymosin gene. :-141.</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37503</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">95</infon><infon key="fpage">5281</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9560267</infon><infon key="citation">Felzien, L. K., C. Woffendin, M. O. Hottiger, R. A. Subbramanian, E. A. Cohen, and G. J. Nabel.. HIV transcriptional activation by the accessory protein, VPR, is mediated by the p300 co-activator. :-5286.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37504</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">187</infon><infon key="fpage">2031</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9625762</infon><infon key="citation">Garcia-Rodriguez, C., and A. Rao.. Nuclear factor of activated T cells (NFAT)-dependent transactivation regulated by the coactivators p300/CREB-binding protein (CBP). :-2036.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">J. Exp. Med.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37505</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="fpage">178</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9613201</infon><infon key="citation">Giles, R. H., D. J. Peters, and M. H. Breuning.. Conjunction dysfunction: CBP/p300 in human disease. :-183.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">Trends Genet.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37506</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">333</infon><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9639554</infon><infon key="citation">Gomez-Marquez, J., and P. Rodriguez.. Prothymosin alpha is a chromatin-remodelling protein in mammalian cells. :-3.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">Biochem. J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37507</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">226</infon><infon key="fpage">217</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3338551</infon><infon key="citation">Gomez-Marquez, J., and F. Segade.. Prothymosin alpha is a nuclear protein. :-219.</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37508</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">264</infon><infon key="fpage">8451</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2785990</infon><infon key="citation">Gomez-Marquez, J., F. Segade, M. Dosil, J. G. Pichel, X. R. Bustelo, and M. Freire.. The expression of prothymosin alpha gene in T lymphocytes and leukemic lymphoid cells is tied to lymphocyte proliferation. :-8454.</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37509</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="fpage">7568</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8052621</infon><infon key="citation">Grossman, S. R., E. Johannsen, X. Tong, R. Yalamanchili, and E. Kieff.. The Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 2 transactivator is directed to response elements by the J kappa recombination signal binding protein. :-7572.</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37510</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="fpage">523</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10611231</infon><infon key="citation">Herrera, J. E., K. L. West, R. L. Schiltz, Y. Nakatani, and M. Bustin.. Histone H1 is a specific repressor of core histone acetylation in chromatin. :-529.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37511</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">72</infon><infon key="fpage">8252</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9733868</infon><infon key="citation">Hottiger, M. O., and G. J. Nabel.. Interaction of human immunodeficiency virus type 1 Tat with the transcriptional coactivators p300 and CREB binding protein. :-8256.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37512</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">72</infon><infon key="fpage">4371</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9557727</infon><infon key="citation">Imai, S., J. Nishikawa, and K. Takada.. Cell-to-cell contact as an efficient mode of Epstein-Barr virus infection of diverse human epithelial cells. :-4378.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37513</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="fpage">175</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10322138</infon><infon key="citation">Jacobson, S., and L. Pillus.. Modifying chromatin and concepts of cancer. :-184.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37514</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="fpage">3111</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9628907</infon><infon key="citation">Karetsou, Z., R. Sandaltzopoulos, M. Frangou-Lazaridis, C. Y. Lai, O. Tsolas, P. B. Becker, and T. Papamarcaki.. Prothymosin alpha modulates the interaction of histone H1 with chromatin. :-3118.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">Nucleic Acids Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37515</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">vol. 2</infon><infon key="fpage">2343</infon><infon key="citation">Kieff, E.. Epstein-Barr virus and its replication, p. -2395. In B. N. Fields, D. M. Knipe, and P. M. Howley (ed.), , 3rd ed., . Lippincott-Raven Publishers, Philadelphia, Pa.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Fields virology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37516</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">90</infon><infon key="fpage">9237</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8415684</infon><infon key="citation">Ling, P. D., D. R. Rawlins, and S. D. Hayward.. The Epstein-Barr virus immortalizing protein EBNA-2 is targeted to DNA by a cellular enhancer-binding protein. :-9241.</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37517</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="fpage">1202</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9891054</infon><infon key="citation">Liu, L., D. M. Scolnick, R. C. Trievel, H. B. Zhang, R. Marmorstein, T. D. Halazonetis, and S. L. Berger.. p53 sites acetylated in vitro by PCAF and p300 are acetylated in vivo in response to DNA damage. :-1209.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37518</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="fpage">1288</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10433617</infon><infon key="citation">Luo, R. X., and D. C. Dean.. Chromatin remodeling and transcriptional regulation. :-1294.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">J. Natl. Cancer Inst.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37519</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">69</infon><infon key="fpage">3624</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7745710</infon><infon key="citation">Marshall, D., and C. Sample.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C is a transcriptional regulator. :-3630.</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37520</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">87</infon><infon key="fpage">953</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8945521</infon><infon key="citation">Ogryzko, V. V., R. L. Schiltz, V. Russanova, B. H. Howard, and Y. Nakatani.. The transcriptional coactivators p300 and CBP are histone acetyltransferases. :-959.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37521</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="fpage">1794</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11036085</infon><infon key="citation">Orre, R. S., M. A. Cotter II, C. Subramanian, and E. S. Robertson.. Prothymosin alpha functions as a cellular oncoprotein by inducing transformation of rodent fibroblasts in vitro. :-1799.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37522</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">73</infon><infon key="fpage">5688</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10364319</infon><infon key="citation">Radkov, S. A., R. Touitou, A. Brehm, M. Rowe, M. West, T. Kouzarides, and M. J. Allday.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C interacts with histone deacetylase to repress transcription. :-5697.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37523</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">vol. 2</infon><infon key="fpage">2397</infon><infon key="citation">Rickinson, A., and E. Kieff. Epstein-Barr virus, p. -2446. In B. N. Fields, D. M. Knipe, and P. M. Howley (ed.), , 3rd ed., . Lippincott-Raven Publishers, Philadelphia, Pa.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Fields virology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37524</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="fpage">143</infon><infon key="citation">Robertson, E. S.. The Epstein-Barr virus EBNA3 protein family as regulators of transcription. :-150.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Epstein-Barr Virus Rep.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37525</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">2</infon><infon key="fpage">73</infon><infon key="citation">Robertson, E. S., and E. Kieff.. Genetic analysis of Epstein-Barr virus in B lymphocytes. :-80.</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Epstein-Barr Virus Rep.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37526</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">69</infon><infon key="fpage">3108</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7707539</infon><infon key="citation">Robertson, E. S., S. Grossman, E. Johannsen, C. Miller, J. Lin, B. Tomkinson, and E. Kieff.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear protein 3C modulates transcription through interaction with the sequence-specific DNA-binding protein Jkappa. :-3116.</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37527</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">70</infon><infon key="fpage">3068</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8627785</infon><infon key="citation">Robertson, E. S., J. Lin, and E. Kieff.. The amino-terminal domains of Epstein-Barr virus nuclear proteins 3A, 3B, and 3C interact with RBPJkappa. :-3074.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37528</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">64</infon><infon key="fpage">4084</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2166806</infon><infon key="citation">Sample, J., L. Young, B. Martin, T. Chatman, E. Kieff, and A. Rickinson.. Epstein-Barr virus types 1 and 2 differ in their EBNA-3A, EBNA-3B, and EBNA-3C genes. :-4092.</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37529</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="fpage">230</infon><infon key="citation">Shikama, N., J. Lyon, and N. LaThangue.. The p300/CBP family: integrating signals with transcription factors and chromatin. :-235.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37530</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="fpage">350</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11231635</infon><infon key="citation">Subramanian, C., M. A. Cotter II, and E. S. Robertson.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear protein EBNA-3C interacts with the human metastatic suppressor Nm23-H1: a molecular link to cancer metastasis. :-355.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Med.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37531</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">67</infon><infon key="fpage">2014</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8445720</infon><infon key="citation">Tomkinson, B., E. Robertson, and E. Kieff.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear proteins EBNA-3A and EBNA-3C are essential for B-lymphocyte growth transformation. :-2025.</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37532</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">257</infon><infon key="fpage">152</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10854063</infon><infon key="citation">Vareli, K., M. Frangou-Lazaridis, I. van der Kraan, O. Tsolas, and R. van Driel.. Nuclear distribution of prothymosin alpha and parathymosin: evidence that prothymosin alpha is associated with RNA synthesis processing and parathymosin with early DNA replication. :-161.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Exp. Cell Res.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37533</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">238</infon><infon key="fpage">799</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8706683</infon><infon key="citation">Vareli, K., O. Tsolas, and M. Frangou-Lazaridis.. Regulation of prothymosin alpha during the cell cycle. :-806.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Eur. J. Biochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37534</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">246</infon><infon key="fpage">911</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2683088</infon><infon key="citation">Vinson, C. R., P. B. Sigler, and S. L. McKnight.. Scissors-grip model for DNA recognition by a family of leucine zipper proteins. :-916.</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37535</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="fpage">430</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10618435</infon><infon key="citation">Wang, L., S. R. Grossman, and E. Kieff.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear protein 2 interacts with p300, CBP, and PCAF histone acetyltransferases in activation of the LMP1 promoter. :-435.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37536</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">183</infon><infon key="fpage">293</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9422984</infon><infon key="citation">Yanai, H., K. Takada, N. Shimizu, Y. Mizugaki, M. Tada, and K. Okita.. Epstein-Barr virus infection in non-carcinomatous gastric epithelium. :-298.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">J. Pathol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37537</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">74</infon><infon key="fpage">5151</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10799590</infon><infon key="citation">Zhao, B., and C. E. Sample.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 3C activates the latent membrane protein 1 promoter in the presence of Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 2 through sequences encompassing an spi-1/Spi-B binding site. :-5160.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">J. Virol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37538</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="fpage">4973</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7957063</infon><infon key="citation">Zimber-Strobl, U., L. J. Strobl, C. Meitinger, R. Hinrichs, T. Sakai, T. Furukawa, T. Honjo, and G. W. Bornkamm.. Epstein-Barr virus nuclear antigen 2 exerts its transactivating function through interaction with recombination signal binding protein RBP-J kappa, the homologue of Drosophila Suppressor of Hairless. :-4982.</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>37539</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>37540</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>37559</offset><text>Schematic of basic structure of the EBNA3C protein with the identified motifs. Domains for interaction with p300 at both the amino and carboxy termini of the molecule are indicated. ProTalpha specifically interacts with the region between aa 366 and 400, a region shown previously to be essential for B-lymphocyte transformation (40). Arrow (at aa 365), insertion of an amber stop codon in the three reading frames, which demonstrated that EBNA3C is essential for B-lymphocyte transformation (40). The interaction domain for RBP-Jkappa (Jkappa) at the amino-terminal region and the leucine zipper (LZ) motif, acidic domains (AD), and proline (P)-rich and glutamine (Q)-rich domains are indicated (37, 40). The regions involved in activation and repression and the region of homology for the EBNA3 family members at the amino terminus are also shown (33, 34, 36, 37). NLS, nuclear localization signal.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>38451</offset><text>Luciferase assay demonstrating that ProTalpha fused to GAL4 activates transcription when tethered to the promoter in 293 cells. 293 cells were transfected with increasing amounts of pM-ProTalpha in 5-mug increments. Transfections were balanced for amounts of DNA and normalized for transfection efficiencies. The pFr vector contains the luciferase gene downstream of a promoter element with GAL4 binding sites, which is targeted by the GAL4 DNA binding domain. The relative intensities are expressed as luciferase units (RLU). The pM vector contains only the GAL4 DNA binding domain not fused to a cDNA and was used as a control in this assay. Western blot (WB) shows increasing levels of ProTalpha with increasing amounts of ProTalpha DNA. The membrane was blotted with a rabbit polyclonal antibody against ProTalpha. A comparative stain of protein transferred to the membrane demonstrating equivalent levels of protein loading is shown at the bottom.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>39389</offset><text>The p300 coactivator enhances the transcription activation mediated by ProTalpha. The p300 expression vector was transfected in increasing amounts along with pM-ProTalpha in a luciferase assay. All transfections were normalized for transfection efficiencies and total DNA. Transfected cultures were harvested after 24 h of incubation at 37 C. The p300 expression construct was added in increments of 5 mug without pM-ProTalpha. Relative luciferase units (RLU) were measured for 10 s with an MGM luminometer (Optocomp1), and means of three experiments are shown. A Western blot (WB) assay for ProTalpha and p300 levels and for those of the protein loading control used for comparison is shown at the bottom.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>40085</offset><text>Luciferase assay shows that EBNA3C down-modulates the transcription activity mediated by ProTalpha and p300 in 293 cells. Cells were transfected with pFr, pM-ProTalpha, and p300, followed by addition of EBNA3C, and harvested at 24 h after transfection. The results show that EBNA3C modulates the increased transcription activity mediated by pM-ProTalpha and p300. The results are the mean of the relative luciferase units (RLU), normalized for total DNA content and efficiency of transfection, from three independent transfections. Similar amounts of EBNA3C, when transfected alone with the reporter, did not have any detectable effects compared to vector alone in this assay. Western blotting (WB) shows levels of each protein transfected in each lane compared to the equivalent levels of protein in each lane.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>40888</offset><text>In vitro binding assay shows that EBNA3C and ProTalpha interact with p300 at two distinct domains, the CH1 and CH3/HAT domains. S35-labeled in vitro-translated ProTalpha and EBNA3C were incubated with GST fusions overlapping the entire p300. P1 through P5 were prepared and purified by binding to glutathione-Sepharose beads. Beads bound to the GST fusion proteins were washed and incubated with labeled in vitro-translated products. (A) Results of the binding assay with S35-labeled ProTalpha, where binding was seen at the amino terminus and CH3/HAT domain. (B) In vitro-translated S35-labeled EBNA3C similarly bound to the same p300 fusion. (C) Schematic indicating the specific domains of p300 and the known interacting molecules. Note that other cellular and viral transcription regulators interact with p300 at the CH3/HAT domain and at the CH1 domain (22, 38).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>41747</offset><text>The p300 coactivator interacts with EBNA3C at two distinct domains, the amino-terminal 207 aa and the carboxy-terminal 372 aa. ProTalpha interacts specifically with residues located between aa 366 and 400 of EBNA3C. (A) The S35-labeled in vitro-translated regions of EBNA3C bind to the amino terminus of the p300-P1 fusion protein, whereas the carboxy-terminal region, aa 620 to 992, interacts with the p300-P4 fusion protein, which includes the CH3/HAT domain. (B) Specific interaction of ProTalpha with the region comprising aa 366 to 400 of EBNA3C. All input lanes are equivalent to 10% of the total used in the experimental lanes. (C) Schematic of the different regions of EBNA3C used in the binding experiments and the interaction domains for p300 and ProTalpha. NLS, nuclear localization signal.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>42540</offset><text>ProTalpha and EBNA3C compete for binding to p300 at the amino-terminal and CH3/HAT domains. Increasing amounts of ProTalpha and EBNA3C were added to the reaction mixture 1 h after allowing the GST-p300 fusion protein to bind in vitro. (Top) Effect of competition with the amino-terminal region; (bottom) competition with the CH3/HAT domain. EBNA3C and ProTalpha were translated in vitro and labeled with the S35 translabel for visualization of the protein by autoradiography.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>43007</offset><text>Histone acetylation assay showing that EBV infection increases the overall acetylation activity associated with cellular molecules which coimmunoprecipitate and form complexes with ProTalpha in the infected cell. EBNA3C cell lines stably overexpressing the E3C protein are E3C.7 and E3C.10. LCL1 and LCL2 are EBV-infected B-lymphoblastoid cell lines expressing the entire panel of latent EBV nuclear antigens. BJAB is an EBV-negative cell line. Cells were lysed, and complexes associated with ProTalpha were immunoprecipitated with polyclonal rabbit serum overnight, washed, and used in the HAT assay. The results, total 3H counts, are the averages of three independent assays. Western blotting (WB) shows the expression of EBNA3C in each assay.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>43747</offset><text>Histone acetylation assay showing that EBNA3C modulates the activity mediated by ProTalpha and p300 in transfected HEK 293T cells. Transfected cells were harvested after 24 h posttransfection and lysed. Cleared lysate was immunoprecipitated with a ProTalpha antibody, washed, and used in the HAT assay. EBNA3C was transfected along with a p300 expression vector and pA3M-ProTalpha. All transfections were balanced with vector DNA for the total amount of DNA per transfection and normalized for transfection efficiencies. The results are the means of three separate assays. The p300 expression construct and the EBNA3C expression construct were transfected independently in the absence of pA3M-ProTalpha to determine their effects alone on the endogenous HAT activity associated with ProTalpha. The levels of protein expressed were evaluated by Western blotting (WB) using specific antibodies against ProTalpha, p300, and EBNA3C.</text><annotation id="7"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="43950" length="99"/><text>Cleared lysate was immunoprecipitated with a ProTalpha antibody, washed, and used in the HAT assay.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>44658</offset><text>The amino and carboxy termini of EBNA3C reverse the HAT activity mediated by ProTalpha and p300. HEK 293T cells were transfected with the first 207 aa of EBNA3C, which contain the RBP-Jkappa interacting domain, aa 1 to 365 and 365 to 992 of EBNA3C, along with similar levels of full-length EBNA3C for comparison. All transfections were balanced as described in Materials and Methods for equivalent amounts of DNA. Each truncated EBNA3C construct and full-length EBNA3C were introduced into the reaction mixture with pA3M-ProTalpha and p300. All transfectants were incubated for 24 h and harvested, and the acetylation complex was immunoprecipitated with a polyclonal antibody against ProTalpha. Complexes were washed and used in the HAT assay. The results are the means of three independent assays. (Bottom) Levels of p300 and ProTalpha expressed compared to equivalent protein loading control. WB, Western blot.</text><annotation id="8"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="45199" length="153"/><text>All transfectants were incubated for 24 h and harvested, and the acetylation complex was immunoprecipitated with a polyclonal antibody against ProTalpha.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>45556</offset><text>Model showing EBNA3C regulation of transcription and HAT activity associated with p300 and ProTalpha. ProTalpha removes histone H1 from the nucleosomes, allowing access for transcription and coactivation complexes, which are functionally similar to some HMG molecules (8, 9, 19, 23). ProTalpha may then recruit and stabilize general transcription complexes and associates with p300 at two distinct contact points at the amino-terminal CH1 domain and at the CH3/HAT domain. The interaction with the HAT domain may be involved in regulation of HAT activity, as the core histones are acetylated and also cooperate with a number of transcription factors in a large general transcription complex. EBNA3C modulates this transcription activity by displacing and modifying the general transcription complex as the activity of p300 and ProTalpha is regulated. Overall, ProTalpha interacts with histone H1, decondensing the nucleosomes as the required transcription regulatory factors are recruited. The resulting activity is activation of transcription, which is modulated as EBNA3C is introduced into the complex.</text></passage></document></collection>