<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>ascii.key</key><document><id>z</id><passage><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1073/pnas.122062299</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc"></infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">12048243</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">122062299 0622</infon><infon key="fpage">7951</infon><infon key="issue">12</infon><infon key="journal-title">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America</infon><infon key="lpage">7955</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Watcharasit;given-names:Piyajit</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bijur;given-names:Gautam N.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Zmijewski;given-names:Jaroslaw W.</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Song;given-names:Ling</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Zmijewska;given-names:Anna</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Chen;given-names:Xinbin</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Johnson;given-names:Gail V. W.</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Jope;given-names:Richard S.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">99</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Direct, activating interaction between glycogen synthase kinase-3beta and p53 after DNA damage</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>93</offset><text>Glycogen synthase kinase-3beta (GSK3beta) is a central figure in Wnt signaling, in which its activity is controlled by regulatory binding proteins. Here we show that binding proteins outside the Wnt pathway also control the activity of GSK3beta. DNA damage induced by camptothecin, which activates the tumor suppressor p53, was found to activate GSK3beta. This activation occurred by a phosphorylation-independent mechanism involving direct binding of GSK3beta to p53, which was confined to the nucleus where p53 is localized, and mutated p53 (R175H) bound but did not activate GSK3beta. Activation of GSK3 promoted responses to p53 including increases in p21 levels and caspase-3 activity. Thus, after DNA damage there is a direct interaction between p53 and GSK3beta, and these proteins act in concert to regulate cellular responses to DNA damage.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>929</offset><text>Cells respond to DNA damage by activating signaling cascades that cause cell-cycle arrest to allow repair or cause apoptosis to eliminate irreparably damaged cells (1-3). After DNA damage, the tumor-suppressor protein p53 is a key intermediate in both cell-cycle arrest and apoptosis, and dysfunctional p53 is one of the most prevalent causes of tumor formation in humans (4-6). Apoptosis induced by p53 after DNA damage is executed by cysteine/aspartate proteases such as the effector caspase-3, but regulatory mechanisms linking p53 to caspase activation remain unclear. Glycogen synthase kinase-3beta (GSK3beta) is a key enzyme in several signaling pathways (7, 8) including the Wnt pathway, through which its activity is controlled by regulatory binding proteins, and is an important proapoptotic signaling enzyme (9-12). Furthermore, apoptotic stimuli induce nuclear accumulation of GSK3beta (13), colocalizing it with p53. Therefore, we examined whether there is a functional interaction between p53 and GSK3beta and whether p53-mediated caspase activation caused by DNA damage involves GSK3beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>2028</offset><text>Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>2036</offset><text>Cell Culture and Treatments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2065</offset><text>Human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y and H1299 cells were grown as described (11, 14). Cells were washed and incubated in serum-free medium for 2 h before experimental treatments, and previously described procedures were used for preparation of cell lysates (13) and for measurements of caspase-3 activity (11). Full-length GSK3beta-binding protein (GBP) cDNA (provided by D. Kimelman) was amplified by PCR (primers 5'-AGTTAGTCGACGCCATGCCGTGTCGCAAGGAG-3' and 5'-ACTATGCGGCCGCTTGCACGGTTGTTCCAGT GCA-3'), digested with SalI and NotI, and inserted into the SalI/NotI sites of the pCMV/Myc/nuc vector (Invitrogen) to make GBP with a nuclear localization signal and a Myc epitope. For construction of pcDNA3.1/XG114, full-length dominant negative GSK3beta (provided by D. Kimelman) was excised from XG114 vector using BamHI and subcloned into the BamHI restriction site of pcDNA3.1(-) (Invitrogen). All constructs were verified by DNA sequencing. SH-SY5Y cell lines stably expressing nuclear localization signal-GBP or dominant negative GSK3beta were generated as described (11).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>3135</offset><text>Immunoblot Analysis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3156</offset><text>Samples were mixed with Laemmli sample buffer (2% SDS) and placed in a boiling water bath for 5 min. Proteins were resolved in SDS-polyacrylamide gels and transferred to nitrocellulose, membranes were probed with antibodies to p53 (Upstate Biotechnology, Lake Placid, NY), poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP), p21 (BD PharMingen, San Diego), GSK3beta (BD Transduction, San Diego), or phospho-Ser-9-GSK3beta (New England Biolabs), and each experiment was carried out two or more times.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>3636</offset><text>GSK3beta Activity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3653</offset><text>The activity of GSK3beta was measured essentially as described (13). Briefly, GSK3beta was immunoprecipitated from cell lysates (100 mug of protein) or nuclear extracts (25 mug of protein). GSK3beta activity was measured by incubating immunoprecipitated GSK3beta or, where indicated, recombinant GSK3beta (New England Biolabs), in 30 mul of kinase buffer [20 mM Tris, pH 7.5/5 mM MgCl2/1 mM DTT/250 muM ATP/1.4 muCi (1 Ci = 37 GBq) of [gamma-32P]ATP, Amersham Pharmacia], with 0.1 mug/mul recombinant tau protein (Panvera, Madison, WI) for 30 min at 30 C, and 25 mul of Laemmli sample buffer (2% SDS) was added to stop the reaction. Samples were placed in a boiling water bath for 5 min, proteins were separated in 8% SDS polyacrylamide gels, and gels were vacuum-dried, exposed to a phosphoscreen overnight, and quantitated by using a PhosphorImager (Molecular Dynamics). The efficiency of GSK3beta immunoprecipitation was determined by immunoblotting for GSK3beta. In indicated experiments, the activity of recombinant GSK3beta was measured by using a primed substrate, phosphoglycogen synthase peptide-2 (Upstate Biotechnology), as described (11) except that the peptide concentration used was 25 muM and the reaction time was 10 min.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>4873</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4881</offset><text>To study responses to DNA damage we used camptothecin, a topoisomerase I inhibitor that is well known to cause DNA damage, which subsequently activates p53-mediated responses. Camptothecin treatment of human neuroblastoma SH-SY5Y cells caused time-dependent (Fig. 1A) and concentration-dependent (Fig. 1B) increases in the levels of p53 and p53-regulated protein p21WAF1/CIP1. Subsequent to p53 accumulation there was increased proteolysis of the caspase-3 substrate PARP and increased activity of caspase-3, which is consistent with previous reports that DNA damage leads to p53-induced activation of the caspase-3-mediated apoptosis signaling cascade (4-6). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5544</offset><text>To test whether GSK3beta was influenced by DNA damage caused by camptothecin treatment, GSK3beta was immunoprecipitated from camptothecin-treated cells, and its activity was assessed by measuring the phosphorylation of recombinant tau, a well characterized substrate of GSK3beta (15). These measurements revealed that camptothecin treatment resulted in a large and prolonged increase in the activity of GSK3beta (Fig. 1C). Because GSK3beta is located in both the cytosolic and nuclear compartments of cells, and some apoptotic stimuli increase nuclear levels of GSK3beta (13), these compartments were fractionated from control and camptothecin-treated cells to examine which pool of GSK3beta was activated after DNA damage. Surprisingly, there was no nuclear translocation of GSK3beta after camptothecin treatment, because both the nuclear and cytosolic levels of GSK3beta remained unchanged, but there was an exclusive activation of nuclear, not cytosolic, GSK3beta (Fig. 1D). Nuclear GSK3beta was activated within 1 h of camptothecin treatment and remained highly activated for at least 5 h (Fig. 1D). Treatment with another agent that causes DNA damage, etoposide, also increased p53 levels and activated GSK3beta in the nucleus (Fig. 1E). These findings reveal a previously unrecognized effect of DNA damage, activation of GSK3beta in the nucleus.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6870</offset><text>We examined the mechanisms underlying DNA damage-induced activation of GSK3beta, first focusing on potential changes in the phosphorylation state of GSK3beta. GSK3beta is inhibited by phosphorylation of Ser-9 and activated by phosphorylation of Tyr-216 (7, 8, 16, 17). However, after camptothecin treatment there were no changes in the levels of nuclear phospho-Ser-9-GSK3beta (Fig. 2A) or phosphotyrosine-GSK3beta (data not shown). GSK3beta activity also can be regulated by association with other proteins (7, 8). For example, axin facilitates GSK3beta-mediated phosphorylation of beta-catenin, and the inhibitory GBP inhibits GSK3beta activity (18-20). Therefore, we tested whether there might be a direct, regulatory association of GSK3beta with p53 that accumulated in the nucleus after DNA damage by using coimmunoprecipitation measurements. Immunoblots revealed that p53 coimmunoprecipitated with GSK3beta from nuclear fractions prepared from cells treated with camptothecin (Fig. 2B). Similarly, camptothecin treatment resulted in the coimmunoprecipitation of GSK3beta with p53 (data not shown). Thus, DNA damage increased nuclear p53 levels and activated nuclear GSK3beta, and p53 formed a stable complex with GSK3beta in the nucleus. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8089</offset><text>We tested whether p53, rather than other signals generated by DNA damage, accounted for activation of GSK3beta. p53 transiently transfected into p53-null H1299 lung carcinoma cells (14) coimmunoprecipitated with GSK3beta, and expression of p53 was sufficient to increase the activity of nuclear GSK3beta (Fig. 2C). In contrast, mutant p53 (R175H), known to be functionally impaired, associated with but did not activate GSK3beta. This result indicated that the DNA damage-induced activation of GSK3beta resulted from a regulatory association with p53. The association of p53 with GSK3beta, taken in conjunction with the lack of changes in GSK3beta phosphorylation, raised the possibility that p53 may cause the activation of GSK3beta directly. To test this hypothesis, the activity of recombinant GSK3beta was measured in vitro in the absence and presence of recombinant p53. Remarkably, these measurements demonstrated that p53 directly increased the activity of recombinant GSK3beta, because GSK3beta activity increased in a p53 concentration-dependent manner (Fig. 2D). Because GSK3beta phosphorylates substrates that are either unprimed, such as tau, or primed by previous phosphorylation (7, 8), we examined recombinant GSK3beta-mediated phosphorylation of a primed substrate, phosphoglycogen synthase peptide-2, which also exhibited activation by recombinant p53 (n = 3; P &lt; 0.05 compared with GSK3beta activity in the absence of p53; data not shown). Thus, these experiments have shown that p53 is capable of directly binding to GSK3beta, and this direct association increases the activity of GSK3beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9667</offset><text>In the Wnt pathway, scaffolding regulatory proteins control the specificity of GSK3beta-mediated signaling (7, 8). Therefore, we reasoned that association with p53 might direct the actions of GSK3beta to processes involved in p53-induced signaling. To examine this hypothesis, several methods were used to inhibit GSK3beta activity to test whether this modulated p53 mediated responses after DNA damage. Pretreatment with lithium, a selective inhibitor of GSK3beta (21-24), or a structurally dissimilar inhibitor of GSK3beta, sodium valproate (25), reduced the camptothecin-induced increases in p21, PARP proteolysis (Fig. 3A), and caspase-3 activity (data not shown). Lithium and sodium valproate pretreatment also attenuated etoposide-induced increases in p21 levels and PARP proteolysis (Fig. 3B), and stable expression of a dominant negative mutant of GSK3beta (26) also attenuated camptothecin-induced PARP proteolysis (Fig. 3C). Thus, three treatments that reduce the activity of GSK3beta attenuated signaling responses to p53. However, these conditions all reduce GSK3beta activity throughout the cell. Therefore, we devised a method to selectively inhibit nuclear GSK3beta, the pool that is activated by p53. For this purpose, the inhibitory GBP (19, 26) was stably expressed by using a vector with a nuclear localization sequence. Immunoblots confirmed the exclusive nuclear localization of expressed GBP (data not shown). Expression of nuclear GBP did not alter camptothecin-induced increases in p53, but effectively attenuated elevations in the level of p21, and PARP proteolysis induced by camptothecin or etoposide even when a higher concentration (5 muM) of camptothecin was tested (Fig. 3D), confirming that nuclear GSK3beta promotes DNA damage-induced, p53-mediated responses. Thus, not only is nuclear GSK3beta activated by association with p53 after treatment with DNA-damaging agents, but activated nuclear GSK3beta contributes substantially to the signaling activities induced by p53. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11651</offset><text>To test whether p53-activated nuclear GSK3beta affected its interactions with other substrates, the levels of beta-catenin were measured because active GSK3beta promotes the degradation of beta-catenin (7, 8). Treatment with camptothecin reduced cytosolic beta-catenin but not membrane-bound beta-catenin, which is sequestered from accessibility by GSK3beta, and this effect was blocked by inhibition of GSK3beta with lithium (Fig. 3E).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>12072</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12083</offset><text>This identification of a direct, activating interaction between p53 and GSK3beta reveals new mechanisms that regulate the actions of each of these proteins, provides a mechanistic explanation for several previously reported findings, and raises potentially new therapeutic strategies. Although several studies have reported that GSK3beta is involved in apoptotic signaling, in most cases it was inferred from overexpression or inhibition of GSK3beta. When endogenous GSK3beta was found to be activated during apoptosis, the mechanism was attributed to changes in the phosphorylation state of GSK3beta (7-12). The observed activation of GSK3beta in response to DNA damage, which previously was not known to activate GSK3beta, is unique because the phosphorylation state of GSK3beta was unaltered and only nuclear GSK3beta was activated, although the majority of cellular GSK3beta is in the cytosol (13). It is now evident that these unique features are caused by the mechanism found to activate GSK3beta after DNA damage, the association with p53, and the predominantly nuclear localization of p53. It is intriguing to note that this interaction provides a mechanism for p53 to down-regulate several survival-promoting transcription factors that are known to be phosphorylated by GSK3beta in the nucleus (reviewed in ref. 8), the inhibition of which would promote p53's activation of the apoptotic program. Previously GSK3beta was known to be regulated by protein complex formation, because axin and axin-related proteins can facilitate the phosphorylation of beta-catenin by GSK3beta (7, 8, 18, 20), and other GSK3beta-binding proteins such as GBP can inhibit this process (7, 8, 15, 19, 20). However, the regulation of GSK3beta by protein complexes was known only to occur in the context of the Wnt/wingless signaling pathway. Thus, activation of GSK3beta by binding to p53 reveals that protein complexes outside the Wnt/wingless pathway also regulate the activity of GSK3beta, which raises the possibility that additional proteins bind and regulate GSK3beta independently of Wnt/wingless signaling. This interaction likely accounts for the findings that (i) expression of dominant negative p53 blocked apoptosis induced by overexpression of GSK3beta (10), (ii) activation of Akt (protein kinase B), which inhibits GSK3beta, is inhibitory for p53-mediated transcriptional and apoptotic activities (27-29), and (iii) activated p53 down-regulates beta-catenin (30), because GSK3beta promotes proteolysis of beta-catenin (7). Furthermore, the broad cell survival-promoting effects of the GSK3beta inhibitor lithium (8, 31, 32) may be attributable partly to attenuated p53 function (32, 33) consequential to GSK3beta inhibition such as in ischemic brain, where lithium is protective (31). The revelation that GSK3beta modulates p53 function presents opportunities for regulating the effects of p53. For example, chemotherapeutic p53-mediated signaling could be enhanced by activating GSK3beta, and p53-mediated neuronal loss may be attenuated by inhibitors of GSK3beta, although potential proliferative/cancerous effects must be assessed. Thus, these findings reveal mechanisms involved in DNA damage-induced intracellular signaling and raise possibilities for pharmacologically modulating cellular responses to DNA damage.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>15348</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>15367</offset><text>Camptothecin treatment activates p53, caspase-3, and GSK3beta. Cells in serum-free medium (2 h) were treated with 1 muM camptothecin for 1-5 h (A) or 0, 0.3, 1, or 3 muM camptothecin for 3 h (B). p53 and p21 levels and cleavage of intact PARP (116 kDa) to a stable breakdown product (85 kDa) were measured by immunoblot analysis, and caspase-3 activity (means +- SEM; n = 3) was measured by cleavage of a fluorogenic substrate, Ac-DEVD-AMC, as described (11). (C) GSK3beta activity was measured by immunoprecipitating GSK3beta from cells treated with 1 muM camptothecin for 0, 2, 3, 4 or 5 h and measuring the phosphorylation of recombinant tau by using [32P]ATP as described (13). (D) Cytosolic and nuclear fractions were prepared as described (13), followed by immunoprecipitation of GSK3beta (IP'd GSK3beta). Treatment with 1 muM camptothecin (CT) for 3 h did not alter the levels of GSK3beta in either compartment but increased the activity of GSK3beta in the nucleus but not the cytosol. Nuclear GSK3beta activity was time-dependently increased from 1 to 5 h after treatment with 1 muM camptothecin. (E) After treatment with 30 muM etoposide (4 h) GSK3beta was immunoprecipitated from nuclear fractions, and immunoprecipitants were used to immunoblot levels of p53 and GSK3beta and measure the activity of GSK3beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>16668</offset><text>p53 associates with and activates GSK3beta. (A) The phosphorylation state of nuclear and cytosolic GSK3beta was measured after treatment with 1 muM camptothecin for 0-4 h. Phospho-Ser-9-GSK3beta immunoreactivity was unaltered by camptothecin treatment. (B) p53 coimmunoprecipitated with nuclear GSK3beta. Cells were treated with 1 muM camptothecin for 0-5 h, nuclear fractions were prepared, GSK3beta was immunoprecipitated, and the immunoprecipitates were immunoblotted for GSK3beta and p53, which increased time-dependently in the GSK3beta-immunoprecipitates after camptothecin treatment. (C) Transient expression of wild-type (w-t) p53 but not mutant p53 (R175H) in p53-null H1299 lung carcinoma cells (O) increased the activity of nuclear GSK3beta. p53 or p53 (R175H) was transiently expressed, and after 24 h, nuclear fractions were prepared. GSK3beta was immunoprecipitated from the nuclear fraction, GSK3beta activity was measured, and immunoprecipitates were immunoblotted for GSK3beta and p53. (D) p53 activates GSK3beta. The activity of recombinant GSK3beta was measured in the presence of 0-30 ng of recombinant p53, and the time-dependent phosphorylation of recombinant tau by recombinant GSK3beta was measured in the absence (-) and presence (+) of 50 ng of recombinant p53.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>17936</offset><text>Inhibition of GSK3beta attenuates p53-mediated increases in p21 levels and PARP proteolysis. Preincubation for 1 h with inhibitors of GSK3beta, 20 mM lithium or 5 mM sodium valproate (VPA), attenuated 1 muM camptothecin-induced increases in p21 levels and PARP proteolysis (A) and attenuated these responses to treatment with 10 muM etoposide (B). (C) PARP proteolysis induced by treatment with 1 muM camptothecin (CT) was attenuated in cells stably expressing a dominant negative mutant of GSK3beta (dn-GSK3beta), whereas increases in p53 levels were the same as in control cells. (D) Expression of nuclear GBP did not alter camptothecin-induced increases in p53 but reduced p21 levels and PARP proteolysis, reduced PARP proteolysis after treatment with 30 muM etoposide (Etop), and reduced PARP proteolysis induced by treatment with either 1 or 5 muM camptothecin. NLS, nuclear localization signal. (E) beta-Catenin levels were reduced by camptothecin-induced activation of GSK3beta. beta-Catenin was immunoblotted in nuclear, cytosolic, and membrane fractions prepared after treatment with 20 mM lithium (Li) for 4 h, 1 muM camptothecin for 3 h, or both agents (Li+CT).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>19095</offset><text>Abbreviations</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19109</offset><text>GSK3beta</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19116</offset><text>glycogen synthase kinase-3beta</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19145</offset><text>GBP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19149</offset><text>GSK3beta-binding protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19172</offset><text>PARP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19177</offset><text>poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">777</infon><infon key="lpage">783</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rich;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Allen;given-names:R L</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Wyllie;given-names:A H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11048728</infon><infon key="source">Nature (London)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">407</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19205</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">433</infon><infon key="lpage">439</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zhou;given-names:B B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Elledge;given-names:S J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11100718</infon><infon key="source">Nature (London)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">408</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19206</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">117</infon><infon key="lpage">122</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bartek;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lukas;given-names:J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11223026</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">490</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>19207</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">307</infon><infon key="lpage">310</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vogelstein;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lane;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Levine;given-names:A J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11099028</infon><infon key="source">Nature (London)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">408</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19208</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">880</infon><infon key="lpage">888</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Miller;given-names:F D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pozniak;given-names:C D</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Walsh;given-names:G S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11279533</infon><infon key="source">Cell Death Differ</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19209</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">868</infon><infon key="lpage">879</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Morrison;given-names:R S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kinoshita;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11279532</infon><infon key="source">Cell Death Differ</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19210</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">471</infon><infon key="lpage">479</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ferkey;given-names:D M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kimelman;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10985864</infon><infon key="source">Dev Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">225</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19211</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">391</infon><infon key="lpage">426</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Grimes;given-names:C A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Jope;given-names:R S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11527574</infon><infon key="source">Prog Neurobiol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">65</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>19212</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">7789</infon><infon key="lpage">7793</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Takashima;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Noguchi;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sato;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Hoshino;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Imahori;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8356085</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">90</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>19213</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">19929</infon><infon key="lpage">19932</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pap;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Cooper;given-names:G M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9685326</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">273</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>19214</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">7583</infon><infon key="lpage">7590</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bijur;given-names:G N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:De Sarno;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Jope;given-names:R S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10713065</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">275</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19215</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2567</infon><infon key="lpage">2574</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hetman;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Cavanaugh;given-names:J E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kimelman;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Xia;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10729337</infon><infon key="source">J Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19216</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">37436</infon><infon key="lpage">37442</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bijur;given-names:G N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Jope;given-names:R S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11495916</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>19217</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">39927</infon><infon key="lpage">39934</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zhu;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zhang;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Jiang;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Chen;given-names:X</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10982799</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">275</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19218</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">125</infon><infon key="lpage">141</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Johnson;given-names:G V W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hartigan;given-names:J A</infon><infon key="source">Alzheimer's Dis Rev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>19219</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">15</infon><infon key="lpage">19</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sutherland;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Leighton;given-names:I A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cohen;given-names:P</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8250835</infon><infon key="source">Biochem J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">296</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>19220</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">803</infon><infon key="lpage">808</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hughes;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Nikolakaki;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Plyte;given-names:S E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Totty;given-names:N F</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Woodgett;given-names:J R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8382613</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>19221</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1371</infon><infon key="lpage">1384</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ikeda;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kishida;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Yamamoto;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Murai;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Koyama;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Kikuchi;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9482734</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>19222</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1031</infon><infon key="lpage">1041</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Yost;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Farr;given-names:G H;suffix:3rd</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Pierce;given-names:S B</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ferkey;given-names:D M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Chen;given-names:M M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Kimelman;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9635432</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">93</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>19223</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4233</infon><infon key="lpage">4240</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Li;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Yuan;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Weaver;given-names:C D</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Mao;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Farr;given-names:G H;suffix:3rd</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Sussman;given-names:D J</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Jonkers;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Kimelman;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Wu;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10428961</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>19224</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">8455</infon><infon key="lpage">8459</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Klein;given-names:P S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Melton;given-names:D A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8710892</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">93</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>19225</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1664</infon><infon key="lpage">1668</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Stambolic;given-names:V</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ruel;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Woodgett;given-names:J R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8994831</infon><infon key="source">Curr Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>19226</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">95</infon><infon key="lpage">105</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Davies;given-names:S P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Reddy;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Caivano;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Cohen;given-names:P</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10998351</infon><infon key="source">Biochem J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">351</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19227</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">789</infon><infon key="lpage">813</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Phiel;given-names:C J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Klein;given-names:P S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11264477</infon><infon key="source">Annu Rev Pharmacol Toxicol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">41</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>19228</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1327</infon><infon key="lpage">1330</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chen;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Huang;given-names:L D</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Jiang;given-names:Y M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Manji;given-names:H K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10037507</infon><infon key="source">J Neurochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">72</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>19229</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">691</infon><infon key="lpage">702</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Farr;given-names:G H;suffix:3rd</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ferkey;given-names:D M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Yost;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Pierce;given-names:S B</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Weaver;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Kimelman;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10684251</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">148</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19230</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">24263</infon><infon key="lpage">24269</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sabbatini;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:McCormick;given-names:F</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10446202</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>19231</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5390</infon><infon key="lpage">5394</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Mitsuuchi;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Johnson;given-names:S W</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Selvakumaran;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Williams;given-names:S J</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Hamilton;given-names:T C</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Testa;given-names:J R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11034077</infon><infon key="source">Cancer Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">60</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><offset>19232</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5256</infon><infon key="lpage">5264</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Yamaguchi;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tamatani;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Matsuzaki;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Namikawa;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kiyama;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Vitek;given-names:M P</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Mitsuda;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Tohyama;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11054421</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>19233</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">6768</infon><infon key="lpage">6781</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sadot;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Geiger;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Oren;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Ben-Ze'ev;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11564862</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><offset>19234</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2081</infon><infon key="lpage">2084</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nonaka;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Chuang;given-names:D M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9674597</infon><infon key="source">NeuroReport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>19235</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">6039</infon><infon key="lpage">6042</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chen;given-names:R W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Chuang;given-names:D M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10037682</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>19236</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1123</infon><infon key="lpage">1125</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lu;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Song;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Jope;given-names:R S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10321495</infon><infon key="source">NeuroReport</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><offset>19237</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>19238</offset><text>This paper was submitted directly (Track II) to the PNAS office.</text></passage></document></collection>
