<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>sentence.key</key><document><id>z</id><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Hammer;given-names:Gary D.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gummow;given-names:Brian M.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:O'Leary;given-names:Erin E.</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">12861022</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kennell;given-names:Jennifer A.</infon><infon key="fpage">5366</infon><infon key="issue">15</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc"></infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">0417</infon><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1128/MCB.23.15.5366-5375.2003</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">23</infon><infon key="journal-title">Molecular and Cellular Biology</infon><infon key="lpage">5375</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:MacDougald;given-names:Ormond A.</infon><offset>0</offset><text>T-Cell Factor 4N (TCF-4N), a Novel Isoform of Mouse TCF-4, Synergizes with beta-Catenin To Coactivate C/EBPalpha and Steroidogenic Factor 1 Transcription Factors</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>157</offset><text>We have cloned T-cell factor 4N (TCF-4N), an alternative isoform of TCF-4, from developing pituitary and 3T3-L1 preadipocytes. This protein contains the N-terminal interaction domain for beta-catenin but lacks the DNA binding domain. While TCF-4N inhibited coactivation by beta-catenin of a TCF/lymphoid-enhancing factor (LEF)-dependent promoter, TCF-4N potentiated coactivation by beta-catenin of several non-TCF/LEF-dependent promoters. For example, TCF-4N synergized with beta-catenin to activate the alpha-inhibin promoter through functional and physical interactions with the orphan nuclear receptor steroidogenic factor 1 (SF-1). In addition, TCF-4N and beta-catenin synergized with the adipogenic transcription factor CCAAT/enhancer binding protein alpha (C/EBPalpha) to induce leptin promoter activity. The mechanism by which beta-catenin and TCF-4N coactivated C/EBPalpha appeared to involve p300, based upon synergy between these important transcriptional regulators. Consistent with TCF-4N's redirecting the actions of beta-catenin in cells, ectopic expression of TCF-4N in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes partially relieved the block of adipogenesis caused by beta-catenin. Thus, we propose that TCF-4N inhibits coactivation by beta-catenin of TCF/LEF transcription factors and potentiates the coactivation by beta-catenin of other transcription factors, such as SF-1 and C/EBPalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1509</offset><text>Wnts are a family of secreted proteins that play important roles in essentially all aspects of cell fate. Wnts act through Frizzled receptors and low-density lipoprotein receptor-related protein coreceptors to activate several signaling pathways (19, 41). In the canonical pathway, Wnt signaling inhibits glycogen synthase kinase 3, resulting in hypophosphorylation and subsequent stabilization of beta-catenin. After translocation to the nucleus, beta-catenin binds to and coactivates members of the T-cell factor/lymphoid-enhancing factor (TCF/LEF) family of transcription factors, thus mediating the effects of Wnt on gene expression. Wnts regulate the development of many cell types (2, 14, 29, 45). In addition to regulating differentiation of lymphocytes, intestinal crypt cells, and keratinocytes, we recently established that Wnts are key regulators of preadipocyte differentiation (1, 37). Wnt10b is the best candidate for the endogenous inhibitory Wnt because this protein blocks adipocyte conversion and expression of Wnt10b is high in preadipocytes and declines upon induction of differentiation. In addition to regulation of adipogenesis, Wnts play a larger role in preadipocytes, as Wnt1 inhibits preadipocyte apoptosis through induction of insulin-like growth factors (20).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2794</offset><text>The genetic program of adipogenesis has been studied extensively in vitro, with embryonic fibroblasts and preadipocyte lines, and in vivo, with transgenic and knockout mouse models (21, 22, 26, 32, 34), and a paradigm for the cascade of genetic events has emerged. After induction of differentiation, there is a rapid and transient induction of CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein beta (C/EBPbeta) and C/EBPdelta. These transcription factors then activate expression of both C/EBPalpha and peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma (PPARgamma), which then reinforce each other's expression through a positive feedback loop. Activation of the canonical Wnt signaling pathway by Wnt10b, dominant stable beta-catenin, or inhibition of glycogen synthase kinase 3 inhibits adipogenesis by blocking expression of C/EBPalpha and PPARgamma (1, 37). While expression of Wnt10b declines during adipogenesis, levels of nuclear beta-catenin remain elevated until after C/EBPalpha and PPARgamma are induced, suggesting that beta-catenin has additional roles other than inhibition of adipogenesis through TCF/LEF transcription factors. In support for this idea, beta-catenin coactivates non-TCF/LEF transcription factors such as androgen receptor, retinoic acid receptor, and steroidogenic factor 1 (SF-1) (4, 25, 39, 48).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4074</offset><text>Endogenous Wnt signaling inhibits adipogenesis through activation of the canonical pathway and activation of TCF/LEF transcription factors (37). The four members of the mammalian TCF/LEF family of transcription factors all have an N-terminal beta-catenin-interacting domain and a highly conserved HMG box DNA binding domain (46). Heterogeneity in TCF/LEFs arises through multiple mechanisms. For example, forms of TCF-1 and LEF-1 that lack the beta-catenin-interacting domain result from alternative promoter usage (13, 33). Similar forms of TCF-4 and LEF-1 that have been engineered to lack the beta-catenin-interacting domain are commonly used as dominant negative inhibitors of TCF/LEF action. In addition, members of this family are also subject to extensive alternative splicing C-terminal to the HMG box. We recently reported several alternatively spliced isoforms of mouse TCF-4 that are truncated N-terminal to the HMG box domain (3). One of these isoforms, TCF-4N, was identified in developing pituitary and subsequently in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes and adipocytes. While TCF-4N does not contain a DNA binding domain, it retains the region involved in binding beta-catenin. A similar alternatively spliced LEF-1 was identified in humans, but a function was not reported (18).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5346</offset><text>Here we report that TCF-4N has multiple roles in regulation of transcription. While TCF-4N interacts with beta-catenin and inhibits a TCF/LEF-responsive promoter, TCF-4N also interacts with beta-catenin to activate promoters that are not responsive to TCF/LEFs. For example, TCF-4N synergizes with beta-catenin to coactivate the orphan nuclear receptor SF-1. In addition, TCF-4N interacts functionally with beta-catenin and p300 to coactivate the adipogenic transcription factor C/EBPalpha. Ectopic expression of TCF-4N in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes partially relieves the block of adipogenesis caused by dominant stable beta-catenin, consistent with a model in which TCF-4N regulates Wnt signaling by redirecting beta-catenin from TCF/LEF transcription factors to other transcription factors, including SF-1 and C/EBPalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>6147</offset><text>MATERIALS AND METHODS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6169</offset><text>Cell culture.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6183</offset><text>Mouse 3T3-L1 preadipocytes and human embryonic kidney 293T cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (Life Technologies, Inc.) containing 10% calf serum (Sigma) as previously described (42). Y1 adrenocortical carcinoma cells were cultured in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium containing 7.5% horse serum (Invitrogen) and 2.5% fetal bovine serum (Invitrogen). 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were induced to differentiate into adipocytes 2 days after confluence as described previously (11). To visualize cytoplasmic lipid accumulation, 3T3-L1 cells were stained with Oil Red-O (31). To quantify retention of Oil Red-O, stained adipocytes were extracted with 1 ml of 4% Igepal CA-630 (Sigma) in isopropanol for 15 min, and absorbance was measured by spectrophotometry at 520 nm (1). Nuclear extracts were prepared essentially as described previously (5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>7045</offset><text>TCF-4N expression and retroviral plasmids.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7088</offset><text>TCF-4N (see Fig. 1A) was amplified from embryonic day 12.5 developing mouse pituitary gland by reverse transcription-PCR and subcloned into pcDNA3.1+ (Invitrogen) as described previously (3). An N-terminal deletion of the first 31 amino acids (DeltaNTCF-4N) was generated by PCR with TCF-4N as a template (see Fig. 1B). The forward primer (5'-GGATCCACCATGTCGGAAAACTCCTC-3') included a consensus start site of translation downstream of a BamHI restriction site, while the reverse primer (5'-TTATACCCGCACATGTCCAC-3') recognized the unique 3' untranslated region of TCF-4N. The resulting PCR fragment was subcloned into pCR2.1 (Invitrogen). The BamHI-XhoI fragment was then subcloned into the BamHI and XhoI sites of pcDNA3-AU1/Flag. To create a retroviral expression vector for TCF-4N, the HindIII-XhoI fragment from TCF-4N in pcDNA3.1+ was subcloned into the HindIII and XhoI sites of pTS13 containing a HindIII linker.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>8014</offset><text>Luciferase reporter gene assays.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8047</offset><text>The following reporter genes were used: pTOPFLASH and pFOPFLASH (Upstate Biotechnology), cyclin D1-luciferase, mutant TCF(1) and mutant TCF(0-4) (human cyclin D1 [-961]; Frank McCormick, University of California-San Francisco), (Gal4)5-SV40-luciferase (Mitchell A. Lazar, University of Pennsylvania), alpha-inhibin-luciferase (Kelly Mayo, Northwestern University), LexA-luciferase (Holly Ingraham, University of Californi-San Francisco), and leptin-luciferase and mutant leptin-luciferase (M. Daniel Lane, Johns Hopkins University). Expression constructs for mutant human beta-catenin containing an in-frame N-terminal deletion of amino acids 29 to 48 and DeltaNTCF-4E were provided by Frank McCormick (University of California-San Francisco). The expression construct for TCF-4N was described previously (3), and the expression vector for TCF-4E was from Gregory Dressler (University of Michigan).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8940</offset><text>The mouse C/EBPalpha expression vector was described previously (36). An expression construct for a fusion protein of the Gal4 DNA binding domain and beta-catenin, Gal4-betaCat, was provided by Kun-Liang Guan (University of Michigan). Expression vectors for mouse SF-1 and a fusion between the LexA DNA binding domain and SF-1 were from Holly Ingraham (University of California-San Francisco). The expression vector encoding a fusion protein of the Gal4 DNA binding domain and the C/EBPalpha transactivation domain, Gal4-C/EBPalpha, was described previously (5). Expression vectors for a deletion mutant of C/EBPalpha lacking all conserved regions but CR2 (CR2-C/EBPalpha) and a deletion mutant lacking CR2 (CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha) were described previously (5). The human p300 expression vector pVR1012-p300 was obtained from Gary Nabel (National Institutes of Health).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9785</offset><text>Human embryonic kidney 293T cells (40-mm plates) were transiently transfected by calcium phosphate coprecipitation with 4 mug of total DNA, including the luciferase reporter gene (as indicated), and 250 ng of cytomegalovirus beta-galactosidase. Additional plasmid DNAs were varied, based upon experimental conditions, and are documented in the figure legends. A constant amount of total cytomegalovirus promoter (pcDNA3.1; Invitrogen) was maintained to control for potential squelching of the transcriptional machinery. After transfection, cells were incubated for 48 h and lysed. Luciferase activity was measured, and variations in transfection efficiency were accounted for by normalization against beta-galactosidase activity (5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>10515</offset><text>Retroviral infection of 3T3-L1 preadipocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10561</offset><text>293T cells (10-cm plates) were transfected by calcium phosphate coprecipitation with control (pTS13) or TCF-4N retroviral vectors and the viral packaging vectors SV-E-MLV-env and SVpsi-E-MLV (7.5 mug of each). Virus-containing medium was collected 16 h after transfection and passed through a 0.45-mum syringe filter. Polybrene (hexadimethrine bromide; Sigma) was added to a final concentration of 8 mug/ml. This medium was then applied to subconfluent ( 30%) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes (10-cm plates). The infection protocol was repeated every 8 to 16 h until cells were  80% confluent. These cells were trypsin treated and replated in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium supplemented with 10% calf serum and 150 mug of hygromycin (Invitrogen) per ml for 5 days. Cells were then infected with control (PGS-CMV-CITE-neo) or S33Y beta-catenin-expressing retroviruses (Eric Fearon, University of Michigan) and selected with 400 mug of geneticin (Life Technologies, Inc.) per ml, and the ability to undergo adipogenesis was evaluated.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>11587</offset><text>Immunoprecipitation and immunoblot analyses.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11632</offset><text>For immunoprecipitation of TCF-4N with beta-catenin, 293T cells (10-cm plates) were transiently transfected with 10 mug of expression vectors for Myc-tagged mutant beta-catenin, TCF-4N, or DeltaNTCF-4N as indicated. Cells were lysed in 50 mM HEPES (pH 7.5)-125 mM NaCl-1 mM EDTA (pH 8.0)-1 mM dithiothreitol-1% Igepal CA-630 and protease inhibitors. Lysates were cleared with protein G plus agarose (Santa Cruz) and incubated with 4 mul of anti-Myc tag clone 9E10 (Upstate Biotechnology). Protein G plus agarose was added to samples, and after incubation for 1 h, pellets were washed and resuspended in sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) loading buffer. Immunoblot analysis was performed with mouse monoclonal immunoglobulin G against TCF-3 and TCF-4 (Upstate Biotechnology) and beta-catenin (Transduction Laboratories).</text><annotation id="0"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="11632" length="215"/><text>For immunoprecipitation of TCF-4N with beta-catenin, 293T cells (10-cm plates) were transiently transfected with 10 mug of expression vectors for Myc-tagged mutant beta-catenin, TCF-4N, or DeltaNTCF-4N as indicated.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12438</offset><text>For immunoprecipitation of beta-catenin with SF-1, nuclear lysates were generated from Y1 adrenocortical carcinoma cells. Briefly, cell membranes were disrupted in a buffer containing 25 mM HEPES (pH 7.6), 5 mM KCl, 0.5 mM MgCl2, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, and 0.5% Igepal CA-630. Nuclei were lysed for 1 h in a buffer containing 25 mM HEPES, 10% sucrose, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 0.01% Igepal CA-630, and 350 mM NaCl, and insoluble proteins were removed by centrifugation. Nuclear lysates were cleared with protein A/G-agarose for 30 min and incubated with antihemagglutinin (anti-HA) antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) or anti-SF-1 antibody (Upstate Biotechnology). Protein A/G-agarose was added to the samples, and after incubation for 1 h, pellets were washed and resuspended in SDS loading buffer. Immunoblot analysis was performed with mouse monoclonal antibody against beta-catenin (Transduction Laboratories).</text><annotation id="1"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="12438" length="121"/><text>For immunoprecipitation of beta-catenin with SF-1, nuclear lysates were generated from Y1 adrenocortical carcinoma cells.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13415</offset><text>Immunoprecipitations of C/EBPalpha with beta-catenin were done essentially as described previously (27). After transient transfection of 293T cells (10-cm plates) with 5 mug of expression vectors for S33Y beta-catenin-Flag (Eric Fearon, University of Michigan), p42C/EBPalpha, and CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha, cells were lysed in 0.5 ml of buffer A (20 mM HEPES [pH 7.9], 350 mM NaCl, 30 mM MgCl2, 1 mM EDTA [pH 8.0], 0.1 mM EGTA [pH 8.0], 20% glycerol, 0.5% Igepal CA-630, 1 mM dithiothreitol, and protease inhibitors). After centrifugation, lysates were diluted with 0.75 ml of buffer B (20 mM HEPES [pH 7.9], 30 mM MgCl2, 1 mM EDTA [pH 8.0], 0.1 mM EGTA [pH 8.0], 20% glycerol, 0.2% Igepal CA-630, 1 mM dithiothreitol, and protease inhibitors). Lysates were cleared with protein A-Sepharose (Pharmacia), split in half, and incubated overnight with either 1 mul of anti-Flag M2 (Sigma) or 1 mul of negative control immunoglobulin G (PPARgamma mouse monoclonal; Santa Cruz) as indicated. Protein A-Sepharose was added to the samples, and after incubation for 1 h, pellets were washed with wash buffer A containing 150 mM NaCl. Proteins were eluted by incubation with competitive Flag peptide (Sigma) overnight, separated by sodium dodecyl sulfate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE), and transferred to a polyvinylidene difluoride membrane. After blocking, the membrane was incubated with mouse monoclonal antibody against beta-catenin (Transduction Laboratories) or rabbit polyclonal antibody against C/EBPalpha (Daniel Lane, Johns Hopkins University).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>14950</offset><text>RESULTS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>14958</offset><text>TCF-4N, an alternatively spliced isoform of TCF-4, lacks DNA binding domain but retains beta-catenin-interacting domain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15077</offset><text>Novel isoforms of mouse TCF-4 lacking the HMG box DNA binding domain were first identified in embryonic mouse pituitary gland (3). We also cloned a similar isoform of TCF-4 from 3T3-L1 preadipocytes. The mRNA for this novel isoform contained a stop codon that terminated translation of the protein prior to the DNA binding domain. We designated this protein TCF-4N because it contained only the N terminus (Fig. 1A). Transfection of a fusion protein containing TCF-4N and green fluorescent protein indicated expression in both nuclear and cytoplasmic compartments (data not shown). In addition, we identified a bovine expressed sequence tag (EST) (GenBank accession number BE749318) with homology to TCF-3 that contains a stop codon at the same site as in TCF-4N. These data, together with the identification of a similar isoform of human LEF-1 (18), suggest a conserved role for isoforms such as TCF-4N in regulating transcription.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16010</offset><text>TCF-4N retains the beta-catenin-interacting domain at the N terminus.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16078</offset><text>To determine whether TCF-4N interacts physically with beta-catenin, we performed a coimmunoprecipitation analysis (Fig. 1C). Expression constructs for TCF-4N and DeltaNTCF-4N, an N-terminal deletion mutant (Fig. 1B), were cotransfected into 293T cells with an expression construct for dominant stable Myc-tagged beta-catenin. As expected, TCF-4N was immunoprecipitated with beta-catenin (Fig. 1C), similar to full-length TCF-4E (data not shown). However, DeltaNTCF-4N was not immunoprecipitated by beta-catenin (Fig. 1C), suggesting that TCF-4N interacts with beta-catenin via an interaction at the N terminus.</text><annotation id="2"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="16078" length="119"/><text>To determine whether TCF-4N interacts physically with beta-catenin, we performed a coimmunoprecipitation analysis (Fig.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16673</offset><text>TCF-4N inhibits activation by beta-catenin of a TCF-responsive reporter gene.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16749</offset><text>beta-Catenin is a coactivator of TCF/LEF transcription factors. Unlike previously described TCF/LEF isoforms, TCF-4N lacks a DNA binding domain; however, TCF-4N retains its ability to interact with beta-catenin (Fig. 1C). We hypothesized that TCF-4N acts as an endogenous inhibitor of beta-catenin by competing with DNA-bound TCF/LEF transcription factors for binding to beta-catenin. To determine if TCF-4N inhibits transcriptional coactivation by beta-catenin, we performed luciferase reporter assays with pTOPFLASH, a TCF-responsive reporter gene that contains multimerized TCF binding sites upstream of a minimal promoter and the coding sequence for luciferase.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17405</offset><text>Expression constructs for dominant stable beta-catenin, TCF-4N, and DeltaNTCF-4E (Fig. 1B) were transiently transfected into 293T cells along with pTOPFLASH or the negative control pFOPFLASH. As expected, ectopic expression of beta-catenin increased reporter gene activity (Fig. 2). Cotransfection of increasing amounts of TCF-4N progressively decreased the reporter activity in response to beta-catenin, similar to the inhibitory effect of the well-established dominant negative form of TCF, DeltaNTCF-4E (Fig. 2) (44). TCF-4N had no effect on reporter activity in the absence of ectopic beta-catenin (data not shown). In addition, neither beta-catenin nor TCF-4N influenced gene expression from pFOPFLASH, in which the TCF binding sites are mutated (Fig. 2). These results indicate that TCF-4N acts through a dominant negative mechanism to inhibit activation by beta-catenin of a TCF-responsive promoter.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18294</offset><text>TCF-4N and beta-catenin synergize to activate transcription from non-TCF-responsive promoters.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18387</offset><text>TCF-4N inhibits activation by beta-catenin of the TCF-responsive promoter gene pTOPFLASH (Fig. 2). To determine the effect of TCF-4N and beta-catenin on what has been reported to be a TCF-dependent promoter, we performed luciferase reporter assays with the human cyclin D1 promoter (cyclin D1-luc), which contains one TCF/LEF consensus site and four cryptic binding sites (40, 44). While beta-catenin activated the cyclin D1 promoter (Fig. 3A), TCF-4N alone had no effect (data not shown). In contrast to our hypothesis that TCF-4N would inhibit cyclin D1 promoter activity, cotransfection of TCF-4N with beta-catenin caused an increase in reporter gene expression even in the absence of TCF binding sites, i.e., mtTCF(1) and mtTCF(0-4) (Fig. 3A). Cotransfection of DeltaNTCF-4N had no effect on beta-catenin activation of the cyclin D1 promoter (data not shown), indicating that the N terminus of TCF-4N is necessary for its effect. beta-Catenin activated the mutant cyclin D1 reporter genes independent of DNA binding by TCF/LEF, because cotransfection of DeltaNTCF-4E did not reduce promoter activity for either mutant reporter gene (Fig. 3A). Furthermore, the increase in promoter activity by cotransfection of TCF-4N, despite mutations in the putative TCF binding sites, suggests that beta-catenin activates transcription via interactions with transcription factors other than TCF/LEFs.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19759</offset><text>To verify that TCF-4N enhances transcriptional coactivation by beta-catenin independently of TCF/LEF transcription factors, we performed reporter gene assays with a Gal4 DNA binding domain-beta-catenin fusion protein (Gal4-betaCat) and a Gal4-responsive reporter gene (Fig. 3B). While transfection of Gal4-betaCat activated the Gal4-responsive promoter by approximately100-fold, TCF-4N had no effect on basal promoter activity (data not shown). When TCF-4N was cotransfected with Gal4-betaCat, TCF-4N synergized with beta-catenin, resulting in a dramatic 8- to 12-fold increase in reporter gene activity over that observed with Gal4-betaCat alone (Fig. 3B). Cotransfection of full-length TCF-4E decreased reporter gene activity, presumably by sequestering Gal4-betaCat. DeltaNTCF-4N had no effect on promoter activity, indicating that the N terminus of TCF-4N is required for its functional interaction with beta-catenin. Taken together, these data indicate that for certain non-TCF/LEF-dependent promoters, TCF-4N and beta-catenin synergize to activate gene expression.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>20807</offset><text>beta-Catenin and TCF-4N synergize to coactivate SF-1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20859</offset><text>Our results with the mutant cyclin D1 promoter suggest that beta-catenin interacts functionally with transcription factors other than TCF/LEFs (Fig. 3A). Recent evidence with the Dax-1 promoter supports a role for beta-catenin as a coactivator of SF-1 (25). Expression of this orphan nuclear receptor is restricted to a subset of endocrine tissues, including gonads, adrenal cortex, ventromedial hypothalamus, and pituitary gonadotropes (8). Interestingly, TCF-4N and similar isoforms were first identified in developing and adult pituitary (3).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21401</offset><text>To explore the possibility that TCF-4N potentiates coactivation by beta-catenin of SF-1, we performed reporter assays with the SF-1-dependent inhibin promoter (inhibin-luc) (16, 23). Expression of SF-1 induced inhibin promoter activity, and cotransfection of beta-catenin resulted in an increase above that with SF-1 alone (Fig. 4A). Cotransfection of increasing amounts of TCF-4N synergized with beta-catenin and SF-1 to stimulate a greater than 2.5-fold increase in inhibin promoter activity. The induction of inhibin promoter activity by TCF-4N, beta-catenin, and SF-1 was not influenced by coexpression with the well-established dominant negative TCF DeltaNTCF-4E (data not shown), indicating that the effects are not mediated through TCF/LEF DNA binding sites. The effects of beta-catenin and TCF-4N were largely dependent upon the presence of SF-1 (Fig. 4A). Our data suggest that beta-catenin and TCF-4N synergize to coactivate the orphan nuclear receptor SF-1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22355</offset><text>To verify the functional interaction between SF-1 and a complex containing beta-catenin and TCF-4N, we used a LexA-dependent reporter gene and a fusion construct in which the SF-1 DNA binding domain was replaced with the LexA DNA binding domain (LexASF-1). Expression of LexASF-1 stimulated an increase in reporter gene activity, and this was further increased by cotransfection of LexASF-1 with beta-catenin (Fig. 4B). Coactivation of LexASF-1 by beta-catenin was almost doubled by coexpression of TCF-4N, consistent with our prior observations with the inhibin promoter (Fig. 4A). In contrast, cotransfection of beta-catenin and TCF-4N without SF-1 resulted in no increase in promoter activity (data not shown). These data demonstrate that TCF-4N potentiates the coactivation of SF-1 by beta-catenin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23148</offset><text>The ability of beta-catenin and TCF-4N to coactivate LexASF-1 confirms that the synergy between beta-catenin, TCF-4N, and SF-1 is independent of DNA binding by TCF/LEF transcription factors, raising the possibility that there is a direct physical interaction between SF-1 and beta-catenin. To determine whether beta-catenin and SF-1 interact in vivo, we used immunoprecipitation assays with nuclear lysates prepared from Y1 adrenocortical carcinoma cells, which express both SF-1 and beta-catenin. Consistent with the hypothesis that beta-catenin and SF-1 interact physically, endogenous beta-catenin was coimmunoprecipitated with SF-1 (Fig. 4C). These data indicate that beta-catenin and TCF-4N coactivate SF-1 through direct physical interactions.</text><annotation id="3"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="23438" length="207"/><text>To determine whether beta-catenin and SF-1 interact in vivo, we used immunoprecipitation assays with nuclear lysates prepared from Y1 adrenocortical carcinoma cells, which express both SF-1 and beta-catenin.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>23882</offset><text>beta-Catenin and TCF-4N synergize to coactivate C/EBPalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23937</offset><text>Given the emerging concept that beta-catenin coactivates transcription factors other than TCF/LEFs, we explored the possibility that beta-catenin and TCF-4N coactivate C/EBPalpha, a transcription factor important for adipogenesis. To determine if beta-catenin and TCF-4N functionally interact with C/EBPalpha, we performed reporter gene assays with the leptin promoter (Leptin-luc and mtLeptin-luc). The leptin promoter contains a C/EBP binding site and has been shown to be C/EBPalpha responsive (12, 15). Expression of C/EBPalpha increased leptin reporter gene activity, and coexpression of C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin resulted in an additive increase (Fig. 5A). Cotransfection of TCF-4N with C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin resulted in a synergistic activation of the leptin promoter that was dependent upon the C/EBPalpha binding site (Fig. 5A). The well-established dominant negative TCF DeltaNTCF-4E did not influence the increase of reporter activity by TCF-4N, C/EBPalpha, and beta-catenin (data not shown). In addition, TCF-4N had no effect on C/EBPalpha activation of the leptin promoter in the absence of exogenous beta-catenin (data not shown). The lack of inhibition by DeltaNTCF-4E suggests that beta-catenin and TCF-4N enhance C/EBPalpha activity through a mechanism that is independent of TCF/LEF DNA binding. Because 293T cells express little or no endogenous C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin increased leptin promoter activity even in the absence of C/EBPalpha binding sites (Fig. 5A), it appears that beta-catenin also interacts with other transcriptional regulators of the leptin promoter. Our data suggest that a complex containing beta-catenin and TCF-4N induces leptin promoter activity specifically through coactivation of C/EBPalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25620</offset><text>To verify the functional interactions between beta-catenin, TCF-4N, and C/EBPalpha, we performed luciferase assays with a Gal4-C/EBPalpha expression construct and a Gal4-responsive reporter gene (Fig. 5B). The Gal4-C/EBPalpha chimeric protein consists of the Gal4 DNA binding domain and the C/EBPalpha transactivation domain truncated prior to the leucine zipper. Transfection of Gal4-C/EBPalpha increased reporter gene activity by almost 10-fold (Fig. 5B). While coexpression of beta-catenin with Gal4-C/EBPalpha did not greatly alter promoter activity, TCF-4N synergized with these factors to dramatically increase promoter activity. The effects of TCF-4N required expression of both Gal4-C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin (data not shown). These data provide strong evidence that beta-catenin and TCF-4N are transcriptional coactivators for C/EBPalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26438</offset><text>Regulation of C/EBPalpha activity by beta-catenin in transfected cells raises the issue of whether the endogenous proteins interact within differentiating preadipocytes. To ascertain whether beta-catenin and C/EBPalpha are present at the same time and in the same cellular compartment, we examined expression of these proteins in nuclear extracts prepared from 3T3-L1 cells at various times after induction of differentiation. Nuclear beta-catenin was elevated for the first 3 days of differentiation but declined dramatically by day 4 (Fig. 5C). C/EBPalpha was expressed by day 2 and was maximal by day 3. Thus, beta-catenin is present in the nucleus during the time that C/EBPalpha is inducing expression of PPARgamma and other adipocyte proteins. In addition, RNase protection analysis demonstrated that TCF-4N was expressed throughout differentiation (Fig. 5C).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>27281</offset><text>beta-Catenin and TCF-4N interact with C/EBPalpha and p300 to activate the leptin promoter.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27367</offset><text>Our laboratory and others have shown that the coactivators p300 and CREB binding protein (CBP) functionally interact with C/EBPalpha (5, 9, 38). Given that beta-catenin also interacts with p300/CBP (10, 24, 43), we hypothesized that p300 is a component of the beta-catenin/TCF-4N complex that coactivates C/EBPalpha. Previous analysis of the N-terminal transactivation domain of C/EBPalpha indicated that there were four main conserved regions, designated CR1 to CR4 (Fig. 6A) (6). Of these four regions, CR2 (amino acids 55 to 108) is sufficient to activate transcription and to interact functionally with p300 (5).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27971</offset><text>To determine the domains of C/EBPalpha that mediate functional interactions with the beta-catenin/TCF-4N complex, we performed luciferase assays with the leptin reporter gene (Leptin-luc) and mutants of C/EBPalpha (Fig. 6B). Cotransfection of a C/EBPalpha mutant consisting of CR2 and the bZIP domain (CR2-C/EBPalpha) with beta-catenin/TCF-4N increased leptin reporter activity similar to that in full-length C/EBPalpha, suggesting that CR2 is sufficient for functional interactions between C/EBPalpha and the beta-catenin/TCF-4N complex. Deletion of CR2 (CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha) largely reduced the functional interaction of C/EBPalpha with beta-catenin/TCF-4N (Fig. 6B). Thus, it appears that CR2 is sufficient to mediate coactivation not only by p300, but also by beta-catenin/TCF-4N.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28721</offset><text>Our data suggest that the CR2 region of C/EBPalpha is required for functional interactions with beta-catenin and TCF-4N. To determine whether the CR2 region of C/EBPalpha is necessary for physical interaction between C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin, we performed immunoprecipitation assays with lysates from 293T cells. We cotransfected 293T cells with beta-catenin, p42 C/EBPalpha and CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha, which lacks the CR2 domain. Full-length C/EBPalpha (p42) was immunoprecipitated with beta-catenin, but CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha was not (Fig. 6C). Using similar methods, we also found that beta-catenin was immunoprecipitated with p42C/EBPalpha (data not shown). Taken together, these data suggest that functional interactions between C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin are mediated through direct physical interactions.</text><annotation id="4"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="28842" length="194"/><text>To determine whether the CR2 region of C/EBPalpha is necessary for physical interaction between C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin, we performed immunoprecipitation assays with lysates from 293T cells.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29491</offset><text>Our prior findings indicate that CR2 is the strongest transactivation domain within C/EBPalpha and acts, in part, through the transcriptional coactivator p300 (5). Given that CR2 interacts with beta-catenin/TCF-4N (Fig. 6B and C) and that beta-catenin interacts with p300 (10, 24, 43), it is possible that the transcriptional complex for C/EBPalpha contains beta-catenin, TCF-4N, and p300. To test whether p300 interacts with beta-catenin/TCF-4N to coactivate C/EBPalpha, we performed luciferase assays on cells transfected with the leptin reporter gene and expression constructs for C/EBPalpha, beta-catenin, TCF-4N, and p300, as indicated (Fig. 6D). Cotransfection of p300 resulted in a synergistic increase in promoter activity over that observed with C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin/TCF-4N. A similar but less robust increase was observed with p300, C/EBPalpha, and beta-catenin in the absence of TCF-4N, suggesting a role for TCF-4N in stabilizing interactions between p300 and the transcriptional complex. Taken together, these data support a model in which beta-catenin coactivates C/EBPalpha through a complex that contains TCF-4N and p300.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>30599</offset><text>TCF-4N partially rescues the block of differentiation by ectopic expression of beta-catenin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30690</offset><text>Activation of the canonical Wnt signaling pathway by inhibition of glycogen synthase kinase 3 or enforced expression of beta-catenin blocks adipogenesis through activation of TCF/LEF target genes (1, 35, 37). Our results indicate that TCF-4N decreases coactivation of TCF/LEF family members by beta-catenin yet enhances coactivation of other transcription factors, including C/EBPalpha. To determine if TCF-4N alters the ability of beta-catenin to block differentiation, we stably expressed beta-catenin alone or beta-catenin with TCF-4N by sequential retroviral infections (Fig. 7A and B). Control 3T3-L1 preadipocytes and those expressing TCF-4N differentiated fully in response to inducers of adipogenesis (Fig. 7A). While expression of beta-catenin blocked the differentiation of 3T3-L1 preadipocytes, coexpression with TCF-4N resulted in more cells undergoing adipogenesis than observed with beta-catenin alone (Fig. 7A). Expression of exogenous beta-catenin in both cell lines was similar by immunoblot analysis (data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31707</offset><text>We also performed a reciprocal experiment in which control cells and beta-catenin-expressing cells were infected with control or TCF-4N retroviruses (Fig. 7B). This experiment produced similar results, with increased differentiation in cells that expressed beta-catenin and TCF-4N compared to preadipocytes that expressed beta-catenin alone. After extraction and quantification of Oil Red-O, we found that the amount of stain was at least twofold higher in cells that coexpressed beta-catenin and TCF-4N compared to cells that expressed beta-catenin alone (Fig. 7A and B). In addition to increasing amounts of triacylglycerol in these cells, TCF-4N rescued expression of C/EBPalpha (Fig. 7A and B, insets), which is an indicator of adipogenesis. These results are consistent with our reporter gene assays, which indicate that TCF-4N inhibits beta-catenin activation of TCF/LEF target genes and that TCF-4N enhances coactivation by beta-catenin of other transcription factors, such as the adipogenic factor C/EBPalpha.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>32705</offset><text>DISCUSSION</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32716</offset><text>In this study we characterized the function of an alternatively spliced isoform of TCF-4, which we named TCF-4N because it contains the N terminus of the protein. TCF-4N has a translational stop site prior to the DNA binding domain, resulting in a stable protein that retains the ability to bind beta-catenin (Fig. 1C). TCF-4N inhibits the activation by beta-catenin of TOPFLASH, a TCF-dependent promoter, similar to the well-established dominant negative TCF DeltaNTCF-4E (Fig. 2). However, TCF-4N enhances the activation by beta-catenin of TCF-independent promoters, such as the mutant cyclin D1 promoters (Fig. 3A), the SF-1-dependent inhibin promoter (Fig. 4B), the LexA-responsive promoter as activated by LexASF-1 (Fig. 4B), the Gal4-responsive promoter as activated by Gal4-betaCat or Gal4-C/EBPalpha (Fig. 3A and 5B), and the C/EBPalpha-dependent leptin promoter (Fig. 5A). The mechanism by which the beta-catenin/TCF-4N complex coactivates C/EBPalpha appears to involve p300, based upon synergy between these important transcriptional regulators (Fig. 5 and 6). Finally, ectopic expression of TCF-4N in 3T3-L1 preadipocytes partially relieves the block of differentiation caused by beta-catenin (Fig. 7A and B). Thus, we propose that TCF-4N inhibits coactivation by beta-catenin of TCF/LEF transcription factors and enhances the coactivation by beta-catenin of other transcription factors, such as SF-1 (Fig. 4) and the adipogenic transcription factor C/EBPalpha (Fig. 7C).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34168</offset><text>The ability of TCF-4N to partially relieve the inhibition of 3T3-L1 adipogenesis caused by beta-catenin supports the evidence from reporter gene assays that TCF-4N potentiates coactivation by beta-catenin of non-TCF/LEF transcription factors, including the positive regulator of adipogenesis C/EBPalpha (Fig. 5). Rescue of the inhibition of beta-catenin by TCF-4N could potentially be due to inhibition of TCF/LEF-dependent transcription and/or activation of C/EBPalpha and other adipogenic transcription factors. Coactivation of C/EBPalpha by beta-catenin is paradoxical, given the inhibitory effect of Wnt signaling and dominant-stable beta-catenin on adipogenesis. Interestingly, nuclear beta-catenin levels remained elevated for 3 days after induction of adipocyte differentiation (Fig. 5C), despite a decline in the Wnt10b and Frizzled receptors (1). Levels of the adipogenic transcription factors C/EBPalpha and PPARgamma increased during this time and peaked 3 days after induction of differentiation. Since beta-catenin declined after induction of many adipocyte markers and the accumulation of lipid, it appears that beta-catenin has a more complex role during adipogenesis than the strictly antagonistic function predicted by its role in the canonical Wnt signaling pathway.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35422</offset><text>Studies that examined the structure of TCF/LEF transcription factors bound to beta-catenin suggest that they bind as a heterodimer, with a 1:1 stoichiometry (7, 30). As TCF-4N lacks the DNA binding domain and a putative nuclear localization signal, we postulated that TCF-4N could inhibit transcriptional coactivation by beta-catenin by blocking interactions of beta-catenin with DNA-bound TCF/LEF transcription factors. However, the mechanism by which TCF-4N enhances transcriptional coactivation by beta-catenin of target genes is unknown. Protein levels of total exogenous beta-catenin are unaltered by TCF-4N, suggesting that TCF-4N does not increase the stability of beta-catenin (data not shown). beta-Catenin has been reported to be tyrosine phosphorylated, which decreases its affinity for E-cadherin and increases its affinity for TATA binding protein (28); however, we saw no change in tyrosine phosphorylation of beta-catenin when it was coexpressed with TCF-4N (data not shown). However, other important posttranslational modifications of beta-catenin, such as sumoylation or acetylation, may be regulated by TCF-4N (17, 47). Another possibility is that TCF-4N alters the cellular localization of beta-catenin through regulation of the cytosolic/nuclear pool or the membrane-bound pool by an unknown mechanism. However, expression of TCF-4N does not appear to alter the localization of fluorescently tagged beta-catenin (data not shown). Furthermore, the positive effect of TCF-4N on the activity of the Gal4-betaCat fusion protein (Fig. 3B) suggests that the effects of TCF-4N may not involve differences in subcellular localization, as Gal4-betaCat is nuclear due to the Gal4 nuclear localization signal.</text><annotation id="5"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0096</infon><location offset="36125" length="287"/><text>beta-Catenin has been reported to be tyrosine phosphorylated, which decreases its affinity for E-cadherin and increases its affinity for TATA binding protein (28); however, we saw no change in tyrosine phosphorylation of beta-catenin when it was coexpressed with TCF-4N (data not shown).</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37115</offset><text>While the mechanism whereby TCF-4N potentiates transcriptional coactivation by beta-catenin does not appear to involve regulation of beta-catenin stability, tyrosine phosphorylation, or subcellular localization, the positive effect of TCF-4N on beta-catenin may be through the recruitment of transcriptional coactivators. It is well established that beta-catenin physically and functionally interacts with p300 and CBP (10, 24, 43). TCF-4N may stabilize these interactions, because TCF-4N greatly increased the coactivation of C/EBPalpha by p300 and beta-catenin (Fig. 6D). Furthermore, TCF-4N may recruit additional coactivators to the complex that are not recruited by beta-catenin or p300 alone.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37799</offset><text>While we identified and characterized TCF-4N as encoding the N terminus of TCF-4 in the mouse, we also identified by database searches a similar isoform of TCF-3 in cows. Strikingly, the alternative splice site and stop codon are completely conserved between mouse TCF-4N and bovine TCF-3. In addition, another group recently cloned a similarly truncated LEF-1 isoform in humans (18). In contrast to TCF-4N and the putative TCF-3N, which are alternatively spliced and truncated by insertion of a stop codon immediately after the exon junction (3), the novel LEF-1 isoform contains an alternative exon coding for a novel string of amino acids prior to a stop codon. Similar isoforms of LEF-1 in humans, TCF-4 in mice, and TCF-3 in cows suggest a conserved and important role for N-terminal isoforms in regulation of transcription. In this paper we have shown that TCF-4N inhibits TCF/LEF-dependent transcription and stimulates the coactivation by beta-catenin and p300 of other transcription factors, including C/EBPalpha. The effects of TCF-4N on adipogenesis demonstrate its ability to influence cell growth and differentiation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>38924</offset><text>REFERENCES</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="fpage">30998</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12055200</infon><infon key="citation">Bennett, C. N., S. E. Ross, K. A. Longo, L. Bajnok, N. Hemati, K. W. Johnson, S. D. Harrison, and O. A. MacDougald.. Regulation of Wnt signaling during adipogenesis. :-31004.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38935</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="fpage">3286</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9407023</infon><infon key="citation">Cadigan, K. M., and R. Nusse.. Wnt signaling: a common theme in animal development. :-3305.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38936</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="fpage">843</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11845287</infon><infon key="citation">Douglas, K. R., M. L. Brinkmeier, J. A. Kennell, P. Eswara, T. A. Harrison, A. I. Patrianakos, B. S. Sprecher, M. A. Potok, R. H. Lyons, Jr., O. A. MacDougald, and S. A. Camper.. Identification of members of the Wnt signaling pathway in the embryonic pituitary gland. :-851.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Mamm. Genome</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38937</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="fpage">1415</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10607566</infon><infon key="citation">Easwaran, V., M. Pishvaian, Salimuddin, and S. Byers.. Cross-regulation of beta-catenin-LEF/TCF and retinoid signaling pathways. :-1418.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38938</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="fpage">16348</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11340085</infon><infon key="citation">Erickson, R. L., N. Hemati, S. E. Ross, and O. A. MacDougald.. p300 coactivates the adipogenic transcription factor C/EBPalpha. :-16355.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38939</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">79</infon><infon key="citation">Erickson, R. L., K. A. Longo, S. E. Ross, N. Hemati, and O. A. MacDougald.. Structure and function of C/EBPalpha, p. -90. In J. M. Ntambi (ed.), Adipocyte biology and hormone signaling. IOS Press, Amsterdam, The Netherlands.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38940</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="fpage">885</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11136974</infon><infon key="citation">Graham, T. A., C. Weaver, F. Mao, D. Kimelman, and W. Xu.. Crystal structure of a beta-catenin/Tcf complex. :-896.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38941</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="fpage">199</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10433862</infon><infon key="citation">Hammer, G. D., and H. A. Ingraham.. Steroidogenic factor-1: its role in endocrine organ development and differentiation. :-223.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Front. Neuroendocrinol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38942</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="fpage">19754</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11901161</infon><infon key="citation">Hartman, H. B., X. Hu, K. X. Tyler, C. K. Dalal, and M. A. Lazar.. Mechanisms regulating adipocyte expression of resistin. :-19761.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38943</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="fpage">1839</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10775268</infon><infon key="citation">Hecht, A., K. Vleminckx, M. P. Stemmler, F. van Roy, and R. Kemler.. The p300/CBP acetyltransferases function as transcriptional coactivators of beta-catenin in vertebrates. :-1850.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38944</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="fpage">25913</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9325324</infon><infon key="citation">Hemati, N., S. E. Ross, R. L. Erickson, G. E. Groblewski, and O. A. MacDougald.. Signaling pathways through which insulin regulates CCAAT/enhancer binding protein alpha (C/EBPalpha) phosphorylation and gene expression in 3T3-L1 adipocytes. Correlation with GLUT4 gene expression. :-25919.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38945</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="fpage">5283</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9030601</infon><infon key="citation">Hollenberg, A. N., V. S. Susulic, J. P. Madura, B. Zhang, D. E. Moller, P. Tontonoz, P. Sarraf, B. M. Spiegelman, and B. B. Lowell.. Functional antagonism between CCAAT/enhancer binding protein-alpha and peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor-gamma on the leptin promoter. :-5290.</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38946</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">28</infon><infon key="fpage">53</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11326276</infon><infon key="citation">Hovanes, K., T. W. Li, J. E. Munguia, T. Truong, T. Milovanovic, J. Lawrence Marsh, R. F. Holcombe, and M. L. Waterman.. Beta-catenin-sensitive isoforms of lymphoid enhancer factor-1 are selectively expressed in colon cancer. :-57.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Nat. Genet.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38947</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="fpage">547</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11532397</infon><infon key="citation">Huelsken, J., and W. Birchmeier.. New aspects of Wnt signaling pathways in higher vertebrates. :-553.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Curr. Opin. Genet. Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38948</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">93</infon><infon key="fpage">873</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8570651</infon><infon key="citation">Hwang, C. S., S. Mandrup, O. A. MacDougald, D. E. Geiman, and M. D. Lane.. Transcriptional activation of the mouse obese (ob) gene by CCAAT/enhancer binding protein alpha. :-877.</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38949</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="fpage">66</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10628748</infon><infon key="citation">Ito, M., Y. Park, J. Weck, K. E. Mayo, and J. L. Jameson.. Synergistic activation of the inhibin alpha-promoter by steroidogenic factor-1 and cyclic adenosine 3',5'-monophosphate. :-81.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Endocrinol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38950</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="fpage">3803</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11997515</infon><infon key="citation">Kadoya, T., Y. H. Suzuki, T., Yukita, A. Fukui, A. Michiue, T. Asahara, T. Tanaka, K. Asashima, and M. Kikuchi.. Desumoylation activity of axam, a novel axin-binding protein, is involved in downregulation of beta-catenin. :-3819.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38951</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">48</infon><infon key="fpage">221</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11440173</infon><infon key="citation">Kobielak, A., K. Kobielak, and W. H. Trzeciak.. A novel isoform of human lymphoid enhancer-binding factor-1 (LEF-1) gene transcript encodes a protein devoid of HMG domain and nuclear localization signal. :-226.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Acta Biochim. Pol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38952</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="fpage">279</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10858654</infon><infon key="citation">Kuhl, M., L. C. Sheldahl, M. Park, J. R. Miller, and R. T. Moon.. The Wnt/Ca2+ pathway: a new vertebrate Wnt signaling pathway takes shape. :-283.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Trends Genet.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38953</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="fpage">1.</infon><infon key="citation">Longo, K. A., J. A. Kennell, M. J. Ochocinska, S. E. Ross, W. S. Wright, and O. A. MacDougald.. Wnt signaling protects 3T3-L1 preadipocytes from apoptosis through induction of insulin-like growth factors. :</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38954</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">64</infon><infon key="fpage">345</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7574486</infon><infon key="citation">MacDougald, O. A., and M. D. Lane.. Transcriptional regulation of gene expression during adipocyte differentiation. :-373.</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Biochem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38955</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="fpage">5</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11750856</infon><infon key="citation">MacDougald, O. A., and S. Mandrup.. Adipogenesis: forces that tip the scales. :-11.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">Trends Endocrinol. Metab.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38956</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="fpage">8817</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8090730</infon><infon key="citation">Matzuk, M. M., M. J. Finegold, J. P. Mather, L. Krummen, H. Lu, and A. Bradley.. Development of cancer cachexia-like syndrome and adrenal tumors in inhibin-deficient mice. :-8821.</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38957</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">275</infon><infon key="fpage">35170</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10906119</infon><infon key="citation">Miyagishi, M., F. R. Hatta, M. Yoshida, E. Araya, N. Nagafuchi, A. Ishihara, S. Nakajima, and T. Fukamizu.. Regulation of Lef-mediated transcription and p53-dependent pathway by associating beta-catenin with CBP/p300. :-35175.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38958</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="fpage">507</infon><infon key="citation">Mizusaki, H., K. Kawabe, T. Mukai, E. Ariyoshi, M. Kasahara, H. Yoshioka, A. Swain, and K. I. Morohashi.. Dax-1 gene transcription is regulated by Wnt4 in the female developing gonad. Mol. Endocrinol. :-519.</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38959</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Morrison, R. F., and S. R. Farmer.. Hormonal signaling and transcriptional control of adipocyte differentiation. J. Nutr. 130:3116S-3121S.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38960</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="fpage">3208</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11731483</infon><infon key="citation">Pedersen, T. A., E. Kowenz-Leutz, A. Leutz, and C. Nerlov.. Cooperation between C/EBPalpha TATA binding protein/TFIIB and SWI/SNF recruiting domains is required for adipocyte differentiation. :-3216.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38961</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="fpage">20436</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11279024</infon><infon key="citation">Piedra, J., M. D. Castano, J. Miravet, S. Dunach, and M. de Herreros.. Regulation of beta-catenin structure and activity by tyrosine phosphorylation. :-20442.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38962</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="fpage">1837</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10921899</infon><infon key="citation">Polakis, P.. Wnt signaling and cancer. :-1851.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38963</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="fpage">1053</infon><infon key="citation">Poy, F., M. Lepourcelet, R. A. Shivdasani, and M. J. Eck.. Structure of a human Tcf-4-beta-catenin complex. :-1057.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38964</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Preece, A.. A manual for histologic technicians. Little Brown, Boston, Mass.</infon><infon key="year">1972</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38965</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">20</infon><infon key="fpage">535</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10940345</infon><infon key="citation">Rangwala, S. M., and M. A. Lazar.. Transcriptional control of adipogenesis. :-559.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Nutr.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38966</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">285</infon><infon key="fpage">1923</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10489374</infon><infon key="citation">Roose, J., G. Huls, M. van Beest, P. Moerer, K. van der Horn, R. Goldschmeding, T. Logtenberg, and H. Clevers.. Synergy between tumor suppressor APC and the beta-catenin-Tcf4 target Tcf1. :-1926.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38967</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="fpage">145</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11031233</infon><infon key="citation">Rosen, E. D., and B. M. Spiegelman.. Molecular regulation of adipogenesis. :-171.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Annu. Rev. Cell. Dev. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38968</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="fpage">5989</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12138207</infon><infon key="citation">Ross, S. E., R. L. Erickson, I. Gerin, P. M. DeRose, L. Bajnok, K. A. Longo, D. E. Misek, R. Kuick, S. M. Hanash, K. B. Atkins, S. M. Andresen, H. I. Nebb, L. Madsen, K. Kristiansen, and O. A. MacDougald.. Microarray analyses during adipogenesis: understanding the effects of Wnt signaling on adipogenesis and the roles of liver X receptor alpha in adipocyte metabolism. :-5999.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38969</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="fpage">8433</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10567568</infon><infon key="citation">Ross, S. E., R. L. Erickson, N. Hemati, and O. A. MacDougald.. Glycogen synthase kinase 3 is an insulin-regulated C/EBPalpha kinase. :-8441.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Cell. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38970</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">289</infon><infon key="fpage">950</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10937998</infon><infon key="citation">Ross, S. E., N. Hemati, K. A. Longo, C. N. Bennett, P. C. Lucas, R. L. Erickson, and O. A. MacDougald.. Inhibition of adipogenesis by Wnt signaling. :-953.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38971</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="fpage">1665</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11579200</infon><infon key="citation">Schaufele, F., J. F. Enwright 3rd, X. Wang, C. Teoh, R. Srihari, R. Erickson, O. A. MacDougald, and R. N. Day.. CCAAT/enhancer binding protein alpha assembles essential cooperating factors in common subnuclear domains. :-1676.</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Mol. Endocrinol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38972</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="fpage">30935</infon><infon key="citation">Sharma, M., W. W. Chuang, and Z. Sun.. Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt stimulates androgen pathway through glycogen synthase kinase 3beta inhibition and nuclear beta-catenin accumulation. J. Biol. Chem. :-30941.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38973</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">96</infon><infon key="fpage">5522</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10318916</infon><infon key="citation">Shtutman, M., J. Zhurinsky, I. Simcha, C. Albanese, M. D'Amico, R. Pestell, and A. Ben-Ze'ev.. The cyclin D1 gene is a target of the beta-catenin/LEF-1 pathway. :-5527.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38974</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="fpage">452</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9825673</infon><infon key="citation">Shulman, J. M., N. Perrimon, and J. D. Axelrod.. Frizzled signaling and the developmental control of cell polarity. :-458.</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">Trends Genet.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38975</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">255</infon><infon key="fpage">4745</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7372608</infon><infon key="citation">Student, A. K., R. Y. Hsu, and M. D. Lane.. Induction of fatty acid synthetase synthesis in differentiating 3T3-L1 preadipocytes. :-4750.</infon><infon key="year">1980</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38976</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">97</infon><infon key="fpage">12613</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11050151</infon><infon key="citation">Sun, Y., F. T. Kolligs, M. O. Hottiger, R. Mosavin, E. R. Fearon, and G. J. Nabel.. Regulation of beta-catenin transformation by the p300 transcriptional coactivator. :-12618.</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38977</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">398</infon><infon key="fpage">422</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10201372</infon><infon key="citation">Tetsu, O., and F. McCormick.. Beta-catenin regulates expression of cyclin D1 in colon carcinoma cells. :-426.</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38978</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">109</infon><infon key="fpage">S13</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11983149</infon><infon key="citation">van de Wetering, M., W. de Lau, and H. Clevers.. WNT signaling and lymphocyte development. (Suppl.):-S19.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38979</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">244</infon><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11900454</infon><infon key="citation">van Noort, M., and H. Clevers.. TCF transcription factors, mediators of Wnt-signaling in development and cancer. :-8.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">Dev. Biol.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38980</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="fpage">25562</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11973335</infon><infon key="citation">Wolf, D., M. Rodova, E. A. Miska, J. P. Calvet, and T. Kouzarides.. Acetylation of beta-catenin by CREB-binding protein (CBP). :-25567.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38981</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="fpage">11336</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11792709</infon><infon key="citation">Yang, F., X. Li, M. Sharma, C. Y. Sasaki, D. L. Longo, B. Lim, and Z. Sun.. Linking beta-catenin to androgen-signaling pathway. :-11344.</infon><infon key="year">2002</infon><infon key="source">J. Biol. Chem.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>38982</offset></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>38983</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>39002</offset><text>TCF-4N, an alternatively spliced isoform of TCF-4, lacks DNA binding domain but retains beta-catenin-interacting domain. (A) The amino acid sequence of TCF-4N (GenBank accession number AF363725), a novel TCF-4 isoform independently cloned from developing mouse pituitary and 3T3-L1 preadipocytes, is schematically diagramed relative to full-length TCF-4E. The beta-catenin interaction domain is depicted as a black box, and the DNA binding domain is depicted as a gray box. (B) Engineered forms of TCF-4E and TCF-4N designed to lack the N-terminal beta-catenin interaction domain (DeltaNTCF-4E and DeltaNTCF-4N) are diagramed. (C) 293T cells in 10-cm plates were transfected with 10 mug each of the indicated expression vectors by calcium phosphate coprecipitation. Cells were lysed after 48 h, and Myc-tagged beta-catenin was immunoprecipitated (IP) with an anti-Myc (alphamyc) antibody. Immunoprecipitated beta-catenin complexes were separated by SDS-PAGE, followed by immunoblot analysis for TCF-4 and beta-catenin. These results are representative of at least three independent experiments.</text><annotation id="6"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="39768" length="122"/><text>Cells were lysed after 48 h, and Myc-tagged beta-catenin was immunoprecipitated (IP) with an anti-Myc (alphamyc) antibody.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>40076</offset><text>TCF-4N inhibits activation by beta-catenin of a TCF-responsive reporter gene. 293T cells were transfected with pTOPFLASH (25 ng), which is a TCF-responsive reporter construct (solid bars), along with expression vectors for beta-catenin (10 ng), TCF-4N (25, 50, or 100 ng) and DeltaNTCF-4E (100 ng) as indicated. pFOPFLASH (25 ng), a reporter containing mutated TCF consensus binding sites, was transfected as a control (open bars). Samples were normalized to beta-galactosidase activity to correct for variations in transfection efficiency. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to pTOPFLASH alone. These results are representative of at least three independent experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>40788</offset><text>TCF-4N and beta-catenin synergize to activate transcription from non-TCF-responsive promoters. (A) 293T cells were transfected with 5 ng of a cyclin D1 promoter-luciferase construct (cyclinD1-luc; black bars), a cyclin D1-luciferase construct with mutations in the consensus TCF binding site, mtTCF(1) (open bars), or with mutations in the one consensus site and four cryptic TCF binding sites, mtTCF(0-4) (grey bars). Reporter genes were cotransfected with expression vectors for beta-catenin (250 ng), TCF-4N (125, 250, and 500 ng), and DeltaNTCF-4E (500 ng) as indicated. Samples were normalized to beta-galactosidase activity to correct for variations in transfection efficiency. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. (B) 293T cells were transfected with a Gal4-responsive reporter gene (250 ng), which contains multimerized Gal4 binding sites upstream of a minimal promoter and the luciferase gene. Cells were cotransfected with expression constructs for the Gal4 DNA binding domain fused to beta-catenin (Gal4-betaCat; 250 ng) and either 125, 250, or 500 ng of TCF-4N (solid bars), TCF-4E (open bars), or DeltaNTCF-4N (gray bars) as indicated. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene with Gal4-betaCat. These results are representative of at least three independent experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>42194</offset><text>TCF-4N and beta-catenin synergize to coactivate SF-1. (A) 293T cells were transfected with an inhibin-luciferase reporter gene (300 ng). Expression constructs for SF-1 (75 ng), beta-catenin (300 ng), and TCF-4N (125, 250, and 500 ng) were cotransfected as indicated. Samples were normalized to beta-galactosidase activity to correct for variations in transfection efficiency. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. (B) 293T cells were cotransfected with a LexA-responsive reporter gene (100 ng) and a LexASF-1 expression construct (10 ng). Expression constructs for beta-catenin (500 ng) and TCF-4N (500 ng) were cotransfected as indicated. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. (C) SF-1 was immunoprecipitated from nuclear lysates of Y1 adrenocortical carcinoma cells. Immunoprecipitated SF-1 complexes were separated by SDS-PAGE, followed by immunoblot analysis for beta-catenin. These results are representative of at least three independent experiments.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>43289</offset><text>TCF-4N and beta-catenin synergize to coactivate C/EBPalpha. (A) 293T cells were transfected with a leptin promoter reporter gene (250 ng; solid bars) or mtLeptin-luc (open bars), containing a mutated C/EBPalpha binding site. Expression constructs for beta-catenin (250 ng), C/EBPalpha (50 ng), and TCF-4N (125, 250, and 500 ng) were cotransfected as indicated. Samples were normalized to beta-galactosidase activity to correct for variations in transfection efficiency. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. (B) 293T cells were cotransfected with a Gal4-responsive reporter gene (250 ng) and an expression construct for the Gal4 DNA binding domain fused to the transactivation and basic region of C/EBPalpha (5 ng). Expression constructs for beta-catenin (250 ng) and TCF-4N (500 ng) were cotransfected as indicated. Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. These results are representative of at least three independent experiments. (C) Nuclear extracts (20 mug) prepared 1 to 4 days after induction of 3T3-L1 cell differentiation were analyzed by immunoblot for expression of beta-catenin and C/EBPalpha. RNA prepared 1 to 4 days after induction of 3T3-L1 cell differentiation was analyzed for expression of TCF-4N by RNase protection assay with a riboprobe specific for the unique 3' untranslated region.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>44719</offset><text>beta-Catenin and TCF-4N interact with C/EBPalpha and p300 to activate the leptin promoter. (A) The amino acid sequence of mouse C/EBPalpha is schematically diagrammed, with the four conserved regions within the transactivation domain indicated. The CR2-C/EBPalpha and CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha deletion constructs are shown schematically relative to full-length p42C/EBPalpha. (B) 293T cells were transfected with Leptin-luc (250 ng) and 50 ng of expression vectors for full-length C/EBPalpha (solid bars), CR2-C/EBPalpha (open bars), or CR1/3/4-C/EBPalpha (gray bars). Expression constructs for beta-catenin (250 ng) and TCF-4N (500 ng) were cotransfected as indicated. Samples were normalized to beta-galactosidase activity to correct for variations in transfection efficiency. Luciferase activity is reported as fold activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. (C) 293T cells in 10-cm plates were transfected with 5 mug each of the indicated expression vectors by calcium phosphate coprecipitation. Cells were lysed after 48 h, and beta-catenin was immunoprecipitated with anti-Flag antibody. Immunoprecipitated beta-catenin complexes were separated by SDS-PAGE, followed by immunoblot analysis for C/EBPalpha and beta-catenin. (D) 293T cells were transfected with Leptin-luc (250 ng) and expression constructs for C/EBPalpha (50 ng), beta-catenin (250 ng), and TCF-4N (500 ng) as indicated. Cells were cotransfected with 250 ng of either empty vector (solid bars) or human p300 (open bars). Luciferase activity is reported as activation (mean +- standard deviation) relative to the reporter gene alone. Results are representative of at least three independent experiments.</text><annotation id="7"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0019</infon><location offset="45747" length="93"/><text>Cells were lysed after 48 h, and beta-catenin was immunoprecipitated with anti-Flag antibody.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>46378</offset><text>TCF-4N partially rescues the block of differentiation caused by ectopic expression of beta-catenin. (A) 3T3-L1 preadipocytes were infected with a control retrovirus (Hygro) or a retrovirus containing the coding region for TCF-4N. Control and TCF-4N-expressing cells were reinfected with a control retrovirus (Neo) or a retrovirus containing the coding region for S33Y beta-catenin. Two days after confluence, cells were treated with inducers of adipogenesis. Two weeks later, cells were stained with Oil Red-O to visualize the degree of lipid accumulation. The amount of Oil Red-O was quantified after extraction and is displayed as fold absorbance relative to the empty vector control. Cells were lysed, and expression of C/EBPalpha was analyzed by immunoblot (inset). (B) Control (Neo) and S33Y beta-catenin-expressing cells were reinfected with a retrovirus alone (Hygro) or a retrovirus containing the coding region for TCF-4N and analyzed as in A. (C) Model for the regulation of beta-catenin by TCF-4N. Expression of TCF-4N inhibits interactions between beta-catenin and TCF/LEF transcription factors. Complexes containing beta-catenin, TCF-4N, and p300 coactivate multiple transcription factors, including the adipogenic transcription factor C/EBPalpha.</text></passage></document></collection>