<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>sentence.key</key><document><id>3082520</id><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Divya;given-names:Kanneganti</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Han;given-names:Haesun</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tardiff;given-names:Daniel F.</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">21541368</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ju;given-names:Shulin</infon><infon key="issue">4</infon><infon key="year">2011</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">3082520</infon><infon key="article-id_publisher-id">PBIOLOGY-D-10-00015</infon><infon key="alt-title">A Yeast Model of FUS/TLS-Dependent                    Cytotoxicity</infon><infon key="article-id_doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001052</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="elocation-id">e1001052</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="name_10">surname:Ringe;given-names:Dagmar</infon><infon key="name_11">surname:Petsko;given-names:Gregory A.</infon><infon key="name_12">surname:Weissman;given-names:Jonathan S.</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Lindquist;given-names:Susan</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Brown;given-names:Robert H.;suffix:Jr.</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Hayward;given-names:Lawrence J.</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Bosco;given-names:Daryl A.</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Maquat;given-names:Lynne E.</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Zhong;given-names:Quan</infon><offset>0</offset><text>A Yeast Model of FUS/TLS-Dependent Cytotoxicity</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>48</offset><text>FUS/TLS is a nucleic acid binding protein that, when mutated, can cause a subset                     of familial amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (fALS). Although FUS/TLS is normally                     located predominantly in the nucleus, the pathogenic mutant forms of FUS/TLS                     traffic to, and form inclusions in, the cytoplasm of affected spinal motor                     neurons or glia. Here we report a yeast model of human FUS/TLS expression that                     recapitulates multiple salient features of the pathology of the disease-causing                     mutant proteins, including nuclear to cytoplasmic translocation, inclusion                     formation, and cytotoxicity. Protein domain analysis indicates that the                     carboxyl-terminus of FUS/TLS, where most of the ALS-associated mutations are                     clustered, is required but not sufficient for the toxicity of the protein. A                     genome-wide genetic screen using a yeast over-expression library identified five                     yeast DNA/RNA binding proteins, encoded by the yeast genes                         ECM32, NAM8, SBP1,                         SKO1, and VHR1, that rescue the toxicity                     of human FUS/TLS without changing its expression level, cytoplasmic                     translocation, or inclusion formation. Furthermore, hUPF1, a                     human homologue of ECM32, also rescues the toxicity of FUS/TLS                     in this model, validating the yeast model and implicating a possible                     insufficiency in RNA processing or the RNA quality control machinery in the                     mechanism of FUS/TLS mediated toxicity. Examination of the effect of FUS/TLS                     expression on the decay of selected mRNAs in yeast indicates that the                     nonsense-mediated decay pathway is probably not the major determinant of either                     toxicity or suppression.</text><annotation id="0"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="998" length="436"/><text>A                     genome-wide genetic screen using a yeast over-expression library identified five                     yeast DNA/RNA binding proteins, encoded by the yeast genes                         ECM32, NAM8, SBP1,                         SKO1, and VHR1, that rescue the toxicity                     of human FUS/TLS without changing its expression level, cytoplasmic                     translocation, or inclusion formation.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract_title_1</infon><offset>2057</offset><text>Author Summary</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>2072</offset><text>Of all the thousand natural shocks that flesh is heir to, one of the most                     devastating is amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), commonly known as Lou                     Gehrig's Disease. This disorder, which comes in both inherited and random                     forms, is characterized by degeneration of spinal motor neurons, leading to                     paralysis and death. The cause of the sporadic form is unknown, but new insight                     has come from studying the genetic variations that lead to the rarer familial                     forms. One such gene, accounting for 5%-10% of inherited                     ALS, is FUS/TLS, which encodes a protein that normally lives in the nucleus of                     the cell and is involved in the life-cycle of messenger RNA (mRNA).                     ALS-associated mutations in FUS/TLS cause the protein to mislocalize outside the                     nucleus into stress granules. Understanding the basis for the toxicity of                     mislocalized FUS/TLS could lead to new approaches to the treatment of ALS. We                     have made a yeast model for FUS/TLS cellular toxicity that recapitulates the                     mislocalization, granular accumulation, and cell death. We have exploited the                     yeast model to obtain information about what part of the protein is required for                     proper localization and what part is essential for toxicity. We have also                     identified several human genes that, when over-expressed in yeast, are able to                     rescue the cell from the toxicity of mislocalized FUS/TLS. These genes all have                     functions in mRNA quality control, implicating changes in this pathway in the                     pathology of ALS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>3912</offset><text>Introduction</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3925</offset><text>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS, also called Lou Gehrig's disease after one                 of its most famous victims) is a relentlessly progressive, fatal neurodegenerative                 disease with a prevalence of ~5 people out of 100,000 each year and an average                 age of onset of ~60 years. Patients with ALS suffer from degeneration of motor                 neurons in the brain and spinal cord, which leads to progressive muscular weakness.                 ALS accounts for ~1/300 to 1/400 of all deaths, which means that about 1,000,000                 people now alive in the United States will develop ALS. Death typically occurs                 3-5 years after disease onset, due to respiratory paralysis. There is no                 effective treatment for the disease; the only approved ALS drug (riluzole) extends                 the lifespan of some ALS patients by only about 3 months.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4855</offset><text>While most forms of ALS are sporadic and idiopathic (sALS), ~10% of cases                 are inherited in a Mendelian fashion and are designated familial ALS (fALS). As is                 the case for Parkinson's and Alzheimer's diseases, which also have                 ~10% familial forms, genetic analysis has identified several genes that                 cause fALS. The first mutations were identified in SOD1, which                 encodes the ubiquitously expressed copper/zinc superoxide dismutase; these variants                 cause ~20% of fALS worldwide. More than 150 different ALS mutations,                 spanning virtually the entire coding sequence of the highly conserved                     SOD1 gene, have been identified:nearly all of them                 exhibiting autosomal dominant inheritance [1]. Although inclusions containing                 aggregated SOD1 protein have been found in the spinal motor neurons of patients with                 SOD1-dependent fALS, they are generally not found in the sporadic disease.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5914</offset><text>More recently, other genes have been identified that collectively account for a                 significant percentage of the remaining fALS cases. These include the genes coding                 for alsin (ALS2), vesicle associated membrane protein B (VAPB) [2], senataxin (SETX) [3], TAR-DNA-binding                 protein (TDP-43) [4], fused in sarcoma or translocated in liposarcoma                     (FUS/TLS) [5],[6], and optineurin (OPTN) [7]. A small number of other genes                 have been associated with increased risk for sALS, most recently ataxin-2 [8]. Studies of these                 genes have provided important information about the biochemical processes that may                 underlie ALS. Putative mechanisms of toxicity targeting motor neurons include                 glutamate excitotoxicity, oxidative damage, proteasome inhibition, mitochondrial                 dysfunction, ER stress, axonal transport defects, growth factor signaling                 deficiency, and glial cell dysfunction [9],[10].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6954</offset><text>Two of the genes associated with fALS, FUS/TLS and TDP-43, are of special interest                 because inclusions containing these proteins have been identified in motor neurons                 of both sporadic and familial patients [11]-[15]. In addition, both of these                 genes have been linked to rare forms of frontotemporal lobar degeneration [16], indicating                 that they play crucial roles in other neurons. FUS/TLS and TDP-43 are both                 predominantly nuclear RNA binding proteins, although they have also been reported to                 bind DNA in vitro. Both FUS/TLS and TDP-43 are believed to carry out important                 functions in multiple steps of RNA processing, including transcription, splicing,                 transport, translation, and decay [17]. The finding that both                 are fALS genes (each accounts for about 5% of familial ALS cases), and are                 involved in sALS, raises the possibility that RNA processing or quality control                 (damage repair and decay of prematurely terminated messages) may be central to ALS                 pathology. However, the precise connections between RNA biology and ALS remain to be                 discovered.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8216</offset><text>The FUS/TLS protein, which is ubiquitously expressed in all tissues, contains an                 N-terminal putative transcriptional activation domain (residues 1-267) rich in                 serine, tyrosine, glutamine, and glycine residues, followed by a canonical RNA                 binding domain (residues 285-371). The C-terminal region has a zinc finger                 domain (residues 422-453) interrupting a long stretch rich in arginines and                 glycines (residues 285-501). The extreme C-terminal 25 amino acids (residues                 501-526) also are rich in arginines and glycines, and the majority of the                 ALS-associated mutations are found among them. Among other postulated functions,                 FUS/TLS is known to be a component of a large nuclear ribonucleoprotein complex that                 functions in shuttling mRNA out of the nucleus.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9125</offset><text>Variants of FUS/TLS have previously been studied for their role in liposarcoma, in                 which the N-terminal transcriptional activation domain of FUS/TLS is translocated                 into another chromosomal locus, resulting in gene fusions and production of chimeric                 oncoproteins (e.g. FUS-ERG, FUS-CHOP, and FUS-CREB312). The fusion proteins are                 aberrant transcription factors that contribute to the tumorigenic process by                 altering the expression of many target genes [18].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9663</offset><text>Mutations in FUS/TLS found in fALS are largely clustered at the extreme C-terminus of                 the protein. Postmortem histological analysis from patients with FUS/TLS mutations                 indicates that the normally nuclear protein is now found more predominantly in the                 cytosol, where it forms punctate inclusions. This                 mislocalization/inclusion-formation has been proposed to cause either a loss of                 normal protein function in the nucleus, a gain of toxic function in the cytosol, or                 both [5],[17]. Recently, Dormann et al. [19] reported that some of the                 disease-causing mutations affect a non-classical PY nuclear localization signal                 (NLS) in the extreme C-terminus of FUS/TLS and disrupt transportin-mediated nuclear                 import of the protein. As a result, FUS/TLS distribution increases in the cytosol,                 where the protein can be recruited into stress granules [20]. These results have led to the                 hypothesis that nuclear import defects and consequent cellular stress may be                 necessary, and possibly sufficient, for FUS/TLS pathogenesis [19],[20].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10880</offset><text>Since FUS/TLS-immunoreactive inclusions are reported to be a common feature in both                 sporadic and familial ALS [13], it is likely that an understanding of FUS/TLS-associated                 fALS could also provide valuable information about the more common sporadic form of                 the disease. Additionally, the involvement of FUS/TLS in other neurodegenerative                 diseases, such as a subset of FTLD (atypical FTLD-U) [21], neuronal intermediate                 filament inclusion disease (NIFID) [22], and polyglutamine disease [23], suggests that several                 neurodegenerative diseases may have similar underlying pathogenic mechanisms. A                 better understanding of the normal and aberrant functions of FUS/TLS might therefore                 provide clues to uncovering the pathology of neurodegenerative diseases beyond ALS.                 With this in mind, we set out to create a model for FUS/TLS-dependent cytotoxicity                 in a genetically and biochemically tractable organism.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11941</offset><text>With uniquely available genetic and biochemical tools, yeast has proven to be a                 valuable system to study the functions of human proteins involved in many diseases,                 including neurodegenerative disorders [24]-[29]. Although yeast is a simple                 single-cell eukaryote, many fundamental cellular processes are conserved between                 yeast and higher eukaryotes, and a number were first discovered in S.                     cerevisiae or its distant relative, S. pombe. If                 expression of FUS/TLS in yeast can be shown to recapitulate some of the relevant                 features of human FUS/TLS-dependent proteotoxicity, then genetic screens can be used                 to dissect the pathways and processes involved.</text><annotation id="1"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="12186" length="209"/><text>Although yeast is a simple                 single-cell eukaryote, many fundamental cellular processes are conserved between                 yeast and higher eukaryotes, and a number were first discovered in S.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12729</offset><text>In this article, we report a yeast model of FUS/TLS-dependent cytotoxicity, in which                 over-expression and mislocalization of wild-type or mutant FUS/TLS recapitulates the                 phenotypes of toxicity and inclusion formation observed in the human disease.                 Certain features of the model have allowed us to conclude that cytosolic                 localization of large amounts of even the wild-type FUS protein is sufficient to                 cause toxicity, supporting a hypothesis that had been put forward based on studies                 in mammalian cells. A genetic screen using this yeast model for suppressors of                 toxicity identifies, among other genes, the yeast gene ECM32, an                 RNA helicase involved in RNA quality control, as one that rescues FUS/TLS toxicity                 when over-expressed. In addition, hUPF1, a human homolog of                     ECM32, rescues FUS/TLS toxicity, as do its interacting partners                     hUPF2 and (to a lesser extent) hUPF3. The                 rescue does not involve a decrease in FUS/TLS expression or a change in its                 localization or inclusion formation, but it does depend on intact functional domains                 of hUPF1. Since hUPF1 plays an important function                 in mRNA quality control, our data raise the possibility that this pathway might be                 involved in the pathogenesis of FUS/TLS-associated ALS, and                 possibly of the disease in general. We have investigated the role of one aspect of                 RNA quality control, nonsense-mediated decay (NMD), using the yeast model but find                 no evidence that NMD disruption is responsible for FUS/TLS toxicity or that its                 upregulation is important for suppression.</text><annotation id="2"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="13314" length="275"/><text>A genetic screen using this yeast model for suppressors of                 toxicity identifies, among other genes, the yeast gene ECM32, an                 RNA helicase involved in RNA quality control, as one that rescues FUS/TLS toxicity                 when over-expressed.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14578</offset><text>Independently, Sun et al. (2010, [30]) have developed a similar yeast model for                 FUS/TLS-associated ALS and have identified all of the same suppressor genes, plus                 some additional ones, in a similar screen. In addition, they have found genes that,                 when deleted, modulate FUS/TLS toxicity in yeast, and have implicated stress                 granules (discrete cytoplasmic phase-dense particles, observed in cells exposed to                 heat, oxidative, hyperosmolarity, and UV stress, where non-translating mRNAs are                 stored) in this process.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>15186</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>15194</offset><text>Expression and Localization of Human FUS/TLS in Yeast: Over-expression of                     FUS/TLS Is Toxic</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15305</offset><text>Unlike wild type FUS/TLS, which is largely found in the nucleus and somewhat                     diffusely in the cytosol, the mutant proteins associated with fALS are                     predominantly aggregated in the cytoplasm of neurons, where they are proposed to                     be toxic. To determine whether the budding yeast S. cerevisiae                     may serve as a model for investigating the molecular mechanisms of FUS/TLS                     cytotoxicity, we generated yeast strains expressing FUS/TLS. The human                         FUS/TLS gene, in both wild type and mutant (R521G and                     H517Q) forms, was N-terminally fused to green fluorescent protein (GFP) and                     placed under the control of the GAL1 promoter, whereby                     expression is tightly controlled by switching the carbon source in the medium.                     In these strains, expression of both WT and mutant FUS/TLS is highly induced by                     shifting to galactose medium. When either mutant or wild-type protein is                     over-expressed (induced by 2% galactose), the majority of the protein                     forms punctate aggregates in the cytosol (Figure 1A, and Figure S1),                     recapitulating the nuclear to cytoplasmic translocation phenotype characteristic                     of FUS/TLS-associated sporadic and familial ALS, as well as other                     neurodegenerative diseases [5]. Data from an independent yeast model of FUS/TLS                     cytoxicity [30]                     and expression of mutant forms of FUS/TLS in mammalian cells [20] suggest that                     these aggregates could be localized to stress granules.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>17061</offset><text>Expression, localization, and toxicity of FUS/TLS in yeast.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>17121</offset><text>(A) Cells expressing GFP or GFP-FUS were induced by 2% galactose                             for 6 h. Cells were then fixed and viewed by fluorescence microscopy.                             DAPI was used to stain the nucleus. (B) Yeast with integrated GFP, 1XFUS                             (1 copy of untagged FUS integrated into the HIS3 locus                             in the genome), and 2XFUS (2 copies of untagged FUS integrated into the                                 HIS3 locus and the TRP1 locus in                             the genome) were serially diluted (from left to right) and spotted onto                             plates containing either glucose (FUS expression "off") or                             galactose (expression "on"). Picture was taken after 2 d                             growth at 30 C.</text><annotation id="3"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="17223" length="60"/><text>Cells were then fixed and viewed by fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17958</offset><text>To test possible toxicity of aggregated FUS/TLS in the cytosol, one copy of                     FUS/TLS (1XFUS; untagged) and two copies of FUS/TLS (2XFUS; untagged) were                     integrated into the genome of yeast strain W303alpha. Yeast strains with FUS/TLS                     (1XFUS and 2XFUS) were serially diluted and spotted onto plates with glucose                     (expression repressed) and galactose (expression induced). As shown in Figure 1B, FUS/TLS                     over-expression is toxic to yeast in a dose-dependent manner under these                     proliferative growth conditions, with the 2XFUS exhibiting greater toxicity than                     1XFUS. Toxicity of the over-expressed mutant proteins was comparable to that of                     the wild-type (Figure S1;                     see below for an explanation), so the wild-type protein was used for most of the                     remaining experiments, to avoid possible sequence-dependent peculiarities.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18970</offset><text>Inclusions Formed by FUS/TLS Are Different from Those Formed by                     PolyQ-Expanded Huntingtin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19080</offset><text>In yeast models for several other protein misfolding diseases, although the                     morphologies of the aggregated proteins under the fluorescence microscope look                     similar, the actual characteristics of the aggregates are sometimes quite                     different. For example, yeast toxicity and aggregation of the human                     Huntingon's disease-associated protein huntingtin harboring a                     pathogenic polyglutamine expansion (Htt103Q) can be rescued by the deletion of a                     heat shock protein HSP104 (hsp104Delta) or                     yeast prion protein RNQ1 (rnq1Delta). However, the same                     deletions cannot rescue the cytosolic aggregation and toxicity of TDP-43 in                     yeast [28].                     Previous studies also indicate that Htt103Q forms SDS-insoluble aggregates,                     which cannot pass through a 0.2 microM cellulose acetate membrane; however,                     TDP43 aggregates can pass freely [28].</text><annotation id="4"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="19380" length="360"/><text>For example, yeast toxicity and aggregation of the human                     Huntingon's disease-associated protein huntingtin harboring a                     pathogenic polyglutamine expansion (Htt103Q) can be rescued by the deletion of a                     heat shock protein HSP104 (hsp104Delta) or                     yeast prion protein RNQ1 (rnq1Delta).</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20131</offset><text>FUS/TLS has been found to be associated with huntingtin aggregates in                     Huntington's disease patients [23], yet the characteristics of FUS/TLS-dependent fALS                     resemble those of TDP-43-associated ALS. To test possible differences between                     FUS/TLS aggregates and huntingtin or TDP-43, FUS/TLS aggregates isolated from                     over-expressing yeast were tested by a filter retardation assay. As expected,                     Htt103Q was trapped by the membrane; however, FUS/TLS aggregates, like TDP43,                     passed through the membrane freely (Figure 2A). Consistent with this observation, unlike their effects                     on Htt103Q, deletion of HSP104 and RNQ1 did                     not modify the toxicity of FUS/TLS in yeast (Figure 2B), nor its aggregation or                     localization (Figure 2C). In                     addition, over-expression of HSP104 and RNQ1                     had no effect on FUS/TLS toxicity either (unpublished data).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>21181</offset><text>Aggregates of FUS/TLS are different from that of Huntingtin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>21242</offset><text>(A) Yeast cells containing GFP-tagged N-terminal huntingtin harboring                             pathogenic polyglutamine expansions (Htt103Q, stretch of 103 consecutive                             glutamines), normal huntingtin (Htt25Q, stretch of 25 consecutive                             glutamines), and GFP tagged FUS/TLS were induced with galactose for 6 h.                             Filter retardation assay was performed to characterize the aggregates.                             (B) GFP tagged FUS, Htt103Q, or Htt25Q was transformed into                                 HSP104Delta, RNQ1Delta deletion                             strains and the isogenic wild type strain BY4743 (WT). Cells were                             serially diluted and spotted onto glucose (expression "off")                             or galactose plate (expression "on") to observe toxicity.                             Pictures were taken after 2 d growth at 30 C. GFP on the same vector                             (GFP) was used as control. (C) The same strains as above were visualized                             for localization and aggregation of the proteins by fluorescence                             microscopy. (D) pYES2CT/GFP-FUS (FUS) and empty vector (Vec) were                             transformed into wild type yeast, and yeast containing integrated                             Htt103Q. Freshly grown cells were then serially diluted and spotted onto                             glucose (expression "off") or galactose plate (expression                             "on") to observe toxicity. Pictures were taken after 2 d                             growth at 30 C.</text><annotation id="5"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="22196" length="178"/><text>(C) The same strains as above were visualized                             for localization and aggregation of the proteins by fluorescence                             microscopy.</text></annotation><annotation id="6"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="22375" length="184"/><text>(D) pYES2CT/GFP-FUS (FUS) and empty vector (Vec) were                             transformed into wild type yeast, and yeast containing integrated                             Htt103Q.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22935</offset><text>These differences between FUS/TLS and Htt103Q aggregates suggest that the                     toxicity mechanism underlying these two proteins might be different. Consistent                     with this, toxicity resulting from the over-expression of FUS/TLS and Htt103Q is                     additive (Figure 2D).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>23252</offset><text>The C-Terminal Domain of FUS/TLS Is Necessary But Not Sufficient for Its                     Toxicity</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23354</offset><text>The full-length FUS/TLS protein has an N-terminal transcriptional activation                     domain (residues 1-267) including SYQG-rich (residues 1-164) and                     G-rich (residues 165-267) subdomains, and a C-terminal RNA binding region                     (residues 285-526) including RNA binding (residues 285-370), Zinc                     Finger (residues 422-452), and RGG-rich domains (residues 371-421                     and 453-501) (Figure                         3A). The extreme C-terminus (residues 511-526) contains an                     arginine-rich sequence and a putative nuclear localization signal [19]; every one                     of the arginines in this region is the site of an ALS-associated mutation. To                     pinpoint which part of FUS/TLS is required for its toxicity in yeast, we                     characterized eight fragments of the wild-type FUS/TLS protein (tagged with GFP                     at the N-terminus) for their localization, aggregation, and toxicity. As shown                     in Figure 3B, after removal                     of the C-terminal region of the protein (constructs 1 [residues                     1-164], 2 [residues 1-267], and 3 [residues                     1-370]), the protein is no longer toxic, suggesting that the                     C-terminal domain from residues 371 on is required for toxicity. However,                     expression of the C-terminal domain only (constructs 6 [residues                     165-526], 7 [residues 268-526], and 8 [residues                     371-526]) is not toxic, indicating that both C- and N-terminal                     regions of the protein are essential for toxicity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>25106</offset><text>Toxicity and localization of individual domains of FUS/TLS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>25166</offset><text>(A) A serial deletion of the full length FUS/TLS gene from c-terminus,                             labeled as 1-4, and from N-terminus, labeled as 6-8, was                             carried out. (B) The truncated genes (with GFP tag at N-terminus) were                             then placed under the control of GAL1 promoter on the                             yeast expression vector pYES2CT. Yeast with above constructs was                             serially diluted and spotted onto plate containing either glucose                             (expression "off") or galactose (expression                             "on"). Pictures of the plates were taken after 2 d growth at                             30 C. (C) Cells containing the above constructs were grown in the                             Ura-Raffinose medium to mid-log phase. Expression of the proteins was                             induced by 2% galactose for 6 h. Localization and aggregation of                             the proteins was visualized by fluorescence microscopy. (D) Constructs                             3-5 as shown in (A) were also cloned into yeast expression vector                             pDEST52 without the GFP tag. Yeast containing the constructs was                             serially diluted and spotted onto glucose (expression "off")                             or galactose plate (expression "on"). Picture of the plates                             was taken after 2 d growth at 30 C.</text><annotation id="7"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="26104" length="115"/><text>Localization and aggregation of                             the proteins was visualized by fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26687</offset><text>To check for a possible correlation between toxicity and aggregation, all eight                     proteins (N-terminally GFP tagged) were checked using fluorescence microscopy.                     As shown in Figure 3C, all                     the proteins, when over-expressed, show aggregation; however, only constructs 4                     (which lacks the extreme C-terminal 15 residues) and 5 (the full-length protein)                     are toxic. Interestingly, the aggregates formed by constructs 4 and 5 appear                     slightly different from each other and also may differ from the aggregates                     formed by the other constructs. These data suggest that toxicity of FUS/TLS in                     yeast involves mechanisms beyond protein aggregation, a hypothesis supported by                     the results of the suppressor screen (see below).</text><annotation id="8"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="26687" length="178"/><text>To check for a possible correlation between toxicity and aggregation, all eight                     proteins (N-terminally GFP tagged) were checked using fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27575</offset><text>To test the possible effects of the GFP tag on toxicity, we expressed constructs                     3-5 without the N-terminal GFP fusion. Consistent with non-tagged                     constructs, construct 3, which lacks the residues from 371 to 526, is not toxic,                     and constructs 4 and 5 are still toxic. Interestingly, the construct lacking the                     15 amino acids at the extreme C-terminal end (construct 4), where most of the                     fALS mutations are clustered, is more toxic to yeast than the full-length                     protein (construct 5). This result is consistent with the recent finding that                     patients with a nonsense mutation of FUS/TLS at position 495 have more rapidly                     progressive neurodegeneration and earlier onset of the disease [20],[31] and that                     the C-terminus encodes a nuclear localization signal [19].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>28516</offset><text>Localization and Toxicity of FUS/TLS in Yeast Is Not Regulated by Either of                     the Major Yeast Arginine Methyltransferases</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28656</offset><text>Most mutations of FUS/TLS identified in fALS patients are clustered at the very                     end of the C-terminus (residues 510-526), in a region enriched with                     arginine residues [5]. At least one disease-causing mutation has been                     identified for each arginine in this region, implying that these arginine                     residues play a critical role for the function of the protein. One regulatory                     process involving arginine residues is dimethylation, which is an important                     signal for the nuclear/cytoplasmic translocalization of a series of RNA binding                     proteins. That more than 20 arginine residues are indeed dimethylated by the                     enzyme PRMT1 in FUS/TLS in mammalian cells [32], and that all the known                     C-terminal region mutant forms of FUS/TLS do translocate to the cytosol,                     together suggest that arginine methylation may be involved in the shuttling of                     FUS/TLS between nucleus and cytosol and thus may play a role in its toxicity. To                     explore the possible role of the yeast arginine methyl transferases in                     mislocalization, localization and toxicity of FUS/TLS was studied in yeast                     strains in which each of the two major yeast arginine methyltransferases were                     deleted (rmt1Delta and rmt2Delta). As shown in                         Figure 4, FUS/TLS is                     still toxic in rmt1Delta and rmt2Delta strains                         (Figure 4A), and the                     protein is still aggregated in the cytosol in both cases (Figure 4B).</text><annotation id="9"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="29781" length="341"/><text>To                     explore the possible role of the yeast arginine methyl transferases in                     mislocalization, localization and toxicity of FUS/TLS was studied in yeast                     strains in which each of the two major yeast arginine methyltransferases were                     deleted (rmt1Delta and rmt2Delta).</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>30372</offset><text>Deletion of arginine methyl transferase does not                             rescue FUS/TLS toxicity nor change its localization.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>30502</offset><text>(A) Empty vector and N-terminus GFP-tagged FUS/TLS on pYES2CT were                             transformed into yeast arginine methyl transferase deletion strain                                 rmt1Delta, rmt2Delta, and its                             isogenic wild type BY4743 (WT). Spotting assay was performed to observe                             toxicity from the above yeast strains. (B) Expression of the proteins                             from above strains was induced by 2% galactose for 6 h.                             Localization and aggregation of the protein was visualized by                             fluorescence microscopy.</text><annotation id="10"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="31008" length="114"/><text>Localization and aggregation of the protein was visualized by                             fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31145</offset><text>To test the possible redundancy of arginine methyltransferase activity in yeast,                     two small molecule compounds (AMI-1 and AMI-4), previously shown to exhibit                     broad inhibition of arginine methyl transferase activity in mammalian cells and                     in yeast [33],                     were tested on the yeast strain over-expressing FUS/TLS. Consistent with the                     results from the arginine methyl transferase deletion study, inhibition of                     arginine methyl transferase by these two compounds does not change FUS/TLS                     toxicity nor its localization (unpublished data). In addition, over-expression                     of RMT1 and RMT2, or of the human enzyme                     PRMT1, does not modify FUS/TLS toxicity (unpublished data). These data suggest                     that at least the predominant yeast arginine methyl transferases are not                     involved in the cytotoxicity of FUS/TLS in yeast. We next examined the possible                     role of nuclear localization signals in the nuclear/cytosolic distribution of                     the human protein when expressed in yeast.</text><annotation id="11"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="31145" length="388"/><text>To test the possible redundancy of arginine methyltransferase activity in yeast,                     two small molecule compounds (AMI-1 and AMI-4), previously shown to exhibit                     broad inhibition of arginine methyl transferase activity in mammalian cells and                     in yeast [33],                     were tested on the yeast strain over-expressing FUS/TLS.</text></annotation><annotation id="12"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="31984" length="181"/><text>These data suggest                     that at least the predominant yeast arginine methyl transferases are not                     involved in the cytotoxicity of FUS/TLS in yeast.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>32357</offset><text>The NLS of Human FUS/TLS Is Not Efficient in Yeast; However, Cytosolic                     Localization Is Correlated with Toxicity, Consistent with Findings for Neuronal                     Cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32554</offset><text>It was recently reported that FUS/TLS carries a non-classical PY nuclear                     localization signal (NLS) in its extreme C-terminus (approx. residues                     514-526) and this is necessary for its nuclear import [19]. The                     disease-causing mutations clustered in this NLS affect the nuclear localization                     of the protein. The toxicity of the protein and the age of disease onset                     correlate with the protein's cytosolic mislocalization and aggregation                         [19],[20],[31]. Since wild-type FUS was mostly aggregated in                     punctate granules in the yeast cytosol, we posited that its NLS might not be                     functional in this organism. If so, over-expression of even the wild-type                     protein would recapitulate the toxicity of the human mutants, as observed,                     through a failure in nuclear localization. To test this directly, we compared                     the ability of the FUS NLS to direct nuclear localization with a                     well-characterized yeast NLS that uses a similar PY sequence (from Hrp1) by                     fusing them to GFP. Indeed the FUS NLS was defective in nuclear localization                         (Figure 5A).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>33871</offset><text>FUS_plus and FUS_switch promote nuclear localization and lower                             toxicity of FUS/TLS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>33983</offset><text>(A) GFP was fused with the nuclear localization signal                             of FUS/TLS (GFP_FUS) and Hrp1 (GFP_Hrp1) as shown in top part of (A).                             Expression of protein from yeast containing above constructs was induced                             by 2% galactose for 6 h. Localization and aggregation of protein                             was visualized by fluorescence microscopy. (B) Hrp1 NLS was added to the                             c-terminal end of FUS/TLS (FUS_plus) or was used to replace nuclear                             localization signal of FUS/TLS (FUS_switch), as shown on part top of                             (B). Protein expression from yeast containing above constructs was                             induced by 0.1% galactose for 6 h. Protein localization and                             aggregation was visualized by fluorescence microscopy. (C) The same                             yeast strains were grown in raffinose medium and 0.1% galactose                             medium. Cell growth was monitored using a Bioscreen machine for 2 d at                             30 C. Typically, at least 10 replicates were done for each.</text><annotation id="13"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="34262" length="110"/><text>Localization and aggregation of protein                             was visualized by fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation><annotation id="14"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="34754" length="107"/><text>Protein localization and                             aggregation was visualized by fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35183</offset><text>To determine if the failure in nuclear localization contributes to toxicity, we                     tested two constructs, one in which the HRP1 NLS was simply appended to the                     human protein (FUS_plus) and another in which the HRP1 NLS was used to replace                     the FUS/TLS (FUS_switch; Figure                         5B). Both constructs dramatically increased nuclear localization of                     FUS (Figure 5B) and both                     reduced toxicity (Figure                     5C). Aggregation was also reduced when FUS was retargeted to the nucleus,                     but this is probably due to a generally lower level of FUS expression in these                     constructs. Toxicity was not completely ameliorated, likely because some                     residual cytoplasmic FUS persisted even when augmented with the HRP1 NLS (Figure 5B). This relationship                     between mislocalization and toxicity is consistent with data from neuronal cells                         [19] and                     suggests that the wild-type protein is toxic in yeast because the nonfunctional                     NLS mimics the mislocalization effect of the disease-producing mutations in                     human cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>36465</offset><text>Genome Wide Screen to Identify Genes Whose Over-expression Rescues the                     Toxicity of FUS/TLS in Yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36585</offset><text>The ability of yeast expressing human FUS/TLS to recapitulate several salient                     features of disease prompted us to perform a genome-wide over-expression screen.                     By identifying yeast genes that modify FUS/TLS toxicity, we hoped to identify                     pathways or proteins that would illuminate pathogenic mechanisms. We screened an                     over-expression library containing a collection of yeast open reading frames,                     fully sequenced and placed under the control of a galactose-inducible promoter.                     A total of 5,535 genes are covered in this library (representing 95% of                     the yeast genome). We transformed each of the 5,535 genes into the yeast strain                     expressing the moderately toxic one copy of FUS/TLS (untagged FUS/TLS integrated                     into the yeast genome at the HIS3 locus) and selected for those                     that suppress FUS/TLS toxicity upon over-expression. All of the positive                     over-expression plasmids were retransformed into a fresh yeast strain and                     validated for their suppressive effects. Surprisingly, after three rounds of                     retesting, only a handful of yeast genes could suppress FUS/TLS toxicity, all of                     which are listed in the Table                         1. FUS expression is very toxic in yeast, and the identified                     suppressors do not completely abolish the effect of FUS on yeast growth. As                     observed for a similar screen in a yeast alpha-synuclein toxicity model [26], several                     transcription factors that down-regulate the GAL1 promoter activity also                     suppress the toxicity of FUS/TLS (Table 1, bottom section). These modifiers were not specific to                     FUS/TLS; they also suppress other toxic proteins expressed under GAL1 promoter                     control, such as TDP-43.</text><annotation id="15"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="37252" length="318"/><text>We transformed each of the 5,535 genes into the yeast strain                     expressing the moderately toxic one copy of FUS/TLS (untagged FUS/TLS integrated                     into the yeast genome at the HIS3 locus) and selected for those                     that suppress FUS/TLS toxicity upon over-expression.</text></annotation><annotation id="16"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="37960" length="150"/><text>FUS expression is very toxic in yeast, and the identified                     suppressors do not completely abolish the effect of FUS on yeast growth.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_title_caption</infon><offset>38614</offset><text>Yeast genes rescuing the toxicity of human FUS/TLS when                             over-expressed.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>38714</offset><text>   Gene Function Human Homologue Function of Human Homologue   Genes suppressing FUS/TLS toxicity when                                         over-expressed     ECM32 Member of the Dna2p- and Nam7p-like family of RNA                                     helicases; involved in translation termination UPF1 Nuclear mRNA export, mRNA surveillance,                                     nonsense-mediated mRNA decay, Staufen1-mediated mRNA decay,                                     replication-dependent histone mRNA decay, DNA synthesis and                                     repair, telomere maintenance  NAM8* RNA binding protein; component of the U1 snRNP                                     protein complex involved in mRNA maturation TRNAU1AP Unknown; contains a putative RNA-binding                                     domain  SBP1 Putative RNA binding protein; localizes to P-bodies                                     and associates with snRNPs RBM14 Nuclear receptor coactivator  SKO1 Transcription factor of the ATF/CREB family None   VHR1 Transcriptional activator None   Genes regulating GAL1 promoter/general gene                                         expression     MBP1 Transcription factor None   MIG1 Multicopy inhibitor of GAL gene expression None   MIG3 Transcriptional repressor    REG1 Negative regulator of glucose-repressible                                     genes None   ZDS1 Transcriptional silencing None   ZDS2 Transcriptional silencing None </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_footnote</infon><offset>40187</offset><text>*Identified in a number of other yeast suppressor screens. May                                 affect GAL-driven gene expression.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40317</offset><text>All the FUS/TLS-specific suppressors are DNA/RNA binding proteins (Table 1, top section; and                         Figure 6A), including                         ECM32, SBP1, SKO1, and                         VHR1. As shown in Figure 6B, FUS/TLS protein level was not                     altered by over-expression of these four genetic modifiers, supporting the                     hypothesis that the rescue is not mediated by reducing the amount of                     FUS/TLS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>40799</offset><text>Expression of ECM32, SBP1,                                 SKO1, and VHR1 rescues FUS/TLS                             toxicity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>40927</offset><text>(A) ECM32, SBP1, SKO1,                             and VHR1 were individually transformed into 1X FUS                             strain. Spotting assay was performed to observe toxicity of yeast                             containing the above constructs. (B) Protein expression was induced by                             2% galactose for 6 h from above yeast strains. Western blot                             analysis was performed using an antibody against FUS/TLS. PGK1 is shown                             as a control of protein loading.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>41471</offset><text>ECM32 (also called MTT1) encodes a                     DNA-dependent ATPase/DNA helicase belonging to the Dna2p- and Nam7p-like family                     of helicases that are involved in modulating translation termination [34].                     (Interestingly, we also detected NAM8, an RNA binding protein                     that interacts genetically with NAM7 in yeast, as a suppressor                     of FUS toxicity. We include it on our list, but we are uncertain of its                     specificity; it appears as a suppressor in many screens and may cause some                     nonspecific downregulation of the GAL1 promoter. Yeast NAM7,                     which is sometimes called yeast UPF1, is a homologue of                         ECM32, but neither we nor Sun et al. [30] found NAM7 as                     a strong suppressor in our screen.) Over-expression of ECM32 is known to induce                     a nonsense suppression phenotype in a wild-type yeast strain, and the ECM32 gene                     product has been shown to interact with translation termination factors and is                     localized to polysomes [34]. ECM32 is homologous to the human gene hUPF1, which                     encodes a protein previously shown to function in both mRNA turnover and                     translation termination, and which can be found in P-bodies, cytoplasmic                     granules that are sites of mRNA sequestration and turnover, including                     nonsense-mediated decay (NMD).</text><annotation id="17"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="42102" length="148"/><text>Yeast NAM7,                     which is sometimes called yeast UPF1, is a homologue of                         ECM32, but neither we nor Sun et al.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43017</offset><text>SBP1 encodes a putative RNA binding protein that is involved in translational                     repression and is also found in cytoplasmic P-bodies [35].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43174</offset><text>SKO1 encodes a basic leucine zipper transcription factor of the ATF/CREB family,                     which forms a complex with Tup1p and Ssn6p that acts as a repressor of                     transcription. In response to osmotic and oxidative stress, this complex can be                     converted into an activator that recruits SAGA and SWI/SNF [36].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43531</offset><text>VHR1 is a transcriptional activator that is required for the vitamin                     H-responsive element (VHRE) mediated induction of VHT1 (Vitamin H                     transporter) and BIO5 (biotin biosynthesis intermediate transporter) in response                     to low biotin concentrations [37]. In humans, biotin deficiency leads to a variety of                     clinical abnormalities, including neurological disorders, growth retardation,                     and dermal abnormalities [38].</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44044</offset><text>All of these genes were identified by Sun et al. in an independent screen for                     suppressors in a similar yeast model for FUS/TLS-dependent proteotoxicity [30]. Differences                     between results of the two screens probably reflect differences in the protocol                     of the initial pass, plus differences in stringency in retesting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44420</offset><text>Of the genetic modifiers identified from our screen, ECM32 is                     the only gene that is capable of rescuing toxicity of yeast strains integrated                     with both one copy (Figure                         7A) and two copies of FUS (Figure 7B). The other suppressors only rescue                     toxicity of 1XFUS (unpublished data). We therefore turned our attention to the                     human homologues of this protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>44878</offset><text>hUPF1 rescues FUS/TLS toxicity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>44910</offset><text>hUPF1 and hUPF2 were cloned into yeast                             expression vector pYES2CT. (A) The constructs were transformed into                             1XFUS (one copy of FUS/TLS integrated at HIS locus). Spotting assay was                             performed to check the rescue of toxicity by hUPF1 and                                 hUPF2. Empty vector and ECM32                             construct from library screen were used as negative and positive                             controls. (B) The above constructs were transformed into 2XFUS (two                             copies of FUS/TLS integrated at HIS locus and TRP locus, respectively).                             Spotting assay was performed to check the rescue of toxicity by                                 hUPF1 and hUPF2. (C) GFP tagged                             FUS/TLS (pYES2CT/GFP-FUS) and RFP tagged hUPF1 (pRSGal1hUPF1-DsRed) were                             transformed into yeast. Protein expression was induced by 2%                             galactose for 6 h and visualized by fluorescence microcopy.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>46013</offset><text>hUPF1, a Human Homolog of ECM32, Rescues Toxicity of                     FUS/TLS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46094</offset><text>Based on sequence similarity (~30% identity and ~50%                     similarity in the helicase domain), hUPF1, a gene playing an                     important role in the pathway of nonsense-mediated decay (NMD), is the closest                     human homolog of ECM32                     [39].                     Because of this homology, we hypothesized that the toxicity of FUS/TLS may be                     rescued by yeast expression of hUPF1. The full-length                         hUPF1 gene was cloned into a yeast expression vector and                     tested on the toxicity of FUS/TLS. Over-expression of hUPF1                     rescues the toxicity of both 1XFUS and 2XFUS (Figure 7A and B). To check for possible                     direct interaction between hUPF1 and FUS/TLS, we co-expressed red fluorescent                     protein-tagged hUPF1 and GFP-tagged FUS/TLS. hUPF1 is expressed mainly in the                     cytosol in yeast but does not co-localize with FUS/TLS (Figure 7C), suggesting the rescue effect by                     hUPF1 might be indirect. However, more data are needed to rule out possible                     over-expression artifacts.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>47298</offset><text>Next, we investigated whether the expression of hUPF2, another                     nonsense-mediated decay pathway gene whose protein product is known to form a                     complex with the UPF1 protein, might also rescue FUS toxicity in yeast, and                     found that it did, to an equal extent as that of hUPF1 (Figure 7). However,                     over-expression of human UPF3, another protein known to                     interact with UPF1, showed only moderate rescue compared to                         hUPF1 and hUPF2 (suppression of toxicity                     of 1XFUS but not of 2XFUS). We then examined the expression of the next closest                     human homologue of ECM32, IGHMBP2                     (~25% identity), a ribosome-associated helicase implicated in DNA                     replication, pre-mRNA splicing, and transcription [40]. Mutations in                         IGHMBP2 cause distal spinal muscular atrophy type 1, a                     neuromuscular disorder [40]. However, expression of hIGHMBP2 in                     yeast did not rescue FUS/TLS toxicity (unpublished data).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>48444</offset><text>To check the possible effect of ECM32, hUPF1,                     and hUPF2 on the protein expression level or aggregation of                     FUS/TLS, Western blots and indirect immunofluorescence using FUS/TLS antibody                     were performed. Neither protein levels (Figure 8A) nor localization or aggregation of                     FUS/TLS (Figure 8B) was                     modified by over-expression of ECM32, hUPF1,                     or hUPF2.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>48913</offset><text>Rescue of FUS/TLS toxicity requires full length                                 hUPF1, and rescue is not mediated                             by decrease in FUS/TLS protein level or inclusion formation of the                             protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>49159</offset><text>(A) Protein expression was induced by 2% galactose for 6 h in                             1XFUS strain expressing hUPF1, hUPF2, or ECM32. Western blot was                             performed using an antibody against FUS/TLS to check the expression of                             FUS/TLS. PGK1 is shown as a control of protein loading; (B) the same                             yeast cells were also subject to indirect immunofluorescence staining                             using primary antibody against FUS/TLS, and secondary antibody                             conjugated with fluorescein. Nuclear DNA was stained with DAPI. (C)                             Different domains of hUPF1 were cloned into a yeast                             expression vector and transformed into 1XFUS strain. Spotting assay was                             performed to check rescue of the toxicity. hUPF1-418, hUPF2 binding                             domain; hUPF419-1118, ATPase/Helicase domain; hUPF1R843C, inactivated                             ATPase/Helicase by arginine to cysteine mutation at residue of 843 in                             the full length FUS/TLS.</text><annotation id="18"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="49450" length="305"/><text>PGK1 is shown as a control of protein loading; (B) the same                             yeast cells were also subject to indirect immunofluorescence staining                             using primary antibody against FUS/TLS, and secondary antibody                             conjugated with fluorescein.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>50320</offset><text>hUPF1 has an N-terminal hUPF2 binding domain and a C-terminal ATPase/Helicase                     domain. To determine whether the rescue of FUS/TLS toxicity requires both                     domains, we tested the constructs expressing only the hUPF2 binding domain                     (hUPF1-418) or the ATPase/Helicase domain (hUPF419-1118). As shown in Figure 8C, neither domain                     rescues the toxicity of FUS/TLS to the extent that the full-length wild type                     protein rescues. To further test whether ATPase/Helicase activity is required                     for the rescue, we checked the full-length protein with ATPase/Helicase                     partially inactivated by a point mutation (R844C) [41] and found that FUS/TLS                     toxicity cannot be fully rescued when ATPase/Helicase activity of hUPF1 is                     inhibited. It is noteworthy that hUPF1(R844C) still has 60% of the                     activity of wild-type hUPF1 [41], so it is quite possible that fully inactivated hUPF1                     would not rescue at all. These data suggest that both domains of hUPF1 and                     functional ATPase/Helicase activity are required for its rescue of FUS/TLS                     toxicity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>51597</offset><text>CYH2 But Not MER2 Pre-mRNA Was Accumulated When FUS Was                     Over-expressed</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>51688</offset><text>To prevent the potential accumulation of deleterious nonsense fragments of                     polypeptides in the cytoplasm, mRNAs that retain an intron containing an                     in-frame nonsense codon are usually degraded by the nonsense-mediated decay                     (NMD) pathway. It is long established that CYH2 and                         MER2 pre-mRNA are among the substrates of this pathway in                     yeast. These pre-mRNAs are accumulated 2- to 5-fold when the NMD pathway is                     deficient [42]. To                     check the potential effects of FUS expression on the NMD pathway, qRT-PCR was                     utilized to determine CYH2 and MER2 pre-mRNA                     levels in 1XFUS yeast, and in its suppressor strains. As shown in Figure 9A,                         CYH2 pre-mRNA was increased about 2-fold when FUS is                     over-expressed, and co-expression of its suppressor hUPF1 brought                         CYH2 pre-mRNA back to the wild type level; however,                     co-expression of another suppressor, ECM32, did not, suggesting                     that these two suppressors may rescue FUS toxicity through different                     mechanisms.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_title_caption</infon><offset>52945</offset><text>Yeast CYH2 but not MER2 pre-mRNA                             was accumulated when FUS is over-expressed.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>53050</offset><text>Cells were grown in raffinose medium to early log phase. Protein                             expression was induced by 2% galactose for 6 h in 1XFUS strain                             expressing empty vector (1XFUS), human UPF1 (+hUPF1), or                                 ECM32 (+ECM32). CYH2 pre-mRNA (A) and MER2                             pre-mRNA level (B) were determined by qRT-PCR using 18sRNA as an                             internal control. Pre-mRNA in wild type yeast cell without integration                             of FUS (WT) was normalized to 1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>53619</offset><text>In contrast to CYH2, over-expression of FUS and co-expression of                     its suppressors did not change MER2 pre-mRNA levels (Figure 9B). Since                         MER2 pre-mRNA is another substrate of the NMD pathway, this                     result implies that accumulation of CYH2 pre-mRNA by FUS                     over-expression is not through its direct effect on the NMD pathway but through                     an effect on one or more additional pathways of mRNA quality control. Possibly,                     the restoration of the level of CYH2 pre-mRNA to normal by                     hUPF1 expression in the 1XFUS strain also does not reflect hUPF1 function in                     NMD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>54337</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>54348</offset><text>Many essential cellular functions are conserved in the simple eukaryote yeast.                 Studies from this organism have provided valuable information for our understanding                 of many critical cellular functions, including cell cycle regulation, DNA                 replication, RNA synthesis and processing, protein synthesis, protein trafficking,                 and signal transduction. This simple system has also been utilized to study                 functions of proteins involved in human diseases, including neurodegenerative                 diseases. Although a yeast model usually cannot recapitulate all of the cellular                 processes in human cells, it has proven to capture key aspects of molecular                 pathology for several neurodegenerative disorders [27]. With its ease of                 high-throughput manipulations for both genetics and biochemistry, the yeast model                 organism provides invaluable tools for studying molecular mechanisms of human                 diseases. For those human proteins for which yeast cytotoxicity models are                 available, toxicity from each protein is usually quite different. Genetic modifiers                 identified from those yeast models usually do not overlap, supporting the use of                 yeast models for studying functions of human proteins specifically.</text><annotation id="19"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="55529" length="198"/><text>Genetic modifiers                 identified from those yeast models usually do not overlap, supporting the use of                 yeast models for studying functions of human proteins specifically.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>55744</offset><text>In this article, we report a yeast model of FUS/TLS-associated proteotoxicity when                 the protein is mislocalized to the cytoplasm. The model faithfully recapitulates the                 cytosolic aggregation and cytotoxicity observed in spinal motor neurons in the human                 disease. We exploited this model to test various hypotheses about FUS-mediated                 cytotoxicity. Comparison of the aggregates isolated from the model with those from                 yeast models of huntingtin toxicity and TDP-43 toxicity showed that they differed                 from the former but were similar to the latter; two yeast genes known to affect                 huntingtin aggregation when over-expressed also failed to affect FUS/TLS                 localization or aggregation. Clustering of fALS-associated FUS mutations in regions                 of potential arginine dimethylation prompted us to investigate the effects of                 deletion of either of the major yeast arginine methyltransferases on FUS/TLS                 cytosolic localization and toxicity, but neither their deletions nor introduction of                 known chemical inhibitors of yeast arginine methyltransferase activity had any                 effect on these properties. Over-expression of the major yeast and human arginine                 methyltransferaaes also failed to modulate FUS/TLS toxicity in yeast. However, we                 have no data at present to indicate that human FUS/TLS is a substrate for the yeast                 arginine methyltransferases (even though they are close homologues of the major                 human arginine methyltransferase, PRMT1), so we cannot conclude from this experiment                 that arginine methylation may play no role in FUS/TLS toxicity in mammalian cells.                 It does not seem to be a major factor in toxicity in yeast.</text><annotation id="20"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="56154" length="1018"/><text>Comparison of the aggregates isolated from the model with those from                 yeast models of huntingtin toxicity and TDP-43 toxicity showed that they differed                 from the former but were similar to the latter; two yeast genes known to affect                 huntingtin aggregation when over-expressed also failed to affect FUS/TLS                 localization or aggregation. Clustering of fALS-associated FUS mutations in regions                 of potential arginine dimethylation prompted us to investigate the effects of                 deletion of either of the major yeast arginine methyltransferases on FUS/TLS                 cytosolic localization and toxicity, but neither their deletions nor introduction of                 known chemical inhibitors of yeast arginine methyltransferase activity had any                 effect on these properties. Over-expression of the major yeast and human arginine                 methyltransferaaes also failed to modulate FUS/TLS toxicity in yeast.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57657</offset><text>Initially, the observation that both WT and mutant FUS localized to the cytoplasm and                 were equally toxic was unexpected. However, recent work on the C-terminal FUS                 mutations provides a satisfying explanation [19]. These mutations prevent the                 nuclear import of FUS, increasing cytoplasmic accumulation in stress granules and,                 eventually, producing toxic and insoluble aggregates. FUS uses an unusual nuclear                 localization signal (NLS) of the bPY-type. Although yeast has this same bPY-type                 nuclear localization system, divergence in the recognition signal would cause toxic                 mislocalization of even the WT FUS protein in yeast. Indeed, when we compared the                 ability of the WT FUS NLS signal and a known functional yeast bPY-type NLS to drive                 a GFP reporter into the nucleus, the FUS signal was nonfunctional. Next, we reasoned                 that if cytoplasmic mislocalization of FUS was responsible for increased toxicity,                 then restoring nuclear localization with a recognition sequence that does function                 in yeast should reduce toxicity. This proved to be correct. Thus, our work provides                 an independent validation of Haass' recent model [19], recapitulating the                 observation that cytoplasmic mislocalization is important in the toxicity of FUS.                 This mechanistic link between mutations and toxicity is in contrast to TDP-43, where                 ALS mutations increase aggregation in vitro (as opposed to transport) and enhance                 toxicity in yeast [28]. In agreement, the accompanying manuscript demonstrates                 that FUS mutations do not alter aggregation or toxicity [30]. The lack of an effect of ALS                 mutations in yeast separates two aspects of FUS pathology:(1) mislocalization                 and (2) cytoplasmic toxicity. Since the NLS is nonfunctional in yeast, our system                 models the cytoplasmic-dependent toxicity, but not the mechanism of mislocalization                 itself. Because the link between mislocalization and ALS mutants has been                 established, we view the inability to model mislocalization not as a liability but                 rather as a strength, in that it allows us to focus on toxicity itself.</text><annotation id="21"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="58187" length="206"/><text>Although yeast has this same bPY-type                 nuclear localization system, divergence in the recognition signal would cause toxic                 mislocalization of even the WT FUS protein in yeast.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>60082</offset><text>We also expressed a series of FUS/TLS constructs with various domains deleted and                 found that the C-terminal region of the protein was necessary but not sufficient for                 toxicity. In an independent, more detailed study using a similar yeast model of                 FUS/TLS toxicity, Sun et al. [30] conclude that, in contrast to TDP-43, determinants in                 both the N- and C-terminal regions of FUS are required to couple aggregation to                 toxicity in vivo and for spontaneous aggregation in vitro, suggesting that FUS                 aggregates by a mechanism distinct from that of TDP-43. They also find that FUS is                 intrinsically aggregation-prone and that the aggregates formed by purified FUS in                 vitro closely resemble the aggregates observed in affected neurons in human                 disease.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>60970</offset><text>Some of the aggregates formed by the various deletion constructs appeared to differ                 from one another slightly when viewed microscopically. We have not yet characterized                 the nature of the aggregation in any of these cases, but if different morphological                 aggregates are indeed toxic and similar-looking aggregates are not always toxic, as                 we in fact observe, our data lend support to the conclusion that aggregation and                 toxicity may not be tightly coupled in this system.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>61520</offset><text>Using a yeast over-expression library screen, we identified five yeast genes that,                 when over-expressed, rescue the toxicity of FUS/TLS. Strikingly, all five genetic                 modifiers are, like FUS, DNA/RNA binding proteins. We have compared genetic                 modifiers from other yeast models and found that these five genes are not identified                 as suppressors in other yeast models for neurodegenerative diseases, including                 Parkinson's disease (over-expression of alpha-synuclein [25]), TDP-43-dependent ALS                 (over-expression of wild-type TDP-43 [28]), and Huntington's                 disease (over-expression of polyQ-expanded huntingtin [24]), indicating that they are                 specific to FUS/TLS. We also note that genetic screens from other yeast models                 usually identify many more genetic modifiers. The very limited number of hits from                 our FUS/TLS yeast model suggests that the toxicity of FUS/TLS may stem from its                 effect on a limited number of cellular functions. Our screening results are similar                 to results obtained independently by Sun et al. [30], who found 23 over-expression                 suppressors (including all of the genes we identified) and also carried out a screen                 for yeast genes that modify toxicity when deleted. Further, they provide compelling                 evidence that stress granules and P-bodies are likely to be involved in FUS/TLS                 effects in yeast. We have also found a correlation between mutant FUS/TLS and stress                 granules that may be relevant to ALS pathogenesis [20].</text><annotation id="22"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="61520" length="151"/><text>Using a yeast over-expression library screen, we identified five yeast genes that,                 when over-expressed, rescue the toxicity of FUS/TLS.</text></annotation><annotation id="23"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="61768" length="536"/><text>We have compared genetic                 modifiers from other yeast models and found that these five genes are not identified                 as suppressors in other yeast models for neurodegenerative diseases, including                 Parkinson's disease (over-expression of alpha-synuclein [25]), TDP-43-dependent ALS                 (over-expression of wild-type TDP-43 [28]), and Huntington's                 disease (over-expression of polyQ-expanded huntingtin [24]), indicating that they are                 specific to FUS/TLS.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>63224</offset><text>Most importantly, we found that expression of hUPF1 (or of its                 physical interacting partner hUPF2 and, to a lesser extent,                     hUPF3) rescues FUS/TLS toxicity. Among other roles,                     hUPF1 plays a very important function in mRNA quality control,                 including nonsense-mediated decay (NMD), a critical cellular mechanism of mRNA                 surveillance that functions to detect nonsense mutations and prevent the expression                 of truncated or erroneous proteins [43]. It has been proposed that a principal event underlying                 neurodegeneration occurs when cytotoxic, truncated proteins are expressed from                 normally degraded nonsense-containing RNAs and pseudogene transcripts [44]. Our finding                 that hUPF1 and hUPF2 rescue the toxicity of                 FUS/TLS is broadly consistent with this hypothesis; however, our results from                 examination of the level of specific NMD mRNA substrates (see below) suggest that                 NMD cannot be the sole RNA pathway affected by FUS or its suppressors in yeast. Our                 results do suggest the possibility that disruption of some part of the RNA quality                 control process might be related to the toxicity mechanism of FUS/TLS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>64562</offset><text>Because ECM32, hUPF1, or hUPF2                 expression all rescue FUS toxicity without dissolving the cytosolic aggregates or                 changing the expression level of FUS or its mislocalization, it is likely that                 toxicity involves disruption of some essential cellular function that is either                 restored or compensated for by the introduction of these genes. One possibility is                 that FUS over-expression sequesters RNA and/or protein molecules involved in                 nonsense-mediated decay, which is an essential function in yeast. Yeast contains no                 FUS homologue, but many of the other proteins important for RNA quality control are                 conserved between S. cerevisiae and humans.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>65334</offset><text>To check the possible direct effect of FUS on the NMD pathway, we determined pre-mRNA                 levels of CYH2 and MER2, which are among the                 reported substrates of the NMD pathway in yeast. If this pathway is impaired by FUS                 over-expression, it is then expected that both pre-mRNAs would be accumulated.                 However, only CYH2 pre-mRNA is increased by FUS expression in our                 assay, suggesting that FUS may interfere with other RNA quality control systems,                 rather than exerting a direct effect on the NMD pathway. It is worth mentioning that                     CYH2 pre-mRNA was accumulated to a much higher level than                     MER2 in our assay (5-fold versus 2-fold; unpublished data);                 this may help to explain no detected accumulation of MER2 pre-mRNA                 when FUS is over-expressed.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>66241</offset><text>In addition, co-expression of hUPF1 and yeast ECM32, two suppressors                 of FUS toxicity, had different effects on the accumulated CYH2                 pre-mRNA level caused by over-expression of FUS. Together with their different                 rescuing effects on other yeast neurodegenerative disease models, these data suggest                 that hUPF1 and ECM32 may rescue FUS toxicity through different                 mechanisms.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>66692</offset><text>It is important to emphasize that we are not claiming that this is a yeast model of a                 human disease. It is a model for the cytotoxicity of a human protein whose                 mislocalization to the cytosol causes a devastating neurologic disorder. It appears                 to recreate the salient features of that part of the pathology: cytosolic                 localization, aggregation in stress granules, and cell death. It has allowed us to                 determine the parts of the protein essential for toxicity, to test hypotheses about                 the factors responsible for localization, and to identify suppressor genes in both                 the yeast and human genome. We believe that the fact that wild type and mutant are                 both toxic in this model is not a failing of the model. Both wild-type and mutant                 are mislocalized to the same extent in yeast because the FUS nuclear localization                 signal, where the mutations occur, is not efficient in the microbe, and so if the                 neurotoxicity of the mutants is entirely due to their mislocalization, as has been                 hypothesized by others, then the wild type protein should also be                 toxic in our model, exactly as observed.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>67988</offset><text>In summary, our yeast model recapitulates multiple features of disease-causing mutant                 protein FUS/TLS pathology, including aggregation, cytosolic localization, and                 toxicity, which should make it valuable for studying the function and mechanism of                 toxicity of this protein in human neurodegenerative disorders. In addition, our                 model is amenable to high-throughput small molecule screens to identify compounds                 that suppress FUS/TLS toxicity. Like TDP-43, which saw a number of cell culture and                 animal models follow its identification as an ALS/FTLD protein, we envisage a                 similar trajectory for FUS/TLS. By importing our yeast findings into mammalian cell                 culture and neuronal systems, we anticipate creating a yeast discovery/mammalian                 confirmation paradigm that will yield critical insights into FUS/TLS pathobiology                 and potentially provide therapeutic targets or pathways for exploitation.</text><annotation id="24"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="68703" length="336"/><text>By importing our yeast findings into mammalian cell                 culture and neuronal systems, we anticipate creating a yeast discovery/mammalian                 confirmation paradigm that will yield critical insights into FUS/TLS pathobiology                 and potentially provide therapeutic targets or pathways for exploitation.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>69040</offset><text>Materials and Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>69062</offset><text>Plasmids</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>69071</offset><text>N-terminal GFP-tagged FUS (pYES2/GFP-FUS): GFP tagged FUS gene was amplified from                     pDEST53/FUS by PCR using forward primer 5'- ATTAGCCGGGTACCATGGCCTCAAACGATTATACCC-3',                     and reverse primer 5'-ATTAGCCGTCTAGATTAATACGGCCTCTCCCTGC-3', and                     sub-cloned into KpnI and XbaI sites of yeast expression vector pYES2CT                     (Invitrogen).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>69476</offset><text>Entry clone of FUS (pDONR221/FUS): full-length FUS gene in destination vector                     pDEST53/FUS was transferred into Gateway entry vector pDONR221 (Invitrogen)                     using BP reaction (Invitrogen).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>69702</offset><text>Yeast expression and integration constructs of FUS: A gateway LR reaction                     (Invitrogen) was used to shuttle FUS gene from entry clone into gateway                     compatible yeast expression vectors (pAG vectors, www.addgene.org/yeast_gateway).</text><annotation id="25"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="69702" length="267"/><text>Yeast expression and integration constructs of FUS: A gateway LR reaction                     (Invitrogen) was used to shuttle FUS gene from entry clone into gateway                     compatible yeast expression vectors (pAG vectors, www.addgene.org/yeast_gateway).</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>69970</offset><text>Yeast expression vectors of UPF1 (pYES2/UPF1) and UPF2 (pYES2/UPF2): UPF1 and                     UPF2 were amplified by PCR. The genes were generously supplied by Dr. Lynne                     Maquat of Rochester University School of Medicine and Dentistry. UPF1 was                     sub-cloned into BamHI and XhoI sites of pYES2CT, and UPF2 was sub-cloned into                     NotI and XhoI sites of pYES2CT.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>70388</offset><text>GFP and FUS NLS fusion constructs were generated using an overlap PCR strategy.                     GFP and HRP1 or FUS/TLS NLSs were PCR amplified in the first step. In the second                     step, GFP was combined with either HRP1 or FUS/TLS NLS PCR using the GFP forward                     primer and HRP1 or FUS/TLS reverse primer. This product was cloned into                     Pst1/Spe1 sites in the pRS424Gal1 vector. For "FUS_plus" or                     "FUS_switch" constructs, the first PCR step amplified FUS or FUS                     lacking the C-terminal PY NLS and the Hrp1 NLS. Full-length FUS or NLS-lacking                     FUS were combined with the Hrp1 NLS PCR product and amplified in a second                     reaction containing a FUS forward primer and HRP1 reverse primer. This final                     product was cloned into pRS424Gal1. Oligo sequences are available upon                     request.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>71345</offset><text>All constructs made for this study were confirmed by sequencing.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>71410</offset><text>Yeast Strains, Media, and Growth Conditions</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>71454</offset><text>1XFUS integration strain was generated by linearizing pAG303GAL1FUS with NheI,                     and followed by transformation into W303alpha strain (MATalpha can1-100,                     his3-11,15, leu2-3,112, trp1-1, ura3-1, ade2-1).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>71689</offset><text>2XFUS integration strain was generated by linearizing pAG303GAL1FUS with NheI,                     and pAG304GAL1FUS with BstZ17I, followed by transformation into W303alpha strain                     (MATalpha can1-100, his3-11,15, leu2-3,112, trp1-1, ura3-1, ade2-1). Both 1XFUS                     and 2XFUS strains were confirmed by PCR.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>72024</offset><text>Htt25 and Htt103 strains: N-terminal fragments of huntingtin with 23 glutamine                     repeats or 103 glutamine repeats, respectively, were integrated into HIS locus                     of W303 strain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>72238</offset><text>rmt1Delta, rmt2Delta, hsp104Delta, and rnq1Delta strains are homozygous diploid                     from the yeast deletion collection (Research Genetics). BY4743 is its isogenic                     wild type.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>72436</offset><text>Synthetic media lacking uracil (Ura-), histidine (His-), histidine and tryptophan                     (His-Trp-), histidine and uracil (His-Ura-), and containing 2% glucose,                     raffinose, or galactose were used for the respective yeast strains.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>72698</offset><text>Yeast cells were grown in 30  incubators (plate) or 30  shakers (liquid                     medium) unless specially mentioned.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>72828</offset><text>Growth curves of FUS NLS strains were monitored using Bioscreen (www.bioscreen.fi). Yeast strains were pre-grown in 2%                     raffinose, diluted to an OD600 of 0.01, and induced with 0.1% galactose                     for 2 d with OD measurements taken every 10 min. Raw data were averaged among                     triplicates and OD600 plotted over time. Three independent experiments were                     performed and a representative shown.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>73291</offset><text>Yeast Over-expression Library</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>73321</offset><text>The over-expression library is the FLEXGene Collection [45]. Additional information about                     the yeast FLEXGene Collection is available at http://plasmid.med.harvard.edu/PLASMID/GetCollection.do?collectionName=HIP%20FLEXGene%20Saccharomyces%20cerevisiae%20%28yeast%29%20ORF%20collection%20%28pBY011%20expression%20vector%29.                     For the expression screen, the clones were transferred into a                     galactose-inducible expression plasmid (pBY011; CEN,                         URA3, AmpR) using the Gateway technology                     (Invitrogen).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>73917</offset><text>Yeast Transformation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>73938</offset><text>Yeast expression constructs were transformed using standard PEG/lithium acetate                     method. Briefly, cells from one-milliliter overnight culture plus DNA construct                     was mixed with transformation buffer (80 microl 50% PEG3350, 10                     microl 1M DTT, and 10 microl 2M LiAC), followed by incubation at 42                      waterbath for 45 min (with occasional mix during the incubation). Cells were                     then spread onto respective dropout plates and grown at 30  for 3-4                     d.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>74494</offset><text>Serial Dilution and Spotting</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>74523</offset><text>Yeast cells were grown overnight to mid-log phase. Cultures were then normalized                     to OD600  = 5.0, and 10x serially diluted and spotted                     onto the respective dropout plates containing 2% glucose or                     galactose.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>74794</offset><text>Immunobotting</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>74808</offset><text>Yeast crude extract was subjected SDS-PAGE, and protein was transferred onto PVDF                     membrane (Millipore), followed by 30 min incubation with superblock (Thermosci).                     PVDF membrane was then hybridized with primary antibody for 2 h at RT, followed                     by wash with 1XPBS 5 times (10 min each), incubation with secondary antibody                     conjugated with alkaline phosphatase (Promega) for 2 h, and 5x10 min wash                     with 1XPBS. The membrane was finally developed with one-step NBT/BCIP solution                     (Thermo scientific). The anti-FUS antibody (Abcam) and anti-PGK1 (Invitrogen)                     were used at a dilution of 1:1,000. The AP conjugated secondary antibody                     was used at dilution of 1:10,000. For FUS NLS fusion experiments, cells                     were induced with 0.1% galactose for 6 h, after which they were fixed and                     visualized with anti-FUS antibody as described above.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>75837</offset><text>Fluorescence Microcopy of GFP-Tagged Protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>75882</offset><text>Cells were grown in selective raffinose medium to early log phase, and 2%                     galactose was then added into the medium for 6 h to induce the expression of the                     protein. Cells were harvested and fixed 1 h on ice in freshly made fixation                     buffer (50 mM Kpi pH 6.5; 1 mM MgCl2, and 4% formaldehyde). Cells were                     then washed 3 times with 1XPBS before viewing by fluorescence microscopy.</text><annotation id="26"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="76233" length="104"/><text>Cells were                     then washed 3 times with 1XPBS before viewing by fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>76338</offset><text>To visualize the nucleus, following the PBS washes, cells were incubated in PBS                     containing DAPI (1:1,000) for 30 min. Cells were finally washed 3 times                     with 1XPBS before viewing by fluorescence microscopy.</text><annotation id="27"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="76476" length="107"/><text>Cells were finally washed 3 times                     with 1XPBS before viewing by fluorescence microscopy.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>76586</offset><text>Filter Retardation Assay</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>76611</offset><text>Yeast cells were grown in raffinose medium to early log phase. Expression of                     protein was induced for 6 h by adding 2% galactose into the medium. Cells                     were harvested and treated with zymolase, and the spheroblast was broken by                     vortex, and protein extract was prepared by collecting the supernatant                     (centrifuge 5,000 rpm, 5 min). Protein concentration was determined by Bradford                     assay. 2% of SDS was added to the protein sample before the sample was                     boiled for 5 min. 10-fold dilutions of protein samples was prepared in 96-well                     plates, and loaded onto the prepared manifold (V&amp;P scientific) with                     cellulose acetate membrane (pore size 2 micro; Whatman). Vacuum was applied                     and all the liquid was sucked through the manifold. After washing 5 times with                     0.2% SDS, the manifold was dissembled carefully, and cellulose acetated                     membrane was used for Western blotting to detect protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>77709</offset><text>Indirect Immunofluorescence of Yeast Cells</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>77752</offset><text>Indirect immunofluorescence of yeast cells with FUS antibody was adapted from                     chapter 40 of "Guide to Yeast Genetics and Molecular Biology." Yeast                     cells were grown to early log phase in the selective raffinose medium, and                     expression of the interested protein was induced for 6 h by 2% galactose.                     Cells were fixed in freshly made fixation buffer (50 mM Kpi pH 6.5, 1 mM MgCl2,                     and 4% formaldehyde) for 2 h at room temperature. Cells were then washed                     two times with PM buffer (0.1 M Kpi pH 7.5, 1 mM MgCl2) and resuspended with PM                     buffer with protease inhibitors (Roche). Cells were then treated with zymolase                     for 20 min. Spheroblasts were harvested at 2,000 rpm and washed once with PM                     with protease inhibitors. Cells were then spotted onto poly-l-lysine coated well                     of the slide. We immersed the slide for 5 min each in methanol and acetone                     (pre-cooled to -20 C). Cells were then blocked by PBS-block (1XPBS,                     1% dried milk, 0.1%BSA, 0.1% octyl glucoside) for 1 h,                     followed by incubation with primary antibody (Abcam, 1:100 dilution),                     wash, incubation with secondary antibody conjugated with fluorescein                     (Invitrogen, 1:100 dilution), and wash.</text><annotation id="28"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="77752" length="355"/><text>Indirect immunofluorescence of yeast cells with FUS antibody was adapted from                     chapter 40 of "Guide to Yeast Genetics and Molecular Biology." Yeast                     cells were grown to early log phase in the selective raffinose medium, and                     expression of the interested protein was induced for 6 h by 2% galactose.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>79206</offset><text>5 microl of mounting solution (Santa Cruz Biotech) was added to each well, and                     cells were viewed using fluorescence microscope. To visualize nucleus, DAPI                     (1:1,000) was included in the mounting solution.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>79449</offset><text>Yeast Over-expression Library Screen</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>79486</offset><text>One copy integrated FUS strain (1XFUS) was grown to early log phase and washed                     with 0.1 M lithium acetate (LiAc) in TE buffer. Cells were then resuspended in                     0.1 M LiAC, and 35 microl of the resuspended cells was aliquoted into 96-well                     plates and incubated at 30  for 30 min. 1 microl of yeast FLEXGene                     Collection DNA (the Collection consists of vectors expressing each of 5,535                     individual yeast genes, arrayed on 96-well plates; see [44]), and 125 microl                     transformation buffer (0.1 M Lithium Acetate, 10% DMSO, 40%                     PEG3350) was then added to the plate, followed by 30 min incubation at 30 ,                     and 20 min heat shock at 42 . Cells were pelleted and resuspended into 200                     microl of synthetic Ura- dropout medium, 10 microl of which was then                     inoculated into new plate with 200 microl Ura- dropout medium in each well.                     Cells were grown at 30 C for 2-3 d. All the liquid handling was done                     using liquid handling robot (Tecan Freedom EVO).</text><annotation id="29"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="79822" length="444"/><text>1 microl of yeast FLEXGene                     Collection DNA (the Collection consists of vectors expressing each of 5,535                     individual yeast genes, arrayed on 96-well plates; see [44]), and 125 microl                     transformation buffer (0.1 M Lithium Acetate, 10% DMSO, 40%                     PEG3350) was then added to the plate, followed by 30 min incubation at 30 ,                     and 20 min heat shock at 42.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>80644</offset><text>Cells were mixed using 96-well plate vortexer (VWR), and quadruply spotted onto                     Ura-Glucose and Ura-Galactose plates using Singer RoToR Robot (Singer                     Instruments), followed by incubation at 30  for 2-3 d. Colonies grown                     on galactose plates were considered as putative suppressors.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>80988</offset><text>After the whole library (5,535 genes) was screened, all the putative suppressors                     were re-tested by re-transforming the corresponding genes into 1XFUS strain.                     Those surviving the re-test are finally confirmed by manually transforming each                     of the corresponding genes into 1XFUS stain, and phenotype was re-tested by                     serial dilution.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>81399</offset><text>Pre-mRNA Analysis by qRT-PCR</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>81428</offset><text>Cells were grown in synthetic raffinose medium to early log phase; expression of                     FUS and its suppressors (hUPF1 and ECM32) were induced by                     2% galactose for 6 h. Cells were harvested, and total RNA was extracted                     using the standard hot acidic phenol method (Current Protocols in Molecular                     Biology, Unit 13.12). RNA was treated with DNase I (Promega) to remove the trace                     contamination of genomic DNA before it was used for cDNA synthesis. cDNA was                     synthesized using the superscript III platinum two-step qRP-PCR kit                     (Invitrogen). qPCR was performed on stepOnePlus real-time PCR system (Applied                     Biosystems). The PCR mixture contained platinum Taq and SYBR Green I                     (Invitrogen) and the corresponding primers: CYH2Pre forward: 5'-GTATCAAATGGTTGTAGAGAGCGC-3', CYH2Pre                     reverse: 5'-TGTGGAAGTATCTCATACCAACC-3'; MER2Pre forward:                         5'-                         GAACAAGATGCTGCTACGAACGGT-3', MER2Pre reverse:                         5'-                         TGCCTGTAGCTGGAATCCGACTTT-3'. mRNA levels were                     quantified and normalized to that of 18sRNA, using primers: 18sRNA forward:                         5'-                         TTCTGGCTAACCTTGAGTCC-3', and 18sRNA reverse 5'-                     AAA ACG TCC TTG GCA AAT GC-3'.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>82913</offset><text>Supporting Information</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>82936</offset><text>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>82997</offset><text>This work is supported by grants from the Fidelity Biosciences Research                     Initiative (GAP and DR), the ALS Therapy Alliance (GAP, DR, DAB and RHB), and                     NIH 1RC1NS06839 (LJH and RHB). RHB also receives funding from NIH U01NS05225-03,                     R01NS050557-05, and 1RC2NS070342-01 as well as the Angel Fund, the ALS                     Association, Project ALS, and the Pierre L. de Bourgknecht ALS Research                     Foundation. Susan Lindquist is an investigator of the Howard Hughes Medical                     Institute. DFT was supported by National Research Service Award fellowship                     number NS614192. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and                     analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>83825</offset><text>References</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Figlewicz;given-names:D. A</infon><infon key="volume">362</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Patterson;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Siddique;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rosen;given-names:D. R</infon><infon key="fpage">59</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8446170</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">62</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Sapp;given-names:P</infon><offset>83836</offset><text>Mutations in Cu/Zn superoxide dismutase gene are associated with                         familial amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Richieri-Costa;given-names:A</infon><infon key="volume">75</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Silva;given-names:H. C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mitne-Neto;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nishimura;given-names:A. L</infon><infon key="fpage">822</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15372378</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><infon key="source">Am J Hum Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">831</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Middleton;given-names:S</infon><offset>83965</offset><text>A mutation in the vesicle-trafficking protein VAPB causes                         late-onset spinal muscular atrophy and amyotrophic lateral                         sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Blair;given-names:I. P</infon><infon key="volume">74</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Huynh;given-names:H. M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bennett;given-names:C. L</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chen;given-names:Y. Z</infon><infon key="fpage">1128</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15106121</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><infon key="source">Am J Hum Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1135</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Puls;given-names:I</infon><offset>84141</offset><text>DNA/RNA helicase gene mutations in a form of juvenile amyotrophic                         lateral sclerosis (ALS4).</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Hu;given-names:X</infon><infon key="volume">319</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Tripathi;given-names:V. B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blair;given-names:I. P</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sreedharan;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">1668</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18309045</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1672</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Vance;given-names:C</infon><offset>84257</offset><text>TDP-43 mutations in familial and sporadic amyotrophic lateral                         sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Tamrazian;given-names:E</infon><infon key="volume">323</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Leclerc;given-names:A. L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bosco;given-names:D. A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kwiatkowski;given-names:T. J;suffix:Jr</infon><infon key="fpage">1205</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19251627</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1208</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Vanderburg;given-names:C. R</infon><offset>84354</offset><text>Mutations in the FUS/TLS gene on chromosome 16 cause familial                         amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:De Vos;given-names:K. J</infon><infon key="volume">323</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hortobagyi;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Rogelj;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vance;given-names:C</infon><infon key="fpage">1208</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19251628</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1211</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Nishimura;given-names:A. L</infon><offset>84471</offset><text>Mutations in FUS, an RNA processing protein, cause familial                         amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 6.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Izumi;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="volume">465</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ito;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Morino;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Maruyama;given-names:H</infon><infon key="fpage">223</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20428114</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">226</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kato;given-names:H</infon><offset>84593</offset><text>Mutations of optineurin in amyotrophic lateral                         sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Chen-Plotkin;given-names:A. S</infon><infon key="volume">466</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hart;given-names:M. P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kim;given-names:H. J</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Elden;given-names:A. C</infon><infon key="fpage">1069</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20740007</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1075</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Johnson;given-names:B. S</infon><offset>84675</offset><text>Ataxin-2 intermediate-length polyglutamine expansions are                         associated with increased risk for ALS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">65</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rothstein;given-names:J. D</infon><infon key="fpage">S3</infon><infon key="issue">Suppl 1</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19191304</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Ann Neurol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">S9</infon><offset>84797</offset><text>Current hypotheses for the underlying biology of amyotrophic                         lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">187</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cleveland;given-names:D. W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Polymenidou;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ilieva;given-names:H</infon><infon key="fpage">761</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19951898</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">772</infon><offset>84901</offset><text>Non-cell autonomous toxicity in neurodegenerative disorders: ALS                         and beyond.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Truax;given-names:A. C</infon><infon key="volume">314</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kwong;given-names:L. K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sampathu;given-names:D. M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Neumann;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">130</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17023659</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">133</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Micsenyi;given-names:M. C</infon><offset>85002</offset><text>Ubiquitinated TDP-43 in frontotemporal lobar degeneration and                         amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Hartley;given-names:J. A</infon><infon key="volume">67</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Highley;given-names:J. R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kirby;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hewitt;given-names:C</infon><infon key="fpage">455</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20385912</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Arch Neurol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">461</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Hibberd;given-names:R</infon><offset>85119</offset><text>Novel FUS/TLS mutations and pathology in familial and sporadic                         amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Yan;given-names:J</infon><infon key="volume">67</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Bigio;given-names:E. H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zhai;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Deng;given-names:H. X</infon><infon key="fpage">739</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20517935</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Ann Neurol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">748</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Fecto;given-names:F</infon><offset>85237</offset><text>FUS-immunoreactive inclusions are a common feature in sporadic                         and non-SOD1 familial amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Krieger;given-names:C</infon><infon key="volume">42</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Dejesus-Hernandez;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stewart;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rademakers;given-names:R</infon><infon key="fpage">170</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20544928</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Muscle Nerve</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">176</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Graff-Radford;given-names:N</infon><offset>85377</offset><text>Fus gene mutations in familial and sporadic amyotrophic lateral                         sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Trojanowski;given-names:J. Q</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lee;given-names:V. M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pesiridis;given-names:G. S</infon><infon key="fpage">R156</infon><infon key="issue">R2</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19808791</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Hum Mol Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">R162</infon><offset>85476</offset><text>Mutations in TDP-43 link glycine-rich domain functions to                         amyotrophic lateral sclerosis.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hodges;given-names:J. R</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Burrell;given-names:J. R</infon><infon key="fpage">349</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20413882</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">J Alzheimers Dis</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">360</infon><offset>85589</offset><text>From FUS to Fibs: what's new in frontotemporal                         dementia?</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">136</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Cleveland;given-names:D. W</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lagier-Tourenne;given-names:C</infon><infon key="fpage">1001</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19303844</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1004</infon><offset>85670</offset><text>Rethinking ALS: the FUS about TDP-43.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">41</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Barr;given-names:F. G</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Xia;given-names:S. J</infon><infon key="fpage">2513</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16213703</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><infon key="source">Eur J Cancer</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">2527</infon><offset>85708</offset><text>Chromosome translocations in sarcomas and the emergence of                         oncogenic transcription factors.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Bentmann;given-names:E</infon><infon key="volume">29</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Edbauer;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Rodde;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Dormann;given-names:D</infon><infon key="fpage">2841</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20606625</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">2857</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Fischer;given-names:I</infon><offset>85824</offset><text>ALS-associated fused in sarcoma (FUS) mutations disrupt                         Transportin-mediated nuclear import.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Zhou;given-names:H</infon><infon key="volume">19</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ko;given-names:H. K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lemay;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bosco;given-names:D. A</infon><infon key="fpage">4160</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20699327</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Hum Mol Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">4175</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Burke;given-names:C</infon><offset>85941</offset><text>Mutant FUS proteins that cause amyotrophic lateral sclerosis                         incorporate into stress granules.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Baker;given-names:M</infon><infon key="volume">132</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Roeber;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Rademakers;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Neumann;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">2922</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19674978</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Brain</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">2931</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kretzschmar;given-names:H. A</infon><offset>86060</offset><text>A new subtype of frontotemporal lobar degeneration with FUS                         pathology.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Rademakers;given-names:R</infon><infon key="volume">118</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kretzschmar;given-names:H. A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Roeber;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Neumann;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">605</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19669651</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Acta Neuropathol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">616</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Baker;given-names:M</infon><offset>86155</offset><text>Abundant FUS-immunoreactive pathology in neuronal intermediate                         filament inclusion disease.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Nukina;given-names:N</infon><infon key="volume">66</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Suzuki;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Koyano;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Doi;given-names:H</infon><infon key="fpage">131</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19833157</infon><infon key="source">Neurosci Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">133</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kuroiwa;given-names:Y</infon><offset>86270</offset><text>The RNA-binding protein FUS/TLS is a common aggregate-interacting                         protein in polyglutamine diseases.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Lindquist;given-names:S. L</infon><infon key="volume">302</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:DeVit;given-names:M. J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Outeiro;given-names:T. F</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Willingham;given-names:S</infon><infon key="fpage">1769</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14657499</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1772</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Muchowski;given-names:P. J</infon><offset>86395</offset><text>Yeast genes that enhance the toxicity of a mutant huntingtin                         fragment or alpha-synuclein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">302</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lindquist;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Outeiro;given-names:T. F</infon><infon key="fpage">1772</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14657500</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1775</infon><offset>86509</offset><text>Yeast cells provide insight into alpha-synuclein biology and                         pathobiology.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Haynes;given-names:C. M</infon><infon key="volume">313</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cashikar;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Gitler;given-names:A. D</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cooper;given-names:A. A</infon><infon key="fpage">324</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16794039</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">328</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Hill;given-names:K. J</infon><offset>86608</offset><text>Alpha-synuclein blocks ER-Golgi traffic and Rab1 rescues neuron                         loss in Parkinson's models.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lindquist;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Khurana;given-names:V</infon><infon key="fpage">436</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20424620</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Nat Rev Neurosci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">449</infon><offset>86724</offset><text>Modelling neurodegeneration in Saccharomyces                             cerevisiae: why cook with baker's yeast?</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Gitler;given-names:A. D</infon><infon key="volume">105</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lindquist;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:McCaffery;given-names:J. M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Johnson;given-names:B. S</infon><infon key="fpage">6439</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18434538</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">6444</infon><offset>86838</offset><text>A yeast TDP-43 proteinopathy model: exploring the molecular                         determinants of TDP-43 aggregation and cellular toxicity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Strathearn;given-names:K. E</infon><infon key="volume">41</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Geddie;given-names:M. L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Chesi;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gitler;given-names:A. D</infon><infon key="fpage">308</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">19182805</infon><infon key="year">2009</infon><infon key="source">Nat Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">315</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Hamamichi;given-names:S</infon><offset>86980</offset><text>Alpha-synuclein is part of a diverse and highly conserved                         interaction network that includes PARK9 and manganese                         toxicity.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Chesi;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hart;given-names:M. P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Diaz;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sun;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">PLoS Biology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Shorter;given-names:J</infon><offset>87150</offset><text>Molecular determinants and genetic modifiers of aggregation and                         toxicity for the ALS disease protein FUS/TLS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Meyer;given-names:T</infon><infon key="volume">75</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Rabe;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Neumann;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Waibel;given-names:S</infon><infon key="fpage">815</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">20660363</infon><infon key="year">2010</infon><infon key="source">Neurology</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">817</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ludolph;given-names:A. C</infon><offset>87284</offset><text>Novel missense and truncating mutations in FUS/TLS in familial                         ALS.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Dreyfuss;given-names:G</infon><infon key="volume">75</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Paushkin;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Friesen;given-names:W. J</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rappsilber;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">3107</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12964758</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><infon key="source">Anal Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">3114</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Mann;given-names:M</infon><offset>87376</offset><text>Detection of arginine dimethylated peptides by parallel precursor                         ion scanning mass spectrometry in positive ion mode.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Swanson;given-names:M. S</infon><infon key="volume">279</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:King;given-names:R. W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Yadav;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cheng;given-names:D</infon><infon key="fpage">23892</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15056663</infon><infon key="year">2004</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">23899</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Weinstein;given-names:E. J</infon><offset>87519</offset><text>Small molecule regulators of protein arginine                         methyltransferases.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Peltz;given-names:S. W</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Banerjee;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Majlesi;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Czaplinski;given-names:K</infon><infon key="fpage">730</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">10836794</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">RNA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">743</infon><offset>87609</offset><text>Mtt1 is a Upf1-like helicase that interacts with the translation                         termination factors and whose overexpression can modulate termination                         efficiency.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">26</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Parker;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Dunckley;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Segal;given-names:S. P</infon><infon key="fpage">5120</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16782896</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">5130</infon><offset>87804</offset><text>Sbp1p affects translational repression and decapping in                         Saccharomyces cerevisiae.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Proft;given-names:M</infon><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Serrano;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Posas;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pascual-Ahuir;given-names:A</infon><infon key="fpage">37373</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11500510</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">37378</infon><offset>87910</offset><text>Multiple levels of control regulate the yeast cAMP-response                         element-binding protein repressor Sko1p in response to                         stress.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Sauer;given-names:N</infon><infon key="volume">281</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Klebl;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Machnik;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Weider;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">13513</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">16533810</infon><infon key="year">2006</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">13524</infon><offset>88081</offset><text>Vhr1p, a new transcription factor from budding yeast, regulates                         biotin-dependent expression of VHT1 and BIO5.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Brandsch;given-names:M</infon><infon key="volume">120</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Neubert;given-names:R. H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wohlrab;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Grafe;given-names:F</infon><infon key="fpage">428</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">12603856</infon><infon key="year">2003</infon><infon key="source">J Invest Dermatol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">433</infon><offset>88215</offset><text>Transport of biotin in human keratinocytes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">103</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Steitz;given-names:J. A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shu;given-names:M. D</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lykke-Andersen;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">1121</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11163187</infon><infon key="year">2000</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1131</infon><offset>88259</offset><text>Human Upf proteins target an mRNA for nonsense-mediated decay                         when bound downstream of a termination codon.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Hoffmann;given-names:K</infon><infon key="volume">29</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Diers;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shuelke;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Grohmann;given-names:K</infon><infon key="fpage">75</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">11528396</infon><infon key="year">2001</infon><infon key="source">Nat Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">77</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lucke;given-names:B</infon><offset>88391</offset><text>Mutations in the gene encoding immunoglobulin mu-binding protein                         2 cause spinal muscular atrophy with respiratory distress type                         1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Maquat;given-names:L. E</infon><infon key="volume">95</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Dietz;given-names:H. C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Perlick;given-names:H. A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sun;given-names:X</infon><infon key="fpage">10009</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9707591</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">10014</infon><offset>88570</offset><text>A mutated human homologue to yeast Upf1 protein has a                         dominant-negative effect on the decay of nonsense-containing mRNAs in                         mammalian cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Rosbash;given-names:M</infon><infon key="volume">90</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Donahue;given-names:J. L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Peltz;given-names:S. W</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:He;given-names:F</infon><infon key="fpage">7034</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8346213</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">7038</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Jacobson;given-names:A</infon><offset>88759</offset><text>Stabilization and ribosome association of unspliced pre-mRNAs in                         a yeast upf1-mutant.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Maquat;given-names:L. E</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Isken;given-names:O</infon><infon key="fpage">699</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">18679436</infon><infon key="year">2008</infon><infon key="source">Nat Rev Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">712</infon><offset>88869</offset><text>The multiple lives of NMD factors: balancing roles in gene and                         genome regulation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">64</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Connolly;given-names:J. B</infon><infon key="fpage">968</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15780493</infon><infon key="year">2005</infon><infon key="source">Med Hypotheses</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">972</infon><offset>88975</offset><text>Neurodegeneration caused by the translation of nonsense: does                         macromolecular misfolding impair the synchrony of gene                         expression?</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Murthy;given-names:T. V</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Bhullar;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Rolfs;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hu;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="fpage">536</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">17322287</infon><infon key="year">2007</infon><infon key="source">Genome Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">543</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Zhu;given-names:C</infon><offset>89152</offset><text>Approaching a complete repository of sequence-verified                         protein-encoding clones for Saccharomyces                         cerevisiae.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>89309</offset><text>Abbreviations</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89323</offset><text>ALS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89327</offset><text>amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89357</offset><text>fALS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89362</offset><text>familial amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89401</offset><text>FUS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89405</offset><text>fused in sarcoma</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89422</offset><text>GFP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89426</offset><text>green fluorescent protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89452</offset><text>mRNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89457</offset><text>messenger RNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89471</offset><text>NIFID</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89477</offset><text>neuronal intermediate filament inclusion disease</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89526</offset><text>NLS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89530</offset><text>nuclear localization signal</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89558</offset><text>NMD</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89562</offset><text>nonsense-mediated decay</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89586</offset><text>OPTN</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89591</offset><text>optineurin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89602</offset><text>sALS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89607</offset><text>sporadic ALS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89620</offset><text>SETX</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89625</offset><text>senataxin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89635</offset><text>TLS</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89639</offset><text>translocated in liposarcoma</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89667</offset><text>VAPB</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89672</offset><text>vesicle associated membrane protein B</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89710</offset><text>VHRE</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>89715</offset><text>vitamin H-responsive element</text></passage></document></collection>