<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>sentence.key</key><document><id>2132640</id><passage><infon key="volume">139</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hopper;given-names:Anita K.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Martin;given-names:Nancy C.</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">9412475</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vaduva;given-names:Gabriela</infon><infon key="fpage">1821</infon><infon key="issue">7</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">2132640</infon><infon key="journal-title">The Journal of Cell Biology</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="lpage">1833</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Actin-binding Verprolin Is a Polarity Development Protein Required for the Morphogenesis and Function of the Yeast Actin Cytoskeleton </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>135</offset><text>Yeast verprolin, encoded by VRP1, is implicated in cell growth, cytoskeletal organization, endocytosis and mitochondrial protein distribution and function. We show that verprolin is also required for bipolar  bud-site selection. Previously we reported that additional actin suppresses the temperature-dependent  growth defect caused by a mutation in VRP1. Here we  show that additional actin suppresses all known defects  caused by vrp1-1 and conclude that the defects relate to  an abnormal cytoskeleton. Using the two-hybrid system, we show that verprolin binds actin. An actin-binding domain maps to the LKKAET hexapeptide located  in the first 70 amino acids. A similar hexapeptide in  other acting-binding proteins was previously shown to  be necessary for actin-binding activity. The entire 70- amino acid motif is conserved in novel higher eukaryotic proteins that we predict to be actin-binding, and  also in the actin-binding proteins, WASP and N-WASP.  Verprolin-GFP in live cells has a cell cycle-dependent  distribution similar to the actin cortical cytoskeleton. In  fixed cells hemagglutinin-tagged Vrp1p often co-localizes with actin in cortical patches. However, disassembly of the actin cytoskeleton using Latrunculin-A does  not alter verprolin's location, indicating that verprolin  establishes and maintains its location independent of  the actin cytoskeleton. Verprolin is a new member of  the actin-binding protein family that serves as a polarity  development protein, perhaps by anchoring actin. We  speculate that the effects of verprolin upon the actin cytoskeleton might influence mitochondrial protein sorting/function via mRNA distribution.</text><annotation id="0"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="641" length="64"/><text>Using the two-hybrid system, we show that verprolin binds actin.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1807</offset><text>The actin cytoskeleton plays crucial roles in fundamental processes such as cell growth, differentiation  and migration, localized membrane growth, endocytosis, and cell division. Saccharomyces cerevisiae is an  excellent organism for the study of the actin cytoskeleton  because many of its components are conserved (Drubin  and Nelson, 1996) and it is possible to probe the function  of particular components in yeast via genetic approaches.  S. cerevisiae cells display cytoskeletal asymmetry during  the cell cycle. As cells initiate a cell cycle, the cytoskeleton  becomes organized anisotropically to facilitate polarized  growth. In G1, a ring of actin marks the site where the bud  will grow. In S and G2, as the bud continues its growth, the  actin cytoskeleton remains highly polarized toward the  bud. Cortical patches are concentrated mainly in the bud  and cables are visible converging toward the mother-bud  axis. After cell division, the newly formed cells are unpolarized and another round of polarization starts with a new  cell cycle (Adams and Pringle, 1984). During the cell cycle  the actin cytoskeleton plays roles in bipolar bud-site selection and polarized secretion of components, as well as polarized movement of organelles such as mitochondria to  the daughter cell (Smith et al., 1995; Wang and Bretscher,  1995; Yang et al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3171</offset><text>The actin cytoskeleton is also important for processes  not necessarily associated with the cell cycle, such as endocytosis (Munn et al., 1995). In our efforts to identify cellular components involved in the distribution of nucleus-encoded proteins to mitochondria, we identified mutations  of VRP1, PAN1, (Zoladek et al., 1995) and RSP5 (Zoladek et al., 1997). Interestingly, all of these genes affect endocytosis and show genetic interactions with each other  and/or with components of the actin cytoskeleton (Munn  et al., 1995; Zoladek et al., 1995; Wendland et al., 1996;  Zoladek et al., 1997). The current studies focus on deciphering the cellular function of the VRP1 gene product.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3861</offset><text>VRP1 codes for verprolin, a 817-amino acid protein  very rich (22%) in proline. Besides a defect in the ability  to grow at elevated temperatures, vrp1 mutants have aberrant cytoskeletons (Donnelly et al., 1993; Zoladek et al.,  1995), defects in cytoplasmic/mitochondrial distribution of  a mitochondrial protein (Zoladek et al., 1995), and defects  in endocytosis (Munn et al., 1995; Zoladek et al., 1997).  We provide evidence here that verprolin is also required  for bipolar budding patterns. How verprolin is involved in  these diverse processes is not understood. In particular, it  is not known whether all the defects are related to the cytoskeletal disorganization or whether verprolin has multiple functions in yeast.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4592</offset><text>In attempts to clone VRP1, ACT1 encoding actin was  uncovered as a suppressor of the vrp1-1 mutation. We  showed that when supplied with actin encoded from a low  copy centromere-containing vector or from a single additional integrated copy of ACT1, vrp1-1 mutant cells could  grow at the nonpermissive temperature; however, ACT1  did not suppress the temperature-sensitive (ts)1 growth defect caused by a disruption allele of VRP1, vrp1::LEU2  (Zoladek et al., 1995). Therefore, an apparent increase in  the intracellular concentration of actin caused allele-specific suppression of the ts growth defects of vrp1 mutant  cells. To begin to understand the role of verprolin in yeast,  we determined which of the defects of vrp1 mutant cells  could be corrected by ACT1. Here we show that actin supplied from a low copy centromere-containing vector corrects all vrp1 defects.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5467</offset><text>We show that verprolin is an actin-binding protein located at positions coincident with the actin cortical cytoskeleton. Many other actin-binding proteins are localized  similarly to verprolin (Doyle et al., 1996; Amberg et al.,  1997; Waddle et al., 1997). The cytoskeletal location of  many actin-binding proteins is dependent upon an appropriate cytoskeleton. However, the polarized locations of  some actin-binding proteins can be actin cytoskeleton independent (Ayscough et al., 1997). Our results demonstrate that verprolin achieves its intracellular localization  through an actin-independent pathway. The pattern of intracellular localization of verprolin, its independence from  actin, its role in bud-site selection, as well as the phenotypes of vrp1 mutants provide evidence that verprolin is a  polarity development protein required for the correct assembly of the actin cytoskeleton.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>6364</offset><text>Materials and Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6386</offset><text>Strains and Genetic Techniques</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6417</offset><text>Media for yeast growth were prepared according to Sherman (1991). Cells  were transformed by the one-step method described by Chen et al. (1992).  The strains used in this study are listed in Table I. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6619</offset><text>General DNA Manipulations</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6645</offset><text>DNA manipulations were done using standard techniques (Sambrook et  al., 1989). Escherichia coli strains employed were DH5alpha and RR1. Restriction endonucleases and modifying enzymes were obtained from New  England Biolabs Inc. (Beverly, MA) or from Promega (Madison, WI). Sequenase was obtained from United States Biochemical Corp., (Cleveland,  Ohio).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>6998</offset><text>Plasmid Construction</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7019</offset><text>To construct the VRP1-green fluorescent protein (GFP) fusion, a 0.7-kb  PCR product containing the GFP open reading frame (ORF) from  pSEY18/GAL1-10/GFP (gift from Roger Y. Tsien, University of California, San Diego, CA) was obtained using the following primers: the 5'oligo,  5'GCCCCGGGCATGAGTAAAGGAGAAGAACTTTTC3' and the  3'oligo, 5'CATTCCCGGGTATAGTTCATCCATGCCATG3'. The PCR  fragment contained built-in SmaI ends and the amplified DNA was cloned  into pGEM-T vectors. From pGEM-T vectors the 0.7-kb GFP was released by digesting with SmaI and further cloned in-frame at the carboxy  terminus of VRP1 that had been digested at the unique BsaAI site, one  codon before the stop codon. The ~4.7-kb HindIII piece containing the  VRP1-GFP fusion and the VRP1 regulatory sequences were transferred  to the single-copy yeast shuttle vector YCplac33 generating YCpVRP1GFP.</text><annotation id="1"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0416</infon><location offset="7019" length="172"/><text>To construct the VRP1-green fluorescent protein (GFP) fusion, a 0.7-kb  PCR product containing the GFP open reading frame (ORF) from  pSEY18/GAL1-10/GFP (gift from Roger Y.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7905</offset><text>For YCpVRP1 plasmid, a 4-kb piece containing the VRP1 gene was removed from the pT6 plasmid (Zoladek et al., 1995) by digesting with HindIII  and cloned into pUC19. From pUC19, the 4-kb Hind III fragment containing VRP1 was further cloned into YCplac33 vector giving rise to YCpVRP1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8189</offset><text>For all two-hybrid constructs, two vectors were used: pACT2, encoding  the Gal4 DNA transcription activation domain, and pAS-CYH2, encoding the Gal4 DNA-binding domain. Both vectors were a gift from S.J.  Elledge (Baylor College of Medicine, Houston, TX). To eliminate possible confusion related to the nomenclature of vector and genes we cloned  in these vectors, we designated pACT2 as pDAD, for DNA Activating  Domain. In the same way, pAS-CYH2 was replaced by pDBD for DNA- Binding Domain in the name of all constructs.</text><annotation id="2"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="8189" length="168"/><text>For all two-hybrid constructs, two vectors were used: pACT2, encoding  the Gal4 DNA transcription activation domain, and pAS-CYH2, encoding the Gal4 DNA-binding domain.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8713</offset><text>For pDAD-VRP1 or pDBD-VRP1, a 2.5-kb PCR product containing  the VRP1 ORF and 71 bp from the trimer of the hemagglutinin (HA) epitope was cloned into pGEM-T giving rise to pGEM-VRP1-2Hy. The  5'oligo was 5'GTACGGATCCAAATGGCAGGTGCTCCA3' and the  3' oligo was 5'TCATATGGATAGGATCC3'. Both oligos have built-in  BamHI ends. The ~2.6-kb BamHI fragment was transferred to pDAD or  pDBD vectors to generate in-frame fusions between Gal4p DNA-binding  domain or the Gal4p transcription activation domain and Vrp1p.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9234</offset><text>pDAD-ACT1 and pDBD-ACT1 were constructed in the following  way: a 1.1-kb PCR product containing the ACT1 ORF following the intron was cloned into pGEM-T vector giving rise to pGEM-ACTIN. For  the PCR reaction, the template was pT3 (Zoladek et al., 1995). Use of the  5' oligo, 5'GTACGGATCCAGGTTGCTGCTTTGGTT3', eliminates the  codons before the intron in the ACT1 gene. The 3' oligo was 5'CAGTGGATCCACACAAAAGCAGAGATTA3'. Both oligos have built-in  BamHI ends. From pGEM-ACTIN the BamHI fragment containing the  ACT1 coding region was transferred to pDAD or pDBD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9808</offset><text>For pDAD-PFY or pDBD-PFY the following procedure was used: a  0.35-kb PCR product containing the PFY1 ORF following the intron was  cloned into pGEM-T giving rise to pGEM-PFY. For the PCR reaction the  template was YCpPFY1 (a gift from S.S. Brown, University of Michigan,  Ann Arbor, MI), the 5' oligo was 5'GTACGGATCCCATACACTGATAACTTA3' and the 3' oligo was 5'GTACGGATCCAAATTAGTATTGAACACC3'. Both oligos have built-in BamHI ends. The BamHI fragment was transferred to pDAD or pDBD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10303</offset><text>For constructing pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2, the pGEM-VRP1-2Hy  plasmid was digested with SalI and the 4.1-kb piece containing the plasmid backbone and amino terminus of VRP1 coding for 363 amino acids  was ligated and further digested with KpnI. The release of an internal  0.35-kb KpnI fragment and further ligation at this KpnI site generated an  out-of-frame fusion beyond codon 70, and generated pGEM-VRP1Delta  SalDeltaKpn1-2. This construct encodes VRP1 amino acids 1-70. The ~0.9-kb  BamHI-SalI fragment was then cloned into pDAD digested BamHI-SalI  giving rise to pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>10899</offset><text>For pDAD-VRP1DeltaKpn1-3, the pGEM-VRP1-2Hy plasmid was digested with KpnI and two pieces, 0.3 and 0.7 kb were released. The backbone plasmid was then closed to create an in-frame fusion between amino  acids 70 and 717 of Vrp1p. This plasmid, pGEM-VRP1DeltaKpn1-3, encodes  the amino terminus (amino acids 1-70) and the carboxy end (amino acids  717-817) of verprolin fused in frame to the Gal4p DNA transcription activation domain. The ~0.5-kb BamHI fragment was removed and cloned in  frame into pDAD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11403</offset><text>For pDAD-VRP1 71-817, a ~2.2-kb PCR product of VRP1 coding for  a protein missing the first 70 amino acids was first cloned into pGEM-T  vectors. From pGEM-T, the 2.2-kb VRP1 fragment containing built-in  BamHI ends was cut out and cloned into the pDAD vector. For PCR, the  5' oligo was: 5'GGGATCCGTACCGTCAGTAGTAAAGGACCC3'  and the 3' oligo was 5'TCATATGGATAGGATCC3'.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11786</offset><text>pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2/EE contains a fusion between the Gal4-DNA-activating domain and the first 70 amino acids of verprolin in which  the two lysines in the LKKAET motif have been mutated to glutamic acids. To construct this plasmid, pGEM-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2 was used for reverse PCR (Hemsley et al., 1989). 5'GAGGAGGCTGAGACCAATGATAGAAGTGCCCCAATC3' and 5'TAGTTTCATTCCCTTTCTA- ATGTCACC3' were the primers used. The correct sequences of the 70- amino acids coding region was verified by DNA sequencing. After removing  the A-tails of the PCR product with T4 polymerase and phosphorylation with T4 kinase, the PCR product was circularized with T4 ligase. The  BamHI-SalI piece was removed and cloned in pDAD vector-digested  BamHI-SalI to give rise to pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2/EE.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12577</offset><text>YCpVRP1-HA was constructed as follows: a 4-kb HindIII VRP1 piece  including the promoter region and the 3'UTR was cloned into pUC19,  giving rise to pUCH. This plasmid was digested at the unique BsaAI site,  one codon before the stop codon in VRP1 gene, and a HaeIII fragment  containing roughly three copies of the hemmaglutinin trimer was placed in  frame at the BsaAI site, creating the tagged version of VRP1. From  pUC19 the HindIII piece containing the tagged VRP1 was digested and  cloned in YCplac33 vector giving rise to YCpVRP1-HA.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13121</offset><text>pT3 is a plasmid from a library inserted into a centromere-containing  vector that contains the ACT1 gene. Transposon mutagenesis of the genomic insert of this plasmid showed that ACT1 is responsible for complementation of the vrp1-1 mutation (Zoladek et al., 1995).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13388</offset><text>YCpLEUMod5p-I,KR6ET, a low copy plasmid bearing a hemagglutinin trimer-tagged version of Mod5p-I,KR6, was a gift from T. Zoladek (Polish Academy of Sciences, Warsaw, Poland).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13563</offset><text>Two-hybrid Analysis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13583</offset><text>Two-hybrid studies were done according to Chien et al. (1991). The host  strain for two-hybrid studies was Y190, a derivative of Y153, and kindly  provided by S.J. Elledge (Durfee et al., 1993). Strain Y190 was transformed sequentially with each of the pairs of plasmids tested. Nitrocellulose membrane lifts, assays of beta-galactosidase activity, and growth on  leu-trp-his- plates were done according to recommendations (Durfee  et al., 1993). Growth on media-lacking histidine was tested in the presence  of 25, 50, and 100 mM 3-amino-1,2,4-triazole.</text><annotation id="3"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="13583" length="54"/><text>Two-hybrid studies were done according to Chien et al.</text></annotation><annotation id="4"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="13646" length="100"/><text>The host  strain for two-hybrid studies was Y190, a derivative of Y153, and kindly  provided by S.J.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>14144</offset><text>Microscopic Imaging and Analysis</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14177</offset><text>For verprolin-GFP localization studies, cells from exponentially growing  cultures or from a one-day fresh plate were used. Cells were spotted on  microscope slide, covered with a coverslip and visualized immediately under a 60x objective (1.4 numerical aperture) using either FITC-filtered illumination or differential interference contrast (DIC) optics. Pictures  were taken on Kodak T-Max 400. A Nikon Microphot-FX equipped with  B-1E filter cube/420-490 excitation filter/5151F barrier filter was used.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14687</offset><text>For verprolin-HA and actin staining in the same cells, indirect immunofluorescence was done as follows: 10 ml logarithmic cultures were fixed  with 5% formaldehyde for 30 min, washed twice with 1x PBS, pH 6.5,  treated with 0.2% Triton X-100 for 10 min, digested 45 min with zymolyase 20T in the presence of beta-mercaptoethanol, washed once with sol. B  (1.2 M sorbitol, 40 mM phosphate buffer, pH 6.5, 0.05 mM MgCl2). After  incubating for an additional 10 min with 0.2% Triton X-100, cells were incubated with primary antibody against HA (12CA5; BAbCO, Richmond,  CA) at a 1:750 dilution for 1 h in solution, washed once with PBS, and  then incubated with secondary Cy3-conjugated goat anti-mouse antibody  (Jackson Immunoresearch Laboratories, Inc., West Grove, PA) at a 1:600  dilution for 45 min. Cells were then washed two times with PBS, and  stained with 3.3 muM Oregon green 488 phalloidin in the dark for 30 min.  Cells were washed once and mounted on slides. Images were acquired and  digitized directly with a SenSys (Photometrics Ltd., Tucson, AZ) CCD  camera coupled to a Nikon Optiphot-2 microscope. Illumination was controlled by a Lambda 10-2C filter-wheel controller (Sutter Instrument  Company, Novato, CA). Image processing was done using IPLab Spectrum software (Signal Analytics, Co., Vienna, VA) running on a 6500/225  Power Macintosh. Files were converted into and further processed using  Adobe Photoshop 4.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16122</offset><text>Staining</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16131</offset><text>For all experiments, except for the co-localization studies described above,  rhodamine phalloidin was used. Cells were fixed and further processed as  recommended (Adams and Pringle, 1991). The endocytosis test was done  according to Dulic et al. (1991). Calcofluor staining was done on live cells  as described (Pringle, 1991).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>16461</offset><text>Latrunculin-A Studies</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16483</offset><text>For growth of cells in the presence of Latrunculin-A (LAT-A), a 200-mul  logarithmic culture was treated with either LAT-A (Molecular Probes  Inc., Eugene, OR) at a concentration of 100 muM in DMSO for 15 min or  with DMSO alone (control). The cells were visualized immediately. At the  same time point, an aliquot from each culture was fixed and processed for  immunofluorescence with rhodamine phalloidin. For cells released from  G0, a culture enriched in unbudded cells was incubated with LAT-A at  100 muM as described for 4 h (Ayscough et al., 1997) and then visualized using the same conditions as for verprolin-GFP localization studies. Actin  cytoskeleton disassembly was verified by staining with rhodamine phalloidin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17212</offset><text>The halo assay to assess LAT-A sensitivity was done as described previously (Ayscough et al., 1997). Plates were incubated at 23 C for 48 h.  Relative apparent LAT-A sensitivity was calculated according to Reneke  et al., 1988.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>17441</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>17449</offset><text>Additional Actin Causes Allele-specific Suppression of  vrp1-1 Phenotypes</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17523</offset><text>We previously showed that vrp1-1 cells transformed with a  centromere-containing plasmid containing ACT1, pT3, or  harboring an integrated copy of ACT1 are able to grow at  nonpermissive temperatures (Zoladek et al., 1995). We  analyzed actin levels in total cell extracts prepared from  wild-type cells (strain T8.1D) or vrp1-1 cells (strain TZ33)  transformed with vector alone or with pT3. When indexed  against the cytoplasmic protein Rna1p, actin levels were  two to fourfold greater in vrp1-1 cells bearing pT3 than in  either parental (strain T8.1D) or vrp1-1 (strain TZ33) cells  transformed with vector alone (data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_3</infon><offset>18159</offset><text>ACT1 Restores the Cytoskeletal Polarization of vrp1-1  Cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18221</offset><text>Mutant vrp1-1 cells have a disorganized cytoskeleton. Cortical patches are distributed randomly between  mother and bud, no concentration of patches can be detected during any phase of the cell cycle, and no actin cables are visible. The defect is more severe when cells are  grown on nonfermentable carbon sources (see mitochondrial defects below), even at permissive temperatures  (Zoladek et al., 1995). To determine whether additional  actin corrects the defects in actin cytoskeleton organization, cells were grown on lactate medium at the permissive  temperature, fixed, and stained with rhodamine phalloidin. Wild-type cells transformed with vector alone have  polarized cytoskeletons (Fig. 1, a and b), whereas mutant  vrp1-1 cells bearing the vector alone have shape alterations and a random distribution of cortical patches between mother and bud (Fig. 1, c and d). In contrast, vrp1-1  cells bearing pT3, encoding ACT1, have a wild-type morphology and polarized distribution of cortical patches between the mother and the bud (Fig. 1, e and f). Therefore,  a two to fourfold increase in the intracellular concentration of actin confers polarized cytoskeleton and normal  shape to vrp1-1 cells. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_3</infon><offset>19427</offset><text>ACT1 Corrects the Endocytosis Defects of vrp1-1 Cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19482</offset><text>Cells with mutations in VRP1 are defective in endocytosis  (Munn et al., 1995; Zoladek et al., 1997). It is known (Benedetti et al., 1994; Munn et al., 1995) that the actin cytoskeleton plays an essential role in the internalization step of  endocytosis in yeast. Many cytoskeletal proteins, such as  actin, Sac6p, calmodulin, End3p, End4p, and type I myosins (Geli and Riezman, 1996) are necessary for endocytic  traffic. To determine whether the defect in endocytosis of  vrp1 mutant cells is related to actin cytoskeleton defects,  we studied fluid phase endocytosis (Dulic et al., 1991) of  vrp1 cells in the presence or absence of the centromere-containing plasmid encoding actin. Parental cells (strain  T8.1D) accumulate Lucifer yellow in vacuoles (Fig. 2, A  and B), whereas vrp1-1 mutant cells do not accumulate  any detectable levels of this compound (Fig. 2, C and D).  However, mutant cells containing pT3 show accumulation  of Lucifer yellow in vacuoles in a manner indistinguishable  from wild-type cells (Fig. 2, E and F). Therefore, an increase in the intracellular quantity of actin suppresses the  endocytosis defect caused by the vrp1-1 mutation. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_3</infon><offset>20649</offset><text>ACT1 Partially Corrects the Mitochondrial Defects of  vrp1-1 Cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20717</offset><text>Mutant vrp1-1 cells have defects in mitochondrial function as assessed by their inability to grow on nonfermentable carbon sources at temperatures exceeding  30 C (Table II). In contrast, vrp1-1 mutant cells grow well  at 30 , 34 , and 35 C and poorly at 37  or 38 C on glucose-containing media. Vrp1-1 mutant cells provided with additional actin grow on glycerol-containing media at temperatures from 30  to 36 C, but not at 38 C (Table II). Therefore,  a two- to fourfold increase in actin levels partially restores  mitochondrial function to vrp1-1 mutants. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21288</offset><text>To determine if additional Act1p affects the delivery of  proteins to mitochondria, we assessed the functional levels  of cytosolic Mod5p-I. Mod5p is a tRNA isopentenyl transferase that modifies tRNAs. Cytosolic levels of Mod5p can  be assessed by studying the levels of modified tRNA Tyr UAA,  which in turn are monitored by assaying nonsense suppression of the lys2-1 allele (Zoladek et al., 1995). Mod5p-I,KR6 is a form of Mod5p-I, with an alteration that provides its quantitative delivery to mitochondria. Parental cells  (strain T8.1D) harboring the plasmid-encoding Mod5p-I,KR6 deliver the great majority of Mod5p-I,KR6 to mitochondria. As these cells do not have sufficient cytosolic  Mod5p-I,KR6 to modify the tRNA Tyr UAA encoded by SUP11,  they can not grow on media lacking lysine (lys-). In contrast, vrp1-1 cells (strain TZ33) bearing the plasmid encoding Mod5p-I,KR6, grow on lys- media. We analyzed the  growth on lys- media of vrp1-1 mutant cells with and without a centromere-containing plasmid encoding actin. Parental cells (strain T8.1D) bearing YCpLEUMod5p-I,KR6ET  and a control centromere-containing plasmid encoding  URA3 alone are able to grow on ura-leu- media (Fig. 3 a),  but not on ura-leu-lys- (Fig. 3 d). By contrast, vrp1-1 cells  bearing YCpLEUMod5p-I,KR6ET and the control URA3  plasmid are able to grow on both ura-leu- (Fig 3 c) and  ura-leu-lys- media (Fig. 3 f). Although able to grow well  on ura-leu- media (Fig. 3 b) vrp1-1 cells bearing YCp  LEUMod5p-I,KR6ET and pT3 containing ACT1 show an  intermediate phenotype on ura-leu-lys- media (Fig. 3 e).  Thus, the partial suppression of the Lys+ phenotype in  vrp1-1 cells indicates that excess actin causes a decrease in  the functional cytoplasmic pool of Mod5p-I,KR6. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>23085</offset><text>Verprolin Is Required for Bipolar Budding But Not for  Axial Budding</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23154</offset><text>Because verprolin is associated with many actin-related  functions and the actin cytoskeleton is required for diploid-specific bipolar budding pattern (Yang et al., 1997),  we examined whether verprolin affects the budding pattern. Haploid vrp1::LEU2 cells (Fig. 4, C and D), like their  wild-type counterparts (Fig. 4, A and B), bud axially. In  contrast, diploid cells homozygous for vrp1::LEU2 (Fig. 4,  G and H) are unable to bud bipolarly like wild-type cells  do (Fig. 4, E and F); instead, they bud randomly. Introduction of the VRP1-GFP fusion on a low copy plasmid  which complements the ts growth of the mutant cells leads  to restoration of the bipolar budding pattern (Fig. 4, I and  J). Thus, verprolin is required for bipolar budding pattern  in diploid cells, but does not appear to influence the axial  budding pattern of haploid cells. Although the budding  pattern in diploid cells homozygous for vrp1::LEU2 is random, the cells are still able to form buds, indicating that  verprolin is required for bud site-selection and not bud  growth per se. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>24223</offset><text>Verprolin Interacts with Actin in the Two-Hybrid System</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24279</offset><text>ACT1 and VRP1 show allele-specific interactions as ACT1  can suppress the vrp1-1 mutation, but not the vrp1::LEU2  disruption. Single-copy suppression and allele-specific interactions provide genetic evidence that Act1p and Vrp1p  may physically interact. We tested the genetic predictions  by using the two-hybrid system (Fields and Song, 1989) to  detect verprolin-actin physical interactions. Also, because  verprolin has 12 stretches of three to nine polyprolines and  polyproline stretches have been shown to bind another actin-binding protein, profilin, we tested whether there is an  interaction between verprolin and profilin. Each gene was  cloned into the vector encoding the Gal4p DNA-binding  domain and the vector encoding the DNA-activating domain and all possible combinations were analyzed. Neither  VRP1 nor ACT1 activated the reporter genes, LacZ and  HIS3, when transformed alone in the Y190 tester strain.  pDBD-PFY, encoding profilin appended to the Gal4p  DNA-binding domain, activated the reporter genes by itself. However, pDAD-PFY, encoding profilin appended  to the Gal4p transcription activation domain did not.  Therefore, pDAD-PFY was used to test interactions between pDBD-ACT1 and pDBD-VRP1. We found that  verprolin interacts with actin but not with profilin (Table  III). Both LacZ and HIS3 transcription (at 100 mM 3-amino- 1,2,4-triazole) are activated when VRP1 and ACT1 are both  present. However, the pDAD-VRP1 plasmid is mitotically  unstable; the loss of plasmid correlates with the loss of  blue color in these cells. The tendency to lose this plasmid  may be related to our observations that overexpression of  verprolin is detrimental to cells (data not shown). As expected (Amberg et al., 1995), we detected interactions between actin-profilin and actin-actin (Table III). We found  no evidence for the dimerization of verprolin, since the  pair pDAD-VRP1 and pDBD-VRP1 did not activate either reporter gene. </text><annotation id="5"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="24535" length="139"/><text>We tested the genetic predictions  by using the two-hybrid system (Fields and Song, 1989) to  detect verprolin-actin physical interactions.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>26239</offset><text>An Actin-binding Domain Maps at Amino Terminus of Verprolin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26299</offset><text>A computer search using the BEAUTY program (Worley  et al., 1995) revealed that the amino terminal 70 amino acids of verprolin show strong homology with similarly located regions in a number of proteins from various species:  Caenorhabditus elegans CELR144.4 gene product (GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession number U23515), Xenopus  laevis proline rich protein (GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession number X68249) and rat SH3 domain-binding protein  (GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession number U25281) (Fig.  5 A). All these genes code for proteins of unknown function. Further, inspection of the core of this extended motif  revealed the presence of a hexapeptide, LKKAET, conserved in a variety of actin-binding proteins, including thymosin, actobindin, tropomyosin, villin, dematin, myosin  heavy chain, fimbrin, alpha-actinin, and plastin (Fig. 5 B). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27128</offset><text>To determine whether there is an actin-binding domain  at the amino terminus of verprolin (Fig. 5 C), VRP1 deletion and out-of-frame constructs were generated (Fig. 6).  If the actin-verprolin interactions detected by the two- hybrid method result from the interaction of the region of  verprolin containing the LKKAET motif, plasmids encoding this region of verprolin should then generate proteins  that interact with actin. Deletion of the carboxy-terminal  455 amino acids generated pDAD-VRP1DeltaSal coding for  verprolin amino acids 1-362. This part of verprolin interacts with actin in the two-hybrid system (Fig. 6). pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-3, which fuses in-frame the first 70 with  the last 100 codons of verprolin, generates a shorter version of verprolin that shows strong interaction with actin.  Finally, pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2 that has an out-of-frame  fusion coding for only the first 70 amino acids of verprolin  was found to code for a protein able to bind actin. Therefore, the first 70 amino acids of verprolin are sufficient for  actin-verprolin interactions in the two-hybrid system. </text><annotation id="6"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="27672" length="74"/><text>This part of verprolin interacts with actin in the two-hybrid system (Fig.</text></annotation><annotation id="7"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="28116" length="123"/><text>Therefore, the first 70 amino acids of verprolin are sufficient for  actin-verprolin interactions in the two-hybrid system.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28232</offset><text>To test whether the LKKAET motif that resides within  the 70-amino acid domain is necessary for the verprolin- actin interaction, we generated a mutant version of the sequence encoding this hexamer. Based on the alignment in  Fig. 5 B and on mutagenesis studies of beta-thymosin (Van  Troys et al., 1996), we chose to mutate the two basic residues of this sequence to acidic residues. We found that the  70-amino acid motif encoding the sequence LEEAET was  unable to interact with actin in the two-hybrid system.  Therefore, as anticipated, the hexamer is necessary for the  interaction of verprolin with actin.</text><annotation id="8"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="28617" length="128"/><text>We found that the  70-amino acid motif encoding the sequence LEEAET was  unable to interact with actin in the two-hybrid system.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28849</offset><text>If verprolin-actin interactions are solely dependent  upon the 70-amino acid motif, constructs not containing  this motif should then generate proteins that fail to interact with actin. To test this, a fusion between the Gal4p  DNA-activating domain and a fragment of VRP1 encoding amino acids 71-817 (pDAD-VRP1 71-817) was constructed. pDAD-VRP1 71-817 shows less activation of LacZ  or HIS3 reporter genes than pDAD-VRP1DeltaSalDeltaKpn1-2.  Therefore, whereas the first 70 amino acids of verprolin,  containing the LKKAET motif, are sufficient for binding  to actin, other actin-binding sequences might reside in verprolin and/or other sequences may influence the efficiency  of actin-binding.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29550</offset><text>Suppression of vrp1-1 phenotypes by actin indicate that  verprolin-actin interactions are important for the function  of verprolin. If so, versions of verprolin lacking the actin-binding domain should fail to complement vrp1 mutations.  Fortuitously, the plasmid encoding the entire verprolin appended to the Gal4p DNA-binding domain (pDAD-VRP1)  constructed for the two-hybrid analyses generates sufficient hybrid protein to complement vrp1-1 (Fig. 6), even  though most of the protein locates to the nucleus as assessed by indirect immunofluorescence (not shown). None  of the other deletion constructs was able to complement  vrp1-1. In particular, pDAD-VRP1 71-817, lacking the  70-amino acid actin-binding domain failed to code for a  functional verprolin (Fig. 6). Provided that this shortened  version of verprolin maintains its native conformation, we  can conclude that the actin-binding domain of verprolin is  important for its in vivo function.</text><annotation id="9"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="29786" length="212"/><text>Fortuitously, the plasmid encoding the entire verprolin appended to the Gal4p DNA-binding domain (pDAD-VRP1)  constructed for the two-hybrid analyses generates sufficient hybrid protein to complement vrp1-1 (Fig.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>30513</offset><text>Cellular Location of Verprolin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30544</offset><text>The allele-specific interactions described above and the  results from the two-hybrid system provide evidence that  verprolin and actin interact directly. To test the prediction  that verprolin localizes with the actin cytoskeleton, we assessed the natural distribution of verprolin tagged with  GFP (Chalfie et al., 1994) in live cells. Wild-type cells (strain  T8.1D) as well as mutant vrp1-1 (strain TZ33) and vrp1:: LEU2 haploid (strain T65.1D) or diploid (strain GVY1)  cells were transformed with low copy YCpVRP1GFP plasmid encoding verprolin-GFP. VRP1-GFP complements  both the vrp1-1 mutation and the vrp1::LEU2 disruption.  Verprolin-GFP expressed from YCpVRP1GFP plasmid  has a similar distribution in wild-type, vrp1-1, vrp1::LEU2,  and vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 mutant cells. However, the  signal is most easily visualized in vrp1::LEU2 (Fig. 7) and  vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 cells bearing YCpVRP1GFP plasmid. In cells preparing to bud, verprolin is localized at the  presumptive budding site (Fig. 7, a and b). As the bud starts  to grow, verprolin concentrates at the tip of the bud (Fig.  7, c and d). There is very little if any verprolin in the cytoplasm. In older buds verprolin has punctate staining, much  like cortical patches (Fig. 7, e and f). Sometimes patches  are at the tip of the buds and sometimes they are eccentric.  When the cells prepare for cytokinesis, there are two rings  of verprolin around the mother-bud neck (Fig. 7, g and h).  Similar actin-containing rings are characteristic for this part  of the yeast life cycle (Adams and Pringle, 1984) and at least  one other actin-binding protein, Aip3p, locates at these  rings during this part of the cell cycle (Amberg et al., 1997).  In freshly divided cells, verprolin patches appear randomly  distributed. The punctuate staining of verprolin-GFP is remarkably similar to that of actin-GFP (Doyle and Botstein, 1996). </text><annotation id="10"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="30544" length="154"/><text>The allele-specific interactions described above and the  results from the two-hybrid system provide evidence that  verprolin and actin interact directly.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32451</offset><text>To determine whether verprolin and actin cortical  patches co-localize, we used indirect immunofluorescence  to locate a HA-tagged version of Vrp1p encoded by the  low copy vector YCpVRP1-HA. This verprolin-HA fusion  fully complements, in either single or multicopy, the vrp1-1  and the vrp1::LEU2 mutations in haploid or diploid cells.  Actin was detected using fluorescent phalloidin. As it was  not possible to stain the cytoskeleton with phalloidin on  slides, the procedure was modified to perform all reactions  in solution (see Materials and Methods). As was found in  studies of live cells, verprolin in fixed cells is located in a  cell cycle-dependent fashion to positions also occupied by  the actin cortical cytoskeleton (Fig. 8). The verprolin patches  overlap most often with actin patches stained with phalloidin. Interestingly, patches in mother cells not associated  with the presumptive bud appear to locate at points of actin cable branch sites (Fig. 8). We conclude that verprolin  is present during the whole cell cycle and is located at or  very near the actin cortical patches. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>33558</offset><text>Verprolin Localization is Actin Independent</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33602</offset><text>Verprolin exhibits a cell cycle-dependent pattern of localization which closely resembles that of its interactor, actin.  To explore the co-dependence of the subcellular distribution of Act1p and Vrp1p we used a pharmacological tool  which recently has been shown to allow the temporal dissection of events involved in bud morphogenesis. LAT-A,  a macrolide isolated from a marine sponge, is a potent  inhibitor of actin cytoskeleton assembly in vertebrates  (Spector et al., 1989) and yeast (Ayscough et al., 1997). We  examined the consequences that disruption of actin cytoskeleton with LAT-A have on verprolin-GFP localization. Cultures of vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 diploid cells (strain  GVY1) containing the VRP1-GFP fusion on a low copy  vector were grown for 15 minutes in the presence of 100  muM LAT-A or in the presence of DMSO diluent alone  and visualized immediately by microscopy. At the same  time point, an aliquot was withdrawn from each culture,  fixed, and processed for rhodamine phalloidin staining.  Whereas the actin cytoskeleton of LAT-A treated cells is  virtually absent (compare Fig. 9, G and H to Fig. 9, C and  D), the localization of verprolin-GFP is unaffected (compare Fig. 9, E and F, to Fig. 9, A and B). Thus, maintenance of the intracellular polarized location of verprolin is  not dependent upon the integrity of actin cytoskeleton. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34976</offset><text>To determine whether verprolin requires the actin cytoskeleton to achieve its location, cultures enriched in unbudded cells (Ayscough et al., 1997) were grown for 4 h in  100 muM LAT-A and then visualized by microscopy. Under  these conditions, while the actin cytoskeleton is disassembled (data not shown), the majority of the cells have verprolin-GFP at the presumptive budding site (Fig. 9, I and  J). This indicates that verprolin achieves its location inside  the cell through an actin-independent pathway.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>35488</offset><text>Effect of Verprolin on Actin Cytoskeleton Stability</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35540</offset><text>Sensitivity to LAT-A varies among actin cytoskeleton-associated mutants and can be used as an indicator of the  effect the respective proteins have on the stability of the  actin cytoskeleton (Ayscough et al., 1997). To test the sensitivity of vrp1 mutant strains to LAT-A we used a halo assay. The vrp1::LEU2 strain harboring the VRP1 gene on a  centromeric plasmid is more resistant to LAT-A than is  the same strain containing vector alone (Fig. 10, compare  A and B). Therefore, disruption of VRP1 gene confers sensitivity to LAT-A. The relative apparent sensitivity (Reneke  et al., 1988) for vrp1::LEU2 compared to vrp1::LEU2  bearing YCpVRP1 is 2.5, a value comparable to that of  other cytoskeletal proteins (Ayscough et al., 1997). This  result suggests that verprolin acts to increase actin cytoskeleton stability. Also, we compared the sensitivity of vrp1-1  cells bearing pT3 to that of vrp1-1 cells bearing YCpVRP1  or an empty vector as control. Although no difference is  apparent between vrp1-1 cells bearing VRP1 or the empty  vector at the permissive temperature, vrp1-1 cells bearing  ACT1 on pT3 show resistance to LAT-A even at a concentration of 2 mM (Fig. 10 E). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>36727</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>36738</offset><text>Verprolin Is an Actin-binding Protein Important for  Numerous Actin-associated Processes</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36827</offset><text>Verprolin was identified as a protein important for both  sorting of Mod5p-I between mitochondria and cytosol  (Zoladek et al., 1995) and endocytosis (Munn et al., 1995).  vrp1-1 mutant cells have an aberrant actin cytoskeleton  which is most apparent at permissive temperatures if the  cells are grown on nonfermentable carbon sources (Zoladek et al., 1995). Allele-specific suppression of vrp1-1 by a  single additional copy of ACT1 (Zoladek et al., 1995) indicated that verprolin and actin physically interact. To confirm the genetic predictions and to understand the nature  of these interactions, we examined vrp1-1 phenotypes, in  addition to temperature sensitive growth, for suppression  by ACT1. We found that ACT1 suppresses vrp1-1 defects  in cytoskeletal polarization, endocytosis, and mitochondrial function. Therefore, it is likely that all phenotypes of  vrp1 mutants relate to an abnormal cytoskeleton.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37746</offset><text>Our studies of fluid phase endocytosis are consistent  with other observations that some, but not all, cytoskeletal  mutations show defects in endocytosis (Munn et al., 1995;  Wendland et al., 1996; Zoladek et al., 1997;). Our data support the involvement of the actin cytoskeleton and, more  probably, cortical actin patches as components of the endocytic machinery. Restoration of endocytosis in vrp1-1  mutant cells by additional actin indicates that their endocytosis defect is most likely a direct consequence of a  defective cytoskeleton.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>38291</offset><text>Actin supplied from a centromere-containing plasmid  also partially corrects the vrp1-1 mitochondrial deficiency  as assessed by growth on nonfermentable carbon sources,  and restores near parental cytoplasmic levels of Mod5p-I,KR6 as assessed by nonsense suppression studies. The  involvement of the actin cytoskeleton with delivery of proteins to mitochondria and with mitochondrial function implicates a novel function for the actin cytoskeleton. Ideas  as to how mitochondria and the cytoskeleton might interrelate are outlined below.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>38830</offset><text>Because the actin cytoskeleton has been shown to be important for bud-site selection (Chant and Pringle, 1995;  Yang et al., 1997), we examined the budding pattern of diploid vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 and haploid vrp1::LEU2 cells.  Verprolin is required for the bipolar budding pattern, but  not for the axial budding pattern. The randomization of  budding pattern in vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 diploids indicates that verprolin is among the proteins required for bipolar site selection in these cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39324</offset><text>We used the two-hybrid system to test the genetic prediction that actin and verprolin interact. We found that actin and verprolin are able to bind each other. The data indicate that verprolin is a new member of the family of  actin-binding proteins. The first 70 amino acids of verprolin are homologous with a similar region of a group of proteins of unknown function from three higher eukaryotes.  Using the two-hybrid system and deletion analysis we  show that the 70 amino acid conserved domain in verprolin is sufficient for interaction with actin.</text><annotation id="11"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="39324" length="95"/><text>We used the two-hybrid system to test the genetic prediction that actin and verprolin interact.</text></annotation><annotation id="12"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="39722" length="153"/><text>Using the two-hybrid system and deletion analysis we  show that the 70 amino acid conserved domain in verprolin is sufficient for interaction with actin.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39877</offset><text>The hexapeptide motif LKKAET, found in a variety of  actin-binding proteins, is in the middle of this conserved  domain. The conservation of the 70-amino acid domain  and the possession of a motif similar to the LKKAET hexapeptide within this domain leads us to predict that these C.  elegans, Xenopus, and rat proteins of unknown function  will subsequently be shown to interact with actin. The  hexapeptide motif has been shown to directly bind actin.  Actobindin, a small actin-binding protein from Acanthamoeba, contains two LKHAET hexapeptides, between  amino acids 15 to 20 and 51 to 56. Lys16 and Lys52 of actobindin can be cross-linked to particular amino acids of  actin (Vandekerckhove et al., 1990; Vancompernolle et al.,  1991). The LKKEKG hexapeptide is crucial for the morphogenic activity of the actin-bundling protein villin. In vitro  studies with a 22-amino acid synthetic peptide including  the villin LKKEKG hexapeptide showed that it is part of  an F-actin binding site involved in the conversion of G-actin  to a polymerization-competent form. The Ser809-Lys825  fragment of villin, containing the first five amino acids of  the LKKEKG hexapeptide, is important for binding to  preformed actin filaments, but insufficient for their induction (Friederich et al., 1992). Moreover, conversion of KKEK  to KEEE in villin significantly decreases villin's morphogenic activity. Finally, the LKKTET hexapeptide in thymosin is essential for binding to actin; mutation of Lys18-19  to Glu drastically abolishes cross-linking with monomeric  actin (Van Troys et al., 1996). By two-hybrid analysis we  showed that the analogous alteration of the verprolin  LKKAET motif to LEEAET destroys the ability of the  70-amino acid domain to interact with actin. Thus it appears that the function of this motif is conserved from  lower to higher eukaryotes.</text><annotation id="13"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="41461" length="178"/><text>By two-hybrid analysis we  showed that the analogous alteration of the verprolin  LKKAET motif to LEEAET destroys the ability of the  70-amino acid domain to interact with actin.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>41743</offset><text>A similarity also exists between the 70-amino acid homology domain of verprolin and COOH-terminal regions  of N-WASP and WASP, both of which contain less conserved versions of the LKKAET motif (Miki et al., 1996;  Symons et al., 1996). Both WASP and N-WASP influence  the organization of the actin cytoskeleton. WASP colocalizes with actin. N-WASP contains a tripartite actin-binding  motif of two shorter verprolin-like domains, one of which  terminates right in the middle of the LKKAET motif followed by a cofilin-like actin-binding motif. When only the  verprolin-like part was tested for actin binding in vitro,  there was very poor binding of N-WASP to actin. When  the whole motif (including the cofilin-like part) was included, actin binding occured (Miki et al., 1996). The data  suggest that part of the 70-amino acid region of verprolin,  in addition to LKKAET, participates in actin binding.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>42651</offset><text>Verprolin Localization Is Independent of Actin Cytoskeleton</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>42711</offset><text>The changes in the cellular distribution of verprolin-GFP  during the cell cycle are very similar to the pattern of  changes that the actin cortical patches undergo during the  cell cycle. However, whereas the actin cytoskeleton is disassembled using the actin assembly inhibitor LAT-A, verprolin's localization is unaffected. Therefore, verprolin  does not require actin to achieve or maintain its polarized  cellular localization. This is not a unique case. Other proteins involved in cell polarity development, including Myo2p,  calmodulin, and Bud6/Aip3p (Ayscough et al., 1997), achieve  polarized localization by an actin-independent pathway.  Also, polarity establishment proteins Cdc42p and Bem1p  become polarized even though the actin cytoskeleton is totally disassembled (Ayscough et al., 1997). Thus, it appears that yeast cells have evolved an actin-independent  pathway for localizing polarity development proteins. By  contrast, other actin-binding proteins including Arp2p,  proteins involved in secretion such as Sec4p, Sec8p, and  the kinesin-like protein Smy1p require actin to achieve  their polarized localization (Ayscough et al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43871</offset><text>The ability of verprolin to localize independently from  actin as well as its role in bud-site selection indicate that it  functions in cell polarity development and maintenance.  As supported by data regarding verprolin's actin-binding  properties, its spatial co-localization with actin and its  downstream effects on cytoskeleton morphogenesis and  stability, verprolin might convey the polarity development  information to the actin cytoskeleton via acting as an anchor for the actin cytoskeleton.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>44373</offset><text>Possible Roles of Verprolin in Mitochondrial Function  and Mitochondrial Protein Sorting</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44462</offset><text>How would verprolin affect cytoskeletal morphology and,  at the same time, be involved in mitochondrial function  and Mod5p-I mitochondria/cytosol sorting? A priori, three  mechanisms could account for the mitochondrial phenotypes: defective mitochondrial movement, altered protein  delivery, and disruption of mRNA sorting. Although it is  known that movement of mitochondria is impaired by  ACT1 mutations that perturb the myosin-binding site (Smith  et al., 1995) and it is known that many, but not all, thermal  sensitive act1 alleles cause abnormal mitochondrial distribution and morphology (Drubin et al., 1993), we do not favor the model that altered mitochondrial distribution/morphology accounts for the mitochondrial defects observed  in vrp1 mutant cells. This is because even on lactate-containing media when the cytoskeleton is clearly depolarized,  vrp1 mutants show no obvious defects in mitochondrial  distribution or morphology (Zoladek et al., 1995 and these  studies). Recently, it has been shown that Mft52p, which  affects the delivery of particular fusion proteins to yeast  mitochondria, is a component of a greater than 5,000-kD  cytosolic particle. Mft52p interacts with mitochondrial targeting sequences and it has been proposed that Mft52p  plays a role in co-translational delivery of proteins to mitochondria (Cartwright et al., 1997; for review see Lithgow  et al., 1997). If such a co-translational mechanism required  a role of the actin cytoskeleton, then the mitochondrial defects we detect in vrp1 mutant cells could be accounted for  by defects in this putative co-translational mechanism of  mitochondrial import.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46113</offset><text>Alternatively, the actin cytoskeleton could be involved  in the delivery of mRNAs encoding mitochondrial proteins to the vicinity of mitochondria. In higher eukaryotes,  the actin cytoskeleton has a role in mRNA sorting (Singer  et al., 1992; Bassell, 1993). mRNA sorting plays an important role in the cellular distribution of cytoskeletal proteins (Lawrence and Singer, 1986; Kislauskis et al., 1994)  and numerous morphogens like Vg-1 (Yisraeli et al., 1990),  nanos (Gavis and Lehmann, 1992) and oskar (Kim-Ha  et al., 1993). The cellular distribution of actin itself has  been shown to occur via sorting of actin mRNA to appropriate subcellular locations (Sundell and Singer, 1991).  Moreover, there are reports implicating mRNA sorting in  the delivery of proteins to mitochondria in higher eukaryotes (Rings et al., 1992; Ricart et al., 1997; for review see  Lithgow et al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>47002</offset><text>Little is known about sorting of mRNA in yeast. ASH1  mRNA is one example of a mRNA which is selectively transported to and expressed solely in daughter cells (Long  et al., 1997). The actin cytoskeleton is actively involved in  the localized transport of ASH1 transcript since mutations  of cytoskeletal genes like ACT1, PFY1, TPM1, and BNI1  impair the transport of ASH1 mRNA to daughter cells  (Long et al., 1997). If mRNAs encoding mitochondrial  proteins are also sorted in yeast, as they are in higher eukaryotic cells, then lesions similar to those affecting the  ability of yeast to distribute ASH1 mRNA might also affect the distribution of transcripts encoding mitochondrial  proteins. The actin-binding protein Bni1p, required for  correct sorting of ASH1 mRNA to daughter cells (Long et  al., 1997), binds the polarity establishment protein Cdc42p  and also Bud6/Aip3p (Evangelista et al., 1997), another  actin-binding protein whose intracellular location (Amberg  et al., 1997) is remarkably similar to that of verprolin. Like  verprolin, Bud6/Aip3p is required for bipolar, but not for  axial budding pattern (Amberg et al., 1997), and both verprolin and Bud6/Aip3p (Ayscough et al., 1997) can achieve  their polarized location even though the actin cytoskeleton is disassembled. Of these three proteins, only Bni1p  has been tested and shown to be responsible for sorting of  ASH1 mRNA. The prediction is that verprolin will be found  to play a role in mRNA sorting.</text><annotation id="14"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="47420" length="277"/><text>If mRNAs encoding mitochondrial  proteins are also sorted in yeast, as they are in higher eukaryotic cells, then lesions similar to those affecting the  ability of yeast to distribute ASH1 mRNA might also affect the distribution of transcripts encoding mitochondrial  proteins.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>48485</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>48504</offset><text>S. cerevisiae Strains Used in This Study</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>48545</offset><text>   Strain  Genotype  Reference   T8.1D  MATalpha SUP11 ade2-1 mod5-1 ura3-1 lys2-1 leu2-3,112 his4-519  Zoladek et al., 1995        TZ33  MATalpha SUP11 ade2-1 mod5-1 ura3-1 lys2-1 leu2-3,112 his4-519 vrp1-1  Zoladek et al., 1995        T65.1D  MATalpha leu2-3, 112 ade1 ura3-52 Ile- MEL1 vrp1::LEU2  Zoladek et al., 1995        Y190  MATa gal4 gal80 his3 trp1-901 ade2-101 ura3-52 leu2-3,112 URA3::GAL- -> lacZ  LYS2::GAL(UAS)- ->HIS3 cyhr  S.J. Elledge, gift (Baylor College  of Medicine, Houston, TX)  Sc467  MATalpha/MATaleu2-3,112/leu2-3,112 ade1/ade1 ura3-52/ura3-52 Ile-/Ile-MEL1/MEL1  Zoladek et al., 1995        GVY1  MATalpha/MATaleu2-3,112/leu2-3,112 ade1/ade1 ura3-52/ura3-52 Ile-/Ile-MEL1/MEL1  vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2  This laboratory</text><annotation id="15"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="48545" length="443"/><text>Strain  Genotype  Reference   T8.1D  MATalpha SUP11 ade2-1 mod5-1 ura3-1 lys2-1 leu2-3,112 his4-519  Zoladek et al., 1995        TZ33  MATalpha SUP11 ade2-1 mod5-1 ura3-1 lys2-1 leu2-3,112 his4-519 vrp1-1  Zoladek et al., 1995        T65.1D  MATalpha leu2-3, 112 ade1 ura3-52 Ile- MEL1 vrp1::LEU2  Zoladek et al., 1995        Y190  MATa gal4 gal80 his3 trp1-901 ade2-101 ura3-52 leu2-3,112 URA3::GAL- -> lacZ  LYS2::GAL(UAS)- ->HIS3 cyhr  S.J.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>49293</offset><text>Cytoskeletal polarization is restored in vrp1-1  cells (strain TZ33) by two- to  fourfold increases in the level  of actin. Representative cells  of wild-type strain T8.1D  bearing an empty plasmid in  a and b; vrp1-1 mutant cells  (strain TZ33) bearing an  empty plasmid in c and d;  and vrp1-1 cells plus ACT1  on the centromere-containing plasmid pT3 in e and f.  Cells were grown on 2% lactate medium at permissive  temperature, fixed as described (Adams and Pringle,  1991) and then stained with  rhodamine-phalloidin for 1 h.  Bar, 3 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>49838</offset><text>Fluid-phase endocytosis is restored in vrp1-1  cells (strain TZ33) by additional actin. Lucifer yellow  uptake in wild-type (strain  T8.1D) cells transformed  with vector alone in A and B;  vrp1-1 mutant cells bearing  vector alone (C and D); and  vrp1-1 cells bearing ACT1 on  pT3 plasmid (E and F). Cells  were grown at permissive  temperature and then incubated with Lucifer yellow  for 2 h. (A, C, and E), FITC  channel. In B, D, and F, the  same cells visualized under  DIC. Bar, 3 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>50330</offset><text>Growth Characteristics of vrp1-1 Cells Bearing ACT1  on the Centromere-containing Plasmid pT3</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>50424</offset><text>     Glycerol  Glucose  23 C  30 C  36 C  38 C 23 C  30 C  36 C  38 C   VRP1  +  +  +  +  +  +  +  +  vrp1-1  +  +-  -  -  +  +  +  -  vrp1-1 and pT3  +  +  +  -  +  +  +  +</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_footnote</infon><offset>50614</offset><text>Growth was assessed after incubating the plates for two days at the indicated temperature. Absence of growth is indicated by (-); wild-type growth indicated by (+), (+-)  designates poor growth.                 </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>50829</offset><text>Extra actin partially suppresses the  Lys+ phenotype of vrp1-1 cells. The plate in  the left is ura-leu- and the one in the right is  ura-leu-lys-. Parental T8.1D cells (a and d);  vrp1-1 cells (strain TZ33), (c and f); vrp1-1  cells bearing pT3 (encoding actin) (b and e).  All strains have Mod5-I,KR6ET gene on a  centromere-containing plasmid; the ura-leu-  master plate was first replica plated to  ura-leu-lys- plate and then to ura-leu- plate.  For all strains, growth was assessed at 23 C.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>51351</offset><text>Budding pattern phenotypes of haploid and diploid  vrp1::LEU2 mutant strains and rescue of mutant phenotype by  VRP1-GFP. Logarithmic cultures of each strain were grown in  selective media at 23 C and then stained with Calcofluor to visualize bud scars. (A) vrp1::LEU2 (strain T65.1D) cells bearing  YCpVRP1GFP plasmid show normal axial budding pattern; (C)  vrp1::LEU2 (strain T65.1D) cells bearing vector alone show axial  pattern; (E) wild-type diploid strain Sc467 bearing an empty plasmid  shows bipolar budding pattern; (G) diploid vrp1::LEU2/vrp1:: LEU2 cells bearing vector alone show random budding pattern;  (H) morphologically, a large proportion of these cells have multiple buds and shape defects; (I) restoration of bipolar budding in  homozygous diploid vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 cells by the VRP1-GFP gene on a centromere-containing plasmid. These cells have  normal morphology (J). B, D, F, H, J are DIC images of A, C, E,  G, I, respectively. Bar, 2.5 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>52323</offset><text>Two-Hybrid Interactions between Verprolin, Actin,  and Profilin</text><annotation id="16"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="52323" length="64"/><text>Two-Hybrid Interactions between Verprolin, Actin,  and Profilin.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>52387</offset><text>     pDBD  pDBD-ACT1  pDBD-PFY  pDBD-VRP1   pDAD  -  -  +  -  pDAD-ACT1  -  +  +  +  pDAD-PFY  -  +  +  -  pDAD-VRP1*  -  +-  +  -</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_footnote</infon><offset>52534</offset><text> The pDAD-VRP1 plasmid is mitoticallly unstable.         </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>52595</offset><text>The actin-binding domain of verprolin. (A) Homologies between the first 70 amino acids of verprolin and C. elegans CELR  144.4 protein ("CELR144.4", GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession number U23515), X. laevis proline-rich protein ("Xlpro-rich", GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession number X68249), and rat SH3-domain-binding protein ("RNU25281", GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ accession  number U25281). Alignment was done using BOXSHADE 3.21 program running on a WWW server at ISREC, Switzerland. Asterisks  designate the position of the LKKAET hexapeptide. (B) LKKAET-like motifs in various cytoskeletal proteins. (C) Diagram of the localization of the actin-binding domain in verprolin. The LKKAET motif is in bold and underlined. The 11 black bars correspond to potential SH3-binding domains having the general pattern APPL/IP.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>53413</offset><text>Mapping of the actin-binding domain of verprolin using  two-hybrid analysis. Various DNA fragments encoding truncated  Vrp1p were cloned in-frame with the Gal4 DNA-activation domain in vector pDAD and the resultant plasmids were transformed into Y190 strain bearing the pDBD-ACT1 construct encoding actin. Association of verprolin with actin was examined by  the qualitative assay for beta-galactosidase and by assessing growth  on media-lacking histidine in the presence of 100 mM 3-amino-1,2,4-triazole. Numbers represent the length in amino acids. Asterisks designate mitotic instability of pDAD-VRP1 and pDAD-VRP1DeltaSal plasmids. (N.D.) not done.</text><annotation id="17"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="53413" length="76"/><text>Mapping of the actin-binding domain of verprolin using  two-hybrid analysis.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>54063</offset><text>In vivo localization  of verprolin-GFP fusion in  vrp1::LEU2 disruptant (as  shown by arrowheads). (a  and c) A verprolin cap marks  the site where the potential  bud will form. (e) Verprolin  localizes to the bud in  patches-like structures. (g)  Cells preparing for cytokinesis have two rings of verprolin-GFP around the neck. b,  d, f, and h are DIC images of  a, c, e, and g frames, respectively. Bar, 2 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>54476</offset><text>Co-localization of  verprolin-HA and actin.  GVY1 cells bearing hemagglutinin-tagged VRP1 on a  centromere-containing vector (YCpVRP1-HA) were  fixed and stained with  12CA5 antibody against the  hemagglutinin tag and then  co-stained with Oregon green  phalloidin as described in  Methods. In A-D representative cells bearing the verprolin-HA fusion are shown.  The same cells, visualized in  the FITC channel to detect  F-actin, are shown in E, F, G,  and H. The two proteins co-localize in many of the cortical patches. However, apparently there are actin patches  which do not seem to contain  verprolin and vice versa. Bar,  1.5 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>55117</offset><text>Localization of verprolin-GFP in the absence or presence of LAT-A in diploid vrp1::LEU2/vrp1::LEU2 cells (strain  GVY1) containing YCpVRP1GFP plasmid. (A-H) Cells were  grown to logarithmic phase, the culture was then divided in two:  half was treated with DMSO alone for 15 min (A-D) and half  with LAT-A solubilized in DMSO for 15 min (E-H). (I and J), a  separate culture of cells enriched for unbudded cells was treated  for 4 h with LAT-A solubilized in DMSO. (A) Localization of  verprolin-GFP in the absence of LAT-A shows the polarized localization of verprolin at the presumptive budding site, in small  buds, and at the mother-bud neck; (C) An aliquot of the culture  used in (A) was fixed and further stained with rhodamine phalloidin to confirm the normal morphology of actin cytoskeletons; (E)  Localization of verprolin-GFP in a logarithmic culture after incubation with LAT-A for 15 min. Verprolin-GFP maintains its intracellular localization at the mother-bud neck or at the tip of  buds. (G) An aliquot of the culture used in E was fixed and  stained with rhodamine phalloidin. Actin cytoskeletons of these  cells are disassembled. (I) Localization of verprolin-GFP in the  presence of LAT-A (4 h) in cells exiting G0. The verprolin-GFP  signal is present at the presumptive budding site while the actin  cytoskeletons of these cells are virtually absent (not shown). B,  D, F, H, and J are DIC images of A, C, E, G, and I, respectively.  Bar, 2 mum.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>56591</offset><text>Halo assay testing the sensitivity of vrp1 mutant  strains to LAT-A. (A) vrp1::LEU2 cells (strain T65.1D) bearing  the VRP1 gene on the centromeric plasmid YCpVRP1. (B) vrp1:: LEU2 cells bearing a vector alone. (C) vrp1-1 cells (strain TZ33)  bearing VRP1 gene on the centromeric plasmid YCpVRP1. (D)  vrp1-1 cells (strain TZ33) with vector alone. (E) vrp1-1 cells (strain  TZ33) bearing ACT1 gene on plasmid pT3. Concentrations of  LAT-A are: 0 (top), 0.5 mM (right), 1 mM (bottom), and 2mM  (left). Strains were grown on ura- selective media at 23 C for 48 h.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>57156</offset><text>Abbreviations used in this paper</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57189</offset><text>DIC</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57193</offset><text>differential interference contrast</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57228</offset><text>GFP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57232</offset><text>green fluorescent protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57258</offset><text>HA</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57261</offset><text>hemagglutinin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57275</offset><text>LAT-A</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57281</offset><text>Latrunculin-A</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57295</offset><text>lys</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57299</offset><text>lysine</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57306</offset><text>ORF</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57310</offset><text>open reading frame</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57329</offset><text>ts</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57332</offset><text>temperature sensitive</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>57354</offset><text>References</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">98</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pringle;given-names:JR</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Adams;given-names:AE</infon><infon key="fpage">934</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6365931</infon><infon key="year">1984</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">945</infon><offset>57365</offset><text>Relationship of actin and tubulin distribution to bud growth in wild-type and morphogenic-mutant Saccharomyces  cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Adams, A.E., and J.R. Pringle. 1991. Staining of actin with fluorochrome-conjugated phalloidin. In Methods Enzymol. Guide to Yeast Genetics and Molecular Biology; Vol. 194. C. Guthrie and G.R. Fink, editors. Academic Press  Inc., San Diego, CA. 729-731.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>57490</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">2</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Botstein;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Basart;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Amberg;given-names:DC</infon><infon key="fpage">28</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7719850</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Nat Struct Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">35</infon><offset>57491</offset><text>Defining protein interactions  with yeast actin in vivo. </text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Pringle;given-names:JR</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Mulholland;given-names:JW</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zahner;given-names:JE</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Amberg;given-names:DC</infon><infon key="fpage">729</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9247651</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Mol BiolCell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">753</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Botstein;given-names:D</infon><offset>57549</offset><text>Aip3p/Bud6p, a yeast actin-interacting protein that is involved in morphogenesis and the selection of bipolar budding sites</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Sanders;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Pokala;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stryker;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ayscough;given-names:KR</infon><infon key="fpage">399</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9128251</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">137</infon><infon key="lpage">416</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Drubin;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Crews;given-names:P</infon><offset>57673</offset><text>High rates of actin filament turnover in budding yeast and roles for actin in establishment and maintenance of cell polarity revealed using the actin inhibitor Latrunculin-A</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">52</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bassell;given-names:GJ</infon><infon key="fpage">127</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8366129</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">133</infon><offset>57847</offset><text>High resolution distribution of mRNA within the cytoskeleton</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Riezman;given-names:H</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Crausaz;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Raths;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Benedetti;given-names:H</infon><infon key="fpage">1023</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7841519</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1037</infon><offset>57908</offset><text>The END3gene encodes a protein that is required for the internalization step of endocytosis and for actin cytoskeleton organization in yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Garrett;given-names:J</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hansen;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Beilharz;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cartwright;given-names:P</infon><infon key="fpage">5320</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9030606</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">5325</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lithgow;given-names:T</infon><offset>58049</offset><text>Mft52, an acid-bristle protein in the cytosol that delivers precursor proteins to yeast mitochondria</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Ward;given-names:WW</infon><infon key="volume">263</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Euskirchen;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tu;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chalfie;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">802</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8303295</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">805</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Prasher;given-names:DC</infon><offset>58150</offset><text>Green fluorescent protein as a marker for gene expression</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">129</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pringle;given-names:JR</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chant;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">751</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7730409</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">765</infon><offset>58208</offset><text>Patterns of bud-site selection in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">21</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kuo;given-names:T-T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Yang;given-names:B-C</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chen;given-names:D-C</infon><infon key="fpage">83</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1735128</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><infon key="source">Curr Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">84</infon><offset>58279</offset><text>One-step transformation of yeast in stationary phase</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Fields;given-names:S</infon><infon key="volume">88</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Sternglanz;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bartel;given-names:PL</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chien;given-names:CT</infon><infon key="fpage">9578</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1946372</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">9582</infon><offset>58332</offset><text>The two-hybrid system: a method to identify and clone genes for proteins that interact with a protein of interest</text><annotation id="18"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="58332" length="114"/><text>The two-hybrid system: a method to identify and clone genes for proteins that interact with a protein of interest.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Orr;given-names:E</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Pallotta;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pocklington;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Donnelly;given-names:SFH</infon><infon key="fpage">585</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7968536</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Mol Microbiol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">596</infon><offset>58446</offset><text>A proline-rich protein, verprolin, involved in cytoskeletal organization and cellular  growth in the yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">93</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Botstein;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Doyle;given-names:T</infon><infon key="fpage">3886</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8632984</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">3891</infon><offset>58580</offset><text>Movement of yeast cortical actin cytoskeleton  visualized in vivo. </text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Wertman;given-names:KF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Jones;given-names:HD</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Drubin;given-names:DG</infon><infon key="fpage">1277</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8167410</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1294</infon><offset>58648</offset><text>Actin structure and function: roles in mitochondrial organization and morphogenesis in budding yeast and identification of the phalloidin-binding site</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">84</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Nelson;given-names:WJ</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Drubin;given-names:DG</infon><infon key="fpage">335</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8608587</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">344</infon><offset>58799</offset><text>Origins of cell polarity</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Dulic, V., M. Egerton, I. Elguindi, S. Raths, B. Singer, and H. Riezman. 1991.  Yeast endocytosis assays. In Methods Enzymol. Guide to Yeast Genetics  and Molecular Biology; Vol. 194. C. Guthrie and G.R. Fink, editors. Academic Press Inc., San Diego, CA. 697-710.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>58824</offset></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Yeh;given-names:S-H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Chen;given-names:P-L</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Becherer;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Durfee;given-names:T</infon><infon key="fpage">555</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8384581</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Elledge;given-names:SJ</infon><infon key="lpage">569</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Lee;given-names:W-H</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Kilburn;given-names:AE</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Yang;given-names:Y</infon><offset>58825</offset><text>The retinoblastoma protein associates with the protein phosphatase type 1 catalytic subunit</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Chow;given-names:CJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Longtine;given-names:MS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blundell;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Evangelista;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">118</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9082982</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">276</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Boone;given-names:C</infon><infon key="lpage">122</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Peter;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Pringle;given-names:JR</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Adames;given-names:N</infon><offset>58917</offset><text>Bni1p, a yeast formin linking Cdc42p and the actin cytoskeleton during polarized morphogenesis</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">340</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Song;given-names:O-K</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Fields;given-names:S</infon><infon key="fpage">245</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2547163</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">246</infon><offset>59012</offset><text>A novel genetic system to detect protein-protein interactions</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Goethals;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Huet;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Vancompernolle;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Friederich;given-names:E</infon><infon key="fpage">81</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1623524</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">70</infon><infon key="lpage">92</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Louvard;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Vandekerckhove;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Finidori;given-names:J</infon><offset>59076</offset><text>An actin-binding site containing a conserved motif of charged amino acid residues is essential for the morphogenic effect of villin</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">71</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lehmann;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gavis;given-names:ER</infon><infon key="fpage">301</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1423595</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">313</infon><offset>59208</offset><text>Localization of nanosRNA controls embryonic polarity</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Riezman;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Geli;given-names:MI</infon><infon key="fpage">533</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8614799</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">535</infon><offset>59261</offset><text>Role of type I myosins in receptor-mediated endocytosis in yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Cortopassi;given-names:G</infon><infon key="volume">17</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Toney;given-names:MD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Arnheim;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hemsley;given-names:A</infon><infon key="fpage">6545</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2674899</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><infon key="source">Nucleic Acids Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">6551</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Galas;given-names:DJ</infon><offset>59326</offset><text>A simple method for site-directed mutagenesis using the polymerase chain reaction</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Macdonald;given-names:PM</infon><infon key="volume">119</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Smith;given-names:JL</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Webster;given-names:PJ</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kim-Ha;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">169</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8275853</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><infon key="source">Development</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">178</infon><offset>59408</offset><text>Multiple RNA  regulatory elements mediate distinct steps in localization of oskarmRNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">127</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Singer;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Zhu;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kislauskis;given-names:EH</infon><infon key="fpage">441</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7929587</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><infon key="source">J  Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">451</infon><offset>59494</offset><text>Sequences responsible for intracellular localization of beta-actin messenger RNA also affect cell phenotype</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">83</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Spudich;given-names:JA</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kron;given-names:SJ</infon><infon key="fpage">6272</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3462694</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">6276</infon><offset>59600</offset><text>Fluorescent actin filaments move on myosin fixed to a glass surface</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">45</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Singer;given-names:RH</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lawrence;given-names:JB</infon><infon key="fpage">407</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3698103</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">415</infon><offset>59668</offset><text>Intracellular localization of messenger RNA for cytoskeletal proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Silver;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Cuezva;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lithgow;given-names:T</infon><infon key="fpage">110</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9149527</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">TIBS (Trends Biochem Sci)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">113</infon><offset>59738</offset><text>Highways for protein delivery to the mitochondria</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Gonzalez;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Meng;given-names:X</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Singer;given-names:RH</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Long;given-names:RM</infon><infon key="fpage">383</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9219698</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">277</infon><infon key="lpage">387</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Jansen;given-names:R-P</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Nasmyth;given-names:K</infon><offset>59788</offset><text>Mating-type switching in yeast controlled by asymmetric localization  of ASH1mRNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Takenawa;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Miura;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Miki;given-names:H</infon><infon key="fpage">5326</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8895577</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">5335</infon><offset>59870</offset><text>N-WASP, a novel actin-depolymerizing protein, regulates the cortical cytoskeletal rearrangement in a PIP2- dependent manner downstream of tyrosine kinases</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Riezman;given-names:H</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Geli;given-names:MI</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stevenson;given-names:BJ</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Munn;given-names:AL</infon><infon key="fpage">1721</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8590801</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1742</infon><offset>60025</offset><text>end5, end6, and  end7: mutations that cause actin delocalization and block the internalization  step of endocytosis in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Pringle, J.R. 1991. Staining of bud scars and other cell wall chitin with calcofluor. In Methods Enzymol. Guide to Yeast Genetics and Molecular Biology; Vol. 194. C. Guthrie and G.R.Fink, editors. Academic Press Inc., San  Diego, CA. 732-735.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>60171</offset></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Thorner;given-names:J</infon><infon key="volume">55</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Courchesne;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blumer;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Reneke;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">221</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2844413</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">234</infon><offset>60172</offset><text>The carboxy-terminal segment of the yeast a-factor receptor is a regulatory domain</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:San;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Izquierdo;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Egea;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ricart;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">635</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9182728</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Biochem J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">324</infon><infon key="lpage">643</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Cuezva;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Martin</infon><offset>60255</offset><text>Subcellular structure containing mRNA for beta subunit of mitochondrial H+-ATP synthase in rat hepatocytes is translationally active</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Grand;given-names:RJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:de Boer;given-names:PA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Buller;given-names:HA</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rings;given-names:EH</infon><infon key="fpage">183</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1563519</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">300</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Moorman;given-names:AF</infon><infon key="lpage">187</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Charles;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Lamers;given-names:WH</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Montgomery;given-names:RK</infon><offset>60388</offset><text>Messenger RNA sorting in enterocytes. Co-localization with encoded proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sambrook, J., E.F. Fritsch, and T. Maniatis. 1989. Molecular Cloning. A Laboratory Manual. Second edition. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Cold  Spring Harbor, NY.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>60464</offset></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sherman, F. 1991. Getting started with yeast. In Methods Enzymol. Guide to  Yeast Genetics and Molecular Biology; Vol. 194. C. Guthrie and G.R. Fink,  editors. Academic Press Inc., San Diego, CA. 3-21.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>60465</offset></passage><passage><infon key="volume">4</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Singer;given-names:RH</infon><infon key="fpage">15</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1558749</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><infon key="source">Curr Opin Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">19</infon><offset>60466</offset><text>The cytoskeleton and mRNA localization</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Pon;given-names:LA</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:O'Sullivan;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Simon;given-names:V</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Smith;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="fpage">1381</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8573793</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1396</infon><offset>60505</offset><text>Organelle-cytoskeletal interactions: actin mutations inhibit meiosis-dependent mitochondrial rearrangement in the budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Kashman;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Blasberger;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shochet;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Spector;given-names:I</infon><infon key="fpage">127</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><infon key="source">Cytoskeleton</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">144</infon><offset>60660</offset><text>Latrunculins-novel marine macrolides that disrupt microfilament organization and affect cell growth: 1. Comparison with cytochalasin D. Cell Motil</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">253</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Singer;given-names:RH</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sundell;given-names:CL</infon><infon key="fpage">1275</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1891715</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1277</infon><offset>60807</offset><text>Requirement of microfilaments in sorting of actin messanger RNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Jiang;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Karlak;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Derry;given-names:JMJ</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Symons;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">723</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8625410</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">84</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Abo;given-names:A</infon><infon key="lpage">734</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Francke;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:McCormick;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lemahieu;given-names:V</infon><offset>60871</offset><text>Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome protein, a novel effector for the GTPase CDC42Hs, is implicated in actin polymerization</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Korn;given-names:ED</infon><infon key="volume">266</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Bubb;given-names:MR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Vandekerckhove;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vancompernolle;given-names:K</infon><infon key="fpage">15427</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1869561</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">15431</infon><offset>60984</offset><text>The interfaces of actin and Acanthamoebaactobindin</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Bubb;given-names:MR</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Vancompernolle;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Van Damme;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vandekerckhove;given-names:J</infon><infon key="fpage">12801</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2376577</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">265</infon><infon key="lpage">12805</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Korn;given-names:ED</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Lambooy;given-names:PK</infon><offset>61035</offset><text>The covalent structure of Acanthamoebaactobindin</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Carlier;given-names:M-F</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Goethals;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Dewitte;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Van Troys;given-names:M</infon><infon key="fpage">201</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8617195</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="lpage">210</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Ampe;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Vandekerckhove;given-names:J</infon><offset>61084</offset><text>The actin binding site of thymosin beta4 mapped by mutational analysis</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Cooper;given-names:JA</infon><infon key="volume">132</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Waterson;given-names:RH</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Karpova;given-names:TS</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Waddle;given-names:JA</infon><infon key="fpage">861</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8603918</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">870</infon><offset>61153</offset><text>Movement of cortical actin patches in yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bretscher;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wang;given-names:T</infon><infon key="fpage">1011</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7579704</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1024</infon><offset>61197</offset><text>The rho-GAP encoded by BEM2regulates cytoskeletal structure in budding yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="volume">135</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Xiao;given-names:Q</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:McCaffery;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wendland;given-names:B</infon><infon key="fpage">1485</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8978817</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">1500</infon><offset>61274</offset><text>A novel fluorescence-activated cell sorter-based screen for yeast endocytosis mutants identifies a yeast homologue of mammalian eps15</text><annotation id="19"><infon key="type">ExperimentalMethod</infon><infon key="PSIMI">0018</infon><location offset="61274" length="134"/><text>A novel fluorescence-activated cell sorter-based screen for yeast endocytosis mutants identifies a yeast homologue of mammalian eps15.</text></annotation></passage><passage><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Smith;given-names:RF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wiese;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Worley;given-names:KC</infon><infon key="fpage">173</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9132271</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Genome Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">184</infon><offset>61408</offset><text>BEAUTY: an enhanced BLAST-based search tool that integrates multiple biological information resources into sequence similarity search results</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">136</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Drubin;given-names:DG</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ayscough;given-names:KR</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Yang;given-names:S</infon><infon key="fpage">111</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9008707</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">123</infon><offset>61550</offset><text>A role for the actin cytoskeleton of Saccharomyces cerevisiaein bipolar bud-site selection</text></passage><passage><infon key="volume">108</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Melton;given-names:DA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sokol;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Yisraeli;given-names:JK</infon><infon key="fpage">289</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2351071</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><infon key="source">Development</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="lpage">298</infon><offset>61641</offset><text>A two-step model for the localization of maternal mRNA in Xenopusoocytes: involvment of microtubules and microfilaments in the translocation and anchoring of Vg-1 mRNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Boguta;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hunter;given-names:LA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Vaduva;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zoladek;given-names:T</infon><infon key="fpage">6884</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8524255</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="lpage">6894</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Hopper;given-names:AK</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Martin;given-names:NC</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Go;given-names:BD</infon><offset>61809</offset><text>Mutations altering the mitochondrial-cytoplasmic distribution of Mod5p implicate the actin cytoskeleton and mRNA 3' ends and/or protein synthesis in mitochondrial delivery</text></passage><passage><infon key="name_3">surname:Boguta;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Vaduva;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tobiasz;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Zoladek;given-names:T</infon><infon key="fpage">595</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9055070</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><infon key="source">Genetics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">145</infon><infon key="lpage">603</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Hopper;given-names:AK</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Martin;given-names:NC</infon><offset>61983</offset><text>MDP1, a Saccharomyces cerevisiae gene involved in mitochondrial/cytoplasmic protein distribution, is identical to the ubiquitin-protein ligase gene RSP5. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>62138</offset><text>Address all correspondence to Anita K. Hopper, Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, The Milton S. Hershey Medical Center,  The Pennsylvania State University, Hershey, Pennsylvania 17033. Tel.:  (717) 531-6008. Fax: (717) 531-7072.</text></passage></document></collection>