<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>ascii.key</key><document><id>2148169</id><passage><infon key="article-id_pmc">2148169</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">9700157</infon><infon key="fpage">665</infon><infon key="issue">3</infon><infon key="journal-title">The Journal of Cell Biology</infon><infon key="kwd">retrieval endosome Golgi vesicle coat</infon><infon key="lpage">681</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Seaman;given-names:Matthew N.J.</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Michael McCaffery;given-names:J.</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Emr;given-names:Scott D.</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">142</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>0</offset><text>A Membrane Coat Complex Essential for  Endosome-to-Golgi Retrograde Transport in Yeast </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>88</offset><text>We have recently characterized three yeast  gene products (Vps35p, Vps29p, and Vps30p) as candidate components of the sorting machinery required for  the endosome-to-Golgi retrieval of the vacuolar protein sorting receptor Vps10p (Seaman, M.N.J., E.G.  Marcusson, J.-L. Cereghino, and S.D. Emr. 1997. J. Cell  Biol. 137:79-92). By genetic and biochemical means we  now show that Vps35p and Vps29p interact and form  part of a multimeric membrane-associated complex  that also contains Vps26p, Vps17p, and Vps5p. This  complex, designated here as the retromer complex, assembles from two distinct subcomplexes comprising (a)  Vps35p, Vps29p, and Vps26p; and (b) Vps5p and  Vps17p. Density gradient fractionation of Golgi/endosomal/vesicular membranes reveals that Vps35p cofractionates with Vps5p/Vps17p in a vesicle-enriched dense  membrane fraction. Furthermore, gel filtration analysis  indicates that Vps35p and Vps5p are present on a population of vesicles and tubules slightly larger than  COPI/coatomer-coated vesicles. We also show by immunogold EM that Vps5p is localized to discrete regions at the rims of the prevacuolar endosome where  vesicles appear to be budding. Size fractionation of cytosolic and recombinant Vps5p reveals that Vps5p can  self-assemble in vitro, suggesting that Vps5p may provide the mechanical impetus to drive vesicle formation.  Based on these findings we propose a model in which  Vps35p/Vps29p/Vps26p function to select cargo for retrieval, and Vps5p/Vps17p assemble onto the membrane to promote vesicle formation. Conservation of  the yeast retromer complex components in higher eukaryotes suggests an important general role for this  complex in endosome-to-Golgi retrieval.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1805</offset><text>The subcellular organelles that comprise the secretory and endocytic pathways perform the essential  function of compartmentalizing often competing  biochemical reactions. Each organelle contains a discrete  set of resident proteins required for the proper functioning  of that compartment. Vesicular carriers provide the vehicles to transport proteins and lipids between organelles,  and thus are crucial for establishing and maintaining the  distinct complement of proteins that define each organelle  and determine its function (Rothman and Orci, 1992;  Rothman and Wieland, 1996). Vesicle formation is mediated by cytoplasmic coat proteins that are recruited onto  specific target membranes (Schekman and Orci, 1996).  Presently the favored model for vesicle-mediated membrane traffic predicts that coat proteins perform two distinct functions: (a) cargo recognition and concentration;  and (b) membrane deformation to generate a free vesicle.  The vesicle coat sequesters a subset of membrane proteins  by recognizing sorting determinants in the cytoplasmic  tails of membrane proteins that are transported in vesicles  (Kirchhausen et al., 1997). Finally, the vesicle coat must  assemble into a structure capable of deforming the donor  membrane into a small vesicle.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>3079</offset><text>A prime example of the role of vesicular carriers in organelle maintenance is the transport of hydrolases to the  lysosome. The lysosome is an acidic degradative organelle  that contains many hydrolases required for protein, lipid,  and carbohydrate turnover as well as downregulation of  activated cell surface receptors through proteolytic degradation (Kornfeld and Mellman, 1989). Biosynthetic transport of hydrolases to the lysosome occurs in a receptor-mediated fashion. Hydrolases that have been modified in  the Golgi complex by adding a mannose-6-phosphate moiety (M6P)1 are sorted away from proteins destined for secretion in the TGN by receptors that recognize M6P (Kornfeld, 1992). The ligand-receptor complexes are then  packaged into vesicles for delivery to an endosomal compartment (Hille-Rehfeld, 1995; Traub and Kornfeld,  1997). The acidic lumen of the endosome triggers release  of hydrolases that are subsequently delivered to the lysosome. To maintain the forward flow of hydrolases to the  lysosome, the M6P receptor must be efficiently recycled  back to the TGN and reused in additional rounds of hydrolase sorting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4220</offset><text>Sorting of the M6P receptor/ligand complexes into vesicles that bud from the TGN is believed to be mediated by  the clathrin/AP-1 vesicle coat. The heterotetrameric AP-1  complex binds to the cytoplasmic tail of the M6P receptor  via tyrosine-containing sequences (Glickman et al., 1989;  Le Borgne and Hoflack, 1997; Le Borgne et al., 1993;  Ohno et al., 1995). Clathrin then assembles onto the membrane-associated AP-1, and through its intrinsic self-assembly properties triggers formation of a budded vesicle  (Pearse and Robinson, 1990). Recycling the M6P receptor  from the endosome to the TGN is also believed to be vesicle-mediated, and has been shown to require the small  GTPase Rab9 (Riederer et al., 1994). However, the role of  Rab9 in this transport pathway is believed to be downstream of vesicle formation, and currently there are no  clear candidates for vesicle coat proteins acting in the retrieval of M6P receptors from the endosome to the Golgi.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>5186</offset><text>This process is mirrored in the simple eukaryote Saccharomyces cerevisiae. In S. cerevisiae the vacuole is analogous to the mammalian lysosome. Genetic screens in yeast  have identifed more than 40 genes whose products are required for efficient delivery of vacuolar hydrolases (Bankaitis et al., 1986; Robinson et al., 1988; Rothman and  Stevens, 1986). These genes have been termed VPS for  vacuolar protein sorting. and overlap partially with the  PEP mutants isolated by screening for reduced protease  activity (Jones, 1977). Phenotypic analysis of the vps mutants has classified the 40 or so complementation groups  into six distinct classes (A-F) based upon criteria such as  the morphological appearance of the vacuole and the severity of the defect in hydrolase sorting (Banta et al., 1988;  Raymond et al., 1992). Studies of the class A mutant vps10  revealed that the VPS10 gene encodes a type I transmembrane protein that functions as a sorting receptor for vacuolar hydrolases, including carboxypeptidase Y (CPY; Marcusson et al., 1994; Westphal et al., 1996). Vps10p normally  resides in a membrane fraction that also contains the late-Golgi enzyme Kex2p (Marcusson et al., 1994) and cycles  between the Golgi and a prevacuolar endosome where it  delivers CPY (and other hydrolases) before being recycled  back to the Golgi (Cereghino et al., 1995; Cooper and  Stevens, 1996). Clathrin has also been shown to be important for sorting Vps10p (Seeger and Payne, 1992a) in the  late-Golgi, and has been suggested to have a role both in  sorting to the vacuole and also retention of late-Golgi  membrane proteins such as the endopeptidase Kex2p  (Payne and Schekman, 1989; Seeger and Payne, 1992b;  Wilsbach and Payne, 1993b; Redding et al., 1996).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6947</offset><text>Recent detailed analysis of some of the class A (VPS29,  VPS30 and VPS35) and class B (VPS5 and VPS17) vps  mutants has shown that these genes are required for the  proper localization of the Vps10 protein (Horazdovsky et al.,  1997; Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997; Seaman et al., 1997).  Disruption of VPS29, VPS30, or VPS35 resulted in almost  complete mislocalization of the Vps10 receptor to the vacuole, causing CPY to be secreted from the cell. These gene  products are also required for the proper localization of  Kex2p and another Golgi-resident endopeptidase, dipeptidyl amino peptidase A (DPAP A; Seaman et al., 1997). As  the VPS29, VPS30, or VPS35 gene products were not required for Golgi-to-endosome transport, we proposed that  they may act in the retrieval/recycling of Vps10p from an  endosomal compartment to the late-Golgi (Seaman et al.,  1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7809</offset><text>VPS5 encodes a protein that is homologous to the mammalian SNX1 protein (Horazdovsky et al., 1997; Nothwehr  and Hindes, 1997). SNX1 is involved in the endocytic trafficking of the epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR),  and was shown to interact with the tail of the EGFR  (Kurten et al., 1996). An epitope-tagged Vps5p has been  localized by immunofluorescence to an endosomal compartment (Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997), and the wild-type  protein cofractionated with a dense pool of membranes  (with a buoyant density similar to that of known coated  vesicles) on Accudenz density gradients (Accurate Chemical  &amp; Scientific Corp., Westbury, NY; Horazdovsky et al., 1997).  Vps5p and Vps17p form a stable complex, and have phenotypes indistinguishable from each other (Horazdovsky et al.,  1997; Kohrer and Emr, 1993). In a vps5 mutant, greater than  50% of the Vps10p is mislocalized to a membrane fraction  enriched in vacuolar markers (Horazdovsky et al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8776</offset><text>Significantly, however, there are major differences between the phenotypes of the class A (vps29, 30 and 35)  mutants and the class B (vps5 and 17) mutants (Banta et al.,  1988; Raymond et al., 1992). First, in class B mutants the  vacuole is fragmented into 10-20 smaller vacuoles, while  class A mutants retain a vacuole with near wild-type morphology (Raymond et al., 1992). Class B mutants also exhibit a more severe defect in trafficking to the vacuole  (Horazdovsky et al., 1997; Kohrer and Emr, 1993; Marcusson et al., 1994; Paravicini et al., 1992; Seaman, et al.,  1997). Hence, while the class A mutants have been proposed specifically to affect retrieval of a subset of membrane proteins such as Vps10p from the endosome to the  Golgi, the class B genes have been proposed to act in a  more general fashion such that when mutated, all endosome-to-Golgi recycling is abolished. This strong retrograde defect presumably also leads to a Golgi-to-endosome anterograde defect due to a lack of recycling of  factors essential for forward transport. Thus, less Vps10p  is mislocalized to the vacuole in a vps5 mutant than is observed for the class A vps29, vps30, and vps35 mutants.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9965</offset><text>Two other potential factors required for endosome to  Golgi transport in yeast are the products of the VPS1 and  VPS26 genes. vps1 and vps26 mutants are both classified  as class F mutants with phenotypes intermediate to those  of the class A and class B vps mutants (Raymond et al.,  1992). VPS1 encodes a high molecular weight GTPase that  belongs to the dynamin family (Nothwehr et al., 1995;  Rothman et al., 1990). VPS1 function is required for the  proper sorting of CPY to the vacuole (Nothwehr et al.,  1995; Rothman et al., 1990; Vater et al., 1992), and is also  important for the correct localization of Kex2p (Wilsbach  and Payne, 1993a; Nothwehr et al., 1995). By analogy to  the established role of dynamin in the budding of clathrin-coated vesicles from the plasma membrane (Damke, 1996;  Takei et al., 1996; Warnock and Schmid, 1996), it has been  proposed that Vps1p acts with clathrin to sort CPY at the  Golgi and possibly to maintain Kex2p in the late-Golgi  (Wilsbach and Payne, 1993b). VPS26 is allelic to the PEP8  gene, and is also required for correct sorting of CPY to the  vacuole (Bachhawat et al., 1994). Phenotypically, vps26  mutants are very similar to vps1 mutants, and thus it has  been proposed that the two proteins function at the same  point (Raymond et al., 1992). A recent screen undertaken  specifically to identify mutants that fail to retain DPAP A  in the late-Golgi resulted in the isolation of several mutants, many of which are allelic to the VPS genes described  above (Nothwehr et al., 1996). For instance, the Golgi retention-defective (grd) mutant grd2 is allelic to vps5. grd9  is allelic to vps35, grd6 is allelic to vps26, and grd1 is allelic  to vps1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11674</offset><text>Here we show that Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps26p, Vps5p,  and Vps17p associate with each other forming a multimeric complex, on vesicular and tubulovesicular membranes. The complex, which we call the retromer complex,  appears to assemble onto the membrane from two distinct  subcomplexes comprising (a) Vps35p, Vps29p, and Vps26p;  and (b) Vps5p and Vps17p. Vps35p and Vps5p colocalize  on sucrose density gradients in fractions with a density  greater than Golgi and endosomal fractions. They are also  found associated together on a population of vesicular  membranes that separate away from Golgi membranes by  gel filtration chromatography. Immunogold EM revealed  that Vps5p is found in clusters on a prevacuolar endosome  at sites where vesicles appear to be budding from the  membrane. Both cytosolic and recombinant Vps5p can  also assemble into a large complex, suggesting that it may  have intrinsic self-assembly activity. In addition we have  found that Vps35p assembles into a high molecular weight  complex in the cytosol, and this assembly is dependent  upon Vps29p. The phenotypic and biochemical data taken  together suggest that these proteins function as a vesicle  coat that directs the retrieval of the Vps10 receptor as well  as other proteins from the endosome to the Golgi.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>12965</offset><text>Materials and Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>12987</offset><text>Reagents, Media, Yeast, and Bacterial Manipulations</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13039</offset><text>Unless otherwise stated, reagents were obtained from Boehringer Mannheim Corp. (Indianapolis, IN), Fisher Scientific Co. (Fairlawn, NJ), or  from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO). All yeast strains were grown in  yeast extract, peptone, dextrose medium (YPD), or yeast nitrogen base  medium (YNB; Sherman et al., 1979). Yeast transformations were performed using alkali cation treatment (Elble, 1992), and Escherichia coli  transformations were performed according to Hanahan (1983). Yeast  strains used in this study are listed in Table I. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13583</offset><text>Western Blotting</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13600</offset><text>Samples solubilized in SDS-PAGE buffer (6 M urea, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH  6.8, 1% SDS) were loaded and electrophoresed (constant current of 20 mA  per gel) on either 8% or 10% polyacrylamide gels. After electrophoresis,  the gel was briefly immersed in transfer buffer (5% methanol, 50 mM Tris,  380 mM glycine) and then placed flat against a sheet of nitrocellulose  (Schleicher &amp; Schuell, Inc., Keene, NH) and assembled into an apparatus  (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) for electrophoretic transfer of the  proteins onto the nitrocellulose. Transfer was accomplished at constant  current (150 mA) for 10-12 h. The blot was then blocked with blocking  buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA, 0.25% gelatin, 0.1% Nonidet P40, 0.1% sodium azide) for an hour before incubation  with antibodies. Most antiserum was used at a dilution of 1:1,000. Antibody incubations were generally for 2 h at room temperature on a rocking  table. Washes were for 30-60 min with several changes of blocking buffer.  [125I]protein A (Amersham Corp., Arlington Heights, IL) was used to detect the first antibodies, and this was used at a dilution of 1:1,000. After  further blocking, the blots was exposed to x-ray film (Eastman Kodak Co.,  Rochester, NY).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>14857</offset><text>CPY Sorting Assays and Subcellular Fractionation Procedures</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14917</offset><text>CPY sorting was performed as described previously in Seaman et al.  (1997). Similarly, cell fractionation experiments using differential centrifugation to separate P100 membranes from P13 membranes and cytosol  (S100) were performed essentially as described previously in Seaman et al.  (1997). Sucrose density gradient fractionation of P100 membranes was  performed as in Seaman et al. (1997) with the exception that a P100 membrane fraction was loaded onto the gradient instead of a supernatant from  a 13,000 g spin. The P100 generated for this experiment was from the lysis  of ~15 ODs of cells, and was resuspended in 0.5 ml of lysis buffer and  briefly dounced in a 1-ml dounce homogenizer before loading onto the sucrose density gradient.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15665</offset><text>Fractionation of P100 membranes by sephacryl S1000 column chromatography was performed as follows. Cells grown in YPD media were harvested at an OD of 2-3 (generally 6,000-7,000 ODs of cells were used).  The cells were spun down using an RC5B centrifuge (Sorvall, Newtown,  CT) in a GS3 rotor (10 min at 5,000 rpm). The cell pellet was washed with  water and spun again. The cells were then resuspended into 500 ml of  spheroplasting buffer (0.8 M sorbitol, 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 10 mM  CaCl2, 2 mM DTT, and 10 mug/OD zymolyase) and incubated at 30 C with  gentle shaking (90 rpm). Spheroplasting was monitored by measuring the  OD 600 nm of an aliquot of cells placed in 1 ml of water. When spheroplasting was 80-90% complete (~60 min), the cells were spun out again  (this time in a GSA rotor) for 10 min at 4 C and 1,500 rpm. The cell pellet  was washed with wash buffer (0.8 M sorbitol, 20 mM Hepes-KOH, pH 7.0,  50 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM EDTA) and then pelleted again as before. The cells were then lysed in chilled lysis buffer (0.2 M sorbitol, 20 mM  Hepes-KOH pH 7.0, 50 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM EDTA) plus protease inhibitors (PMSF, 100mug/ml, pepstatin 1 mug/ml, leupeptin 1 mug/ml,  antipain 5 mug/ml and alpha2-macroglobulin 10 mug/ml) with the aid of a 15-ml  dounce homogenizer (~15 strokes). The lysate was spun at 13,000 g for 10  min in a Sorval SS34 rotor (10,500 rpm) at 4 C. The resulting supernatant  was centrifuged for 1 h at 100,000 g in a 60 ti rotor (32,000 rpm; Beckman  Instruments, Inc., Fullerton, CA) at 4 C. The resulting P100 pellet was resuspended in ~1.5 ml of lysis buffer with the aid of a 1-ml dounce homogenizer, was briefly spun at 13,000 g to pellet any aggregated material, and  was then loaded onto a sephacryl S1000 (Pharmacia, Piscataway, NJ) column (118 cm x 1.5 cm) that had been equilibrated with lysis buffer. The  column was run at 4 C, the samples were eluted using a flow rate of ~250  mul per min, and 2.5-ml fractions were collected. Fractions were analyzed  for various proteins by Western blotting, and were also analyzed by EM.  To strip the P100 membranes, lysis buffer containing 250 mM NaCl was  used to resuspend the membranes after the 100,000-g spin. The membranes were dounced in a 1-ml dounce as described previously, and were  then centrifuged again at 100,000 g to pellet the stripped membranes. The  supernatant was then fractionated on the sephacryl S300 column as described below. Alternatively, the supernatant was dialyzed against  ~1-liter lysis buffer (0.2 M sorbitol, 20 mM Hepes-KOH, pH 7.0, 50 mM  potassium acetate, 2 mM EDTA) overnight at 4 C. After dialysis, the supernatant was spun briefly at 13,000 g, and was then fractionated on a  sephacryl S300 column.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18433</offset><text>Cross-linking of Membrane Fractions or Yeast Lysates</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18486</offset><text>Cells grown in YNB media were first spheroplasted and then labeled for  15 min with [35S]methionine/cysteine. Excess cold methionine and cysteine were added, and the cells were chased for 45 min. The cells were  then spun out and resuspended in lysis buffer (20 mM Hepes-KOH, pH  7.0, 50 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM EDTA, 0.2 M sorbitol) at ~7 ODs/ml.  A lysate was produced by douncing the cells in a dounce homogenizer using 15 strokes of the pestle. The lysate was then transferred to eppendorf  tubes and spun at 300 g for 5 min at 4 C to remove unbroken cells and  large organelles such as nuclei. In some cases the resulting cleared lysate  was then treated with the cross-linker 3,3'-dithiobis sulfosuccinimidyl-proprionate (DTSSP; Pierce Chemical Co., Rockford, IL), which was  added to a final concentration of 2 mM. In other experiments, the cleared  lysate was first spun at 13,000 g for 5 min at 4 C to remove vacuolar membranes, mitochondria, plasma membranes, and endoplasmic reticulum.  The supernatant from this spin was centrifuged further by spinning at  100,000 g for 1 h to generate a P100. This supernatant was then resuspended into 100 mul of lysis buffer with the aid of a plastic pestle, and cross-linker was added to a final concentration of 2 mM. Cross-linking was allowed to proceed for 30 min at room temperature. The reaction was  stopped by adding TCA to a final concentration of 10%, and the tubes  were placed on ice for 20 min to allow the proteins to precipitate. The precipitated proteins were pelleted by centrifugation at 13,000 g for 5 min,  and were then washed twice with ice-cold acetone to remove the TCA. The  samples were lyophilized and then resuspended into 100 mul of urea buffer  (6 M urea, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 1 mM EDTA, 1% SDS). Protein pellets were resuspended with the aid of a sonicating waterbath. 1 ml of immunoprecipitation buffer was added (25 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM  NaCl, 0.5% Tween-20, 0.1 mM EDTA), the samples were spun for 10 min  at 13,000 g to remove insoluble debris, and then antisera was added. Immunoprecipitations were carried out as described previously (Seaman et  al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>20649</offset><text>Fractionation of Yeast Cytosol</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20680</offset><text>Yeast cells grown in YPD media were harvested at an OD 600 nm of ~1.0.  Approximately 200 ODs of cells were spun down in a bench-top clinical  centrifuge. The pellet was washed with water and then resuspended in 50  ml of spheroplasting buffer (0.8 M sorbitol, 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 10 mM  CaCl2). DTT and zymolyase (Seikagaku, Tokyo, Japan) were added to final concentrations of 2 mM and 10 mug/OD, respectively. Spheroplasting  was monitored by observing the drop in OD 600 nm when an aliquot of  the spheroplasting cells was placed in water. When spheroplasting was 80- 90% complete, the cells were spun out as before and washed with chilled  wash buffer (0.8 M sorbitol, 20 mM Hepes-KOH, pH 7.0, 50 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM EDTA). After recovering the cells by centrifugation,  the cells were resuspended into lysis buffer at ~100 ODs per ml. The cells  were lysed with the aid of a dounce homogenizer. The lysate was spun at  13,000 g at 4 C to remove unbroken cells and larger membranes. The supernatant was then spun for 1 h at 4 C and 100,000 g to pellet the remaining membranes. 1 ml of the supernatant (yeast cytosol) was loaded onto a  sephacryl S300 (Pharmacia Biotech, Inc., Piscataway, NJ) column that had  been equilibrated with lysis buffer, and was then fractionated with a flow  rate of 0.4 ml per min using lysis buffer to elute the proteins. 1.25-ml fractions were collected after an initial wait period of 80 min. The fractions  were precipitated with 10% TCA, and the pellets were washed with acetone to remove the TCA as described before. The proteins were resuspended into 100 mul of urea sample buffer (6 M urea, 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH  6.8, 1% SDS, 5% beta-mercaptoethanol, 0.1% bromophenol blue). 30 mul of  the sample was loaded per lane onto an 8% SDS polyacrylamide gel. After electrophoresis, the proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose for  Western blotting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>22581</offset><text>Plasmid Construction, Generation of the vps35dn  Allele, and Cloning and Disruption of VPS26</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22674</offset><text>Standard molecular biology techniques and protocols for DNA manipulation were used throughout this study (Sambrook et al., 1989). To generate  an antisera against Vps29p, a glutathione S-transferase (GST) fusion  (Smith and Johnson, 1988) with Vps29p was created. Using an oligonucleotide primer incorporating a BamH1 site at the 5' end and a primer corresponding to the T3 promoter, the region of VPS29 downstream of the intron (Seaman et al., 1997) was amplified by PCR from pVPS29 -1(Seaman  et al., 1997). The ~1.6-kb fragment was cloned using the TA cloning vector according to manufacturer's instructions (Invitrogen Corp., Carlsbad,  CA). The fragment was excised by BamH1 digestion, and was subcloned  into pGEX 3X (Smith and Johnson, 1988) that had been digested with  BamH1 to generate pGST-VPS29. E. coli transformed with pGST-VPS29  was grown in liquid culture and induced to express by adding isopropyl  beta-d-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) to a final concentration of 0.1 mM. The  protein produced was isolated by glutathione affinity chromatography  (Smith and Johnson, 1988) and by following the manufacturer's instructions, and on SDS gels was found to migrate as a protein with an apparent  size of ~120 kD on SDS polyacrylamide gels. This was much larger than  the predicted size of the fusion (~50 kD), and may have been due to the  very acidic nature of the Vps29 protein, which has a pI of ~4.3. Purified  fusion protein was used to immunize New Zealand white rabbits following  a standard immunization protocol (Harlow and Lane, 1988). After four  boosts, the animal was bled out, and 5 ml of antisera was affinity-purified  on GST-Vps29p that had been coupled to CNBr activated sepharose  (Pharmacia Biotech., Inc.) following the manufacturer's instructions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24464</offset><text>The vps35dn allele was generated and screened for in an identical manner to the vps35ts allele (Seaman et al., 1997) with the exception that the  gapped plasmid was a multicopy plasmid (pRS424) containing VPS35.  VPS26 was cloned by amplifying the gene using PCR and genomic DNA  as template. The primers used for the PCR reaction were designed to  flank the open reading frame, annealing ~200 bp on either side of the  VPS26 gene. A single product of ~1.7 kb was obtained from the PCR, and  was cloned using the TA cloning kit to create pTA26. VPS26 was then  subcloned into Not1, and Kpn1 digested pRS414 and pRS416 after excising VPS26 from pTA26 by Not1 and Kpn1 digestion. The resulting plasmids (pVPS26-414 and pVPS26-416) were transformed into SEY26-1, a  yeast strain carrying a mutation in VPS26. Both plasmids were able to  compliment the CPY sorting defect in SEY26-1 (data not shown). A deletion of VPS26 was generated by removing ~80% of the coding region of  VPS26 by digesting pVPS26-416 with HindIII and Xba1. A HindIII-XbaI  fragment containing the LEU2 gene excised from pBlueScript (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA) containing LEU2 was then subcloned into the cut  pVPS26-416 and ligated. The resulting plasmid pVPS26-LEU2 was used  as a template to amplify the disrupted gene by PCR. The same primers  were used as before. The PCR product was used to transform wild-type  yeast (SEY6210). Transformants were selected by growth on -leu plates.  Deletion of the gene was confirmed by PCR on genomic DNA prepared  from leu+ transformants. Transformation of the vps26Delta strain  (MSY2600) with pVPS26-414 or pVPS26-416 was able to compliment the  CPY sorting defect observed in strain MSY2600 (data not shown). An  epitope-tagged version of VPS26 that compliments a vps26 mutant has  been reported previously (Bachhawat et al., 1994), and was a gift from E.  Jones (Carnegie-Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA). However, it was necessary to subclone a HindIII fragment from the integrating plasmid  p8HA22 (Bachhawat et al., 1994) into HindIII-cut pVPS26-416 to generate an expression plasmid for the hemagglutinin (HA)-tagged VPS26.  This subcloning created pVPS26-HA, which was transformed into  MSY2600 and was found to compliment the CPY sorting defect fully.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26743</offset><text>A yeast strain with a myc-tagged VPS10 gene integrated into the genome was generated in the following way. The plasmid containing VPS10-myc, pEMY10-21 (Cereghino et al., 1995), was cut with BglII to excise the  VPS10-myc construct. The linear DNA was gel-purified, and was used to  transform the strain EMY3 (vps10Delta::HIS3; Marcusson et al., 1994) along  with pCYI50 (Bankaitis et al., 1986) that encodes a CPY-Invertase fusion.  Transformants were selected for growth on -ura plates. Replicas were  screened for the ability to sort CPY-Invertase to the vacuole using a plate  assay (Paravicini et al., 1992). Cells in which the VPS10-myc had integrated into the genome scored as white colonies capable of sorting CPY-Invertase to the vacuole. Four independent colonies were found to be  VPS+. These colonies also contained the VPS10-myc gene as determined  by the presence of the ~200-kD band in immunoprecipitates from 35S- labeled cells using the anti-myc antibody 9E10 (data not shown). Three of  the four were also found to now be his-, indicating that the VPS10-myc  gene had integrated into the vps10::HIS3 locus, displacing the HIS3 gene  in the process. One of the his- VPS+ colonies was designated MSY10-21,  and was used in these studies.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27999</offset><text>To generate significant amounts of Vps5p in bacteria for in vitro studies, a GST-VPS5 fusion was generated. This was achieved by subcloning  an Xba1-Xho1 fragment of VPS5 into Xba1-Xho1 digested pGEX KG  (Pharmacia Biotech., Inc.). The resulting plasmid was termed pGST-VPS5. Digestion at the Xba1 site in Vps5p resulted in the loss of six amino  terminal residues of Vps5p and Xho1 cut downstream of the coding region. This procedure formed an in-frame fusion of VPS5 with GST, which  expressed almost full-length VPS5. An identical fusion was made between  VPS5 and GST in pEG KT, a GST expression system for yeast (Mitchell  et al., 1993). This plasmid was designated pMSGST-5, and when expressed in  vps5Delta, cells were able to compliment the CPY sorting defect fully (data not  shown). Bacteria harboring pGST-VPS5 were induced to express by adding IPTG. The fusion protein was soluble, although poorly expressed. A  protein of ~120 kD was observed on SDS polyacrylamide gels, which corresponded to the full-length fusion. Some proteolysis of the GST-Vps5p  occurred in the bacteria, resulting in breakdown products ranging in size  from 60 to 30 kD. GST-Vps5p that had been eluted from the glutathione-sepharose was dialyzed against ~1 liter of lysis buffer (0.2 M sorbitol, 20  mM Hepes-KOH, pH 7.0, 50 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM EDTA) overnight at 4 C. This buffer was loaded onto the sephacryl S300 column and  fractionated in a manner identical to that for yeast cytosol.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>29485</offset><text>Affinity Isolation of GST-Vps5p from Yeast Lysates</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29536</offset><text>Wild-type and vps5Delta cells harboring a plasmid to express GST-Vps5p in  yeast (pMSGST-5) were grown in -ura, -leu minimal media to an OD 600 nm  of ~1 ODU/mL. 1,000 OD 600-nm equivalents of cells were harvested and  converted to spheroplasts by zymolyase digestion. The spheroplasted cells  were lysed at 100 OD 600-nm equivalents per ml in lysis buffer (0.2 M sorbitol, 20 mM Hepes-KOH, pH 7.0, 50 mM potassium acetate, 2 mM  EDTA) containing 0.5% triton with the aid of a dounce homogenizer. The  lysate was spun at 20,000 g in a sorvall SS34 rotor for 10 min at 4 C to remove insoluble material. The supernatant was collected and incubated  with 150 mul of glutathione sepharose slurry for 15 min at room temperature on a rocking table. After several washes of the sepharose with 10-ml  aliquots of lysis buffer, the bound proteins were eluted using 10 mM of reduced glutathione in 50 mM Tris, pH 8.0. The proteins were precipitated  by adding TCA to 10%, and after acetone washes were resuspended into  SDS-PAGE sample buffer.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>30570</offset><text>Electron Microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30590</offset><text>EM on frozen yeast cells or frozen P100 membrane fractions to localize  Vps5p was performed essentially as described previously (Rieder et al.,  1996; McCaffery and Farquhar, 1995). vps4 cells (SEY 4-1) transformed  with the plasmid pAH31 to express an HA-tagged Vps5p (Nothwehr and  Hindes, 1997) were grown to midlog (~OD 600 nm 0.6) before being spun  down and fixed for 18-24 h in 3% formaldehyde dissolved in PBS, pH 7.4.  The cells were then dispersed in 1% agarose, which was trimmed into  mm3 blocks and then cryoprotected in 2.3 M sucrose containing 25% polyvinylpyrollidone (10,000 D) and frozen onto cryopins in liquid nitrogen.  Ultrathin cryosections were cut on a Reichert Ultracut E (Leica, Deerfield, IL) equipped with an FC4 cryostage, and were collected onto 300 mesh,  formvar/carbon-coated grids and immunolabeled as described previously  (Reider et al., 1996). Sections were adsorption stained/embedded with 3.2%  polyvinyl alcohol, 0.2% methyl cellulose (400 centiposes), and 0.1% uranyl  acetate contained in H2O. Monoclonal anti-HA antibodies (Berkeley Antibody Co., Inc., Richmond, CA) were used to label the HA-tagged Vps5p,  and these were visualized using anti-mouse coupled to 5 nm colloidal-gold.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>31821</offset><text>For size-fractionated Vps5p complexes, the complexes were adsorbed to  300 mesh, formvar/carbon-coated grids (freshly ionized) fixed for 10 min in  3% formaldehyde dissolved in PBS, pH 7.4, and were subsequently immunolabeled (or not) as described previously (McCaffery and Farquhar, 1995). The  complexes were then negatively stained in 2% uranyl acetate and observed  on a JEOL 1200 EX II TEM in paraformaldehyde as in Rieder et al. (1996).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>32264</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>32272</offset><text>Vps35p and Vps29p Interact</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32299</offset><text>Previous studies have identified several genes whose products are required for the correct trafficking of the vacuolar  hydrolase receptor, Vps10p. Strains carrying mutations in  the VPS35, VPS29, or VPS30 genes have phenotypes that  are virtually indistinguishable, and cause Vps10p to become mislocalized to the vacuolar membrane (Seaman et al.,  1997). Detailed analysis of the vps35 mutant strongly suggested that a defect in the retrieval of Vps10p from the  prevacuolar endosome to the late-Golgi was responsible  for the vacuolar protein-sorting defect (Seaman et al.,  1997). The very similar phenotypes of the vps35, vps29,  and vps30 mutants suggested that the gene products may  all function at a common step in the retrieval pathway. To  test this directly and to gain a better understanding of the  roles that the VPS35, VPS29, and VPS30 genes play in the  retrieval of Vps10p, a dominant negative mutant of VPS35  (vps35dn) was generated. When introduced at high copy  number into wild-type cells, this allele caused a significant  defect in the trafficking of CPY to the vacuole, resulting in  50% of the CPY being secreted from the cell as the Golgi-modified p2 precursor form (Fig. 1 A, lanes 1 and 2). Effects of dominant negative alleles are often due to titration  of other factors by the dominant negative protein. Candidates for these other factors in this case would clearly include Vps29p and/or Vps30p. Therefore, the strain carrying the vps35dn allele was transformed with high-copy  plasmids to overexpress either the VPS29, VPS30, or  VPS35 gene products. Only cells overexpressing VPS29  were able to suppress the CPY sorting defect caused by  the vps35dn allele (Fig. 1 A, lanes 3 and 4). These data  suggest an interaction between Vps35p and Vps29p. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34081</offset><text>To address whether this genetic interaction corresponded  to a physical interaction between Vps35p and Vps29p, we  first investigated the subcellular localization of Vps29p. If  Vps35p and Vps29p physically interact, then it is logical to  expect the proteins to colocalize. To investigate the subcellular localization of Vps29p, a polyclonal antiserum was  raised against a recombinant GST-Vps29p fusion protein  (Materials and Methods). This antiserum recognized a protein with an apparent molecular mass of 45 that was absent  in immunoprecipitations from vps29Delta cells, and was greatly  elevated in cells containing a multicopy VPS29 plasmid  (Fig. 1 B and data not shown). The apparent molecular  mass of Vps29p is significantly larger than its predicted molecular mass of ~30. This discrepancy may be due to some  form of posttranslational modification, or could be caused  by the acidic nature of Vps29p, which has a pI of ~4.3.  Some cross-reactivity of the antiserum with a protein(s)  slightly larger than Vps29p was observed, and is seen in  Fig. 1 B, panel 2 when a lysate from vps29Delta cells was  treated with the Vps29p antiserum. When the subcellular  distribution of Vps29p was investigated (Fig. 1 B, panel 1)  it was found to be a predominantly soluble protein, but  ~20% of Vps29p was associated with the 100,000 g particulate fraction (P100) that contains Vps35p (Paravicini et al.,  1992) and the Golgi membrane proteins Kex2p and  Vps10p (Marcusson et al., 1994). No Vps29p was detected  in the P13 fraction that contains vacuolar membranes, ER,  mitochondria, and plasma membranes (Marcusson et al.,  1994). Deletion of VPS35 resulted in Vps29p becoming  completely soluble (Fig. 1 B, panel 4), demonstrating that  Vps35p is required for membrane association of Vps29p. In  contrast, there was no change in the localization of Vps29p  in cells in which VPS30 was deleted (Fig. 1 B, panel 3).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>36001</offset><text>Vps35p and Vps29p Form a Multimeric Complex with  Vps5p and Vps17p</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36068</offset><text>To investigate further the potential association of Vps35p  with Vps29p, and to identify any other proteins that may  interact with the Vps35p/Vps29p complex, a series of  cross-linking experiments was undertaken. Lysates from  wild-type cells that had been cleared of unbroken cells  were treated with the homobifunctional reducible cross-linker DTSSP. The reaction was stopped by adding TCA  to precipitate the proteins, and then the sample was denatured in a buffer containing SDS and urea to break noncovalent interactions. Vps35p or Vps29p was immunoprecipitated from resulting lysates under nonreducing conditions.  As seen in Fig. 2 A, when no cross-linker is added, the antisera against Vps35p only immunoprecipitated Vps35p  (lane 1). Similarly, the Vps29p antisera predominately recognized Vps29p (lane 2). When cross-linker was added  and either Vps35p (lane 3) or Vps29p (lane 4) was immunoprecipitated, a number of other proteins were detected.  Vps29p cross-linked to a protein with identical mobility to  Vps35p, and both Vps29p and Vps35p cross-linked to  three other proteins:p95, p70, and p50:based upon  their respective migrations on the SDS polyacrylamide gel.  A faint band corresponding to Vps29p was also present  in the Vps35p immunoprecipitates. The relatively low  Vps29p signal in the Vps35p immunoprecipitates is due to  two factors: first, the cross-linking reaction is not completely efficient, which means that not all Vps29p associated with Vps35p will be cross-linked; and second, Vps29p  is a small protein with relatively few methionines and cysteines, and hence will not give a strong signal compared  with larger proteins, such as Vps35p. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37750</offset><text>The interaction between Vps35p and Vps29p indeed  was confirmed in an experiment in which an enriched  source of Vps35p was used as a source of material for  cross-linking. 80% of the total Vps35p is present in an endosome/Golgi/vesicle-enriched fraction that sediments at  100,000 g (P100). Therefore, P100 membranes isolated by  centrifugation from [35S]methionine-labeled wild-type cells  were resuspended in lysis buffer and then treated with  cross-linker. Vps35p or Vps29p was immunoprecipitated  from the lysate using specific antisera. In the presence of  cross-linker (Fig. 2 B, lane 1), Vps35p coimmunoprecipitates with Vps29p and the three other proteins: p95, p70,  and p50. The identity of Vps29p was confirmed by treating  cross-linked immunoprecipitated Vps35p with reducing  agent to break the cross-linker. Vps29p is then immunoprecipitated from the resulting lysate (lane 2). In lane 3,  antibodies against Vps29p immunoprecipitated both  Vps29p and Vps35p, along with the three other proteins  that coimmunoprecipitate with Vps35p (compare lanes 1  and 3). The association of Vps29p with Vps35p was cross-linker-dependent; when no cross-linker was added to the  P100 membranes, Vps29p did not coimmunoprecipitate  with Vps35p (lane 4). As a control for efficient cross-linking, Vps5p was immunoprecipitated from the extracts used  for lane 1 (lane 5). Vps5p has been shown previously to be  stably associated with Vps17p (Horazdovsky et al., 1997),  and hence this interaction was deemed to be a suitable positive control for cross-linking. It was noticed that Vps5p and  Vps17p exhibited mobilities very similar if not identical to  two of the proteins (p95 and p70) that coimmunoprecipitated with Vps35p and Vps29p. Therefore, to test directly  the possibility that Vps5p and Vps17p are interacting with  Vps35p/Vps29p, P100 membranes were cross-linked as before, and Vps35p was immunoprecipitated from the resulting lysates. After treating the immunoprecipitates with reducing agent to break the cross-linker, antibodies against  Vps30p, Vps5p, or Vps17p were added. It was not possible  to detect Vps30p after reducing the Vps35p immunoprecipitate (lane 6); however, antiserum against Vps5p did  immunoprecipitate a protein with the mobility of Vps5p  from the reduced lysate (lane 7), and Vps17p could also be  detected, although to a lesser extent (data not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40143</offset><text>Previously published data have demonstrated that the  P100 membrane-associated Vps35p can be floated out of  60% sucrose using a simple two-step sucrose gradient  (Paravicini et al., 1992). Vps5p has been found to behave  in a similar fashion (Horazdovsky et al., 1997) and therefore the cross-linked complex described here is unlikely to  represent a very large sedimentable particle, but rather a  peripheral membrane-associated complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40585</offset><text>As an independent test of the interactions discovered  through the use of cross-linkers, a fusion protein between  GST and Vps5p was expressed in yeast, and was used to  confirm the presence of the multimeric complex containing Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps17p, and Vps5p. The GST-Vps5p  was functional, as expression in a vps5Delta strain was able to  complement the CPY sorting defect fully (data not  shown). GST-Vps5p isolated from either wild-type (data  not shown) or vps5Delta (Fig. 2 C) yeast lysates using glutathione-sepharose was found to be bound to Vps17p,  Vps35p, and Vps29p (Fig. 2 C, lane 2), but none of these  proteins was detected when a control lysate from a strain  expressing just GST was treated with glutathione-sepharose (Fig. 2 C, lane 1).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>41336</offset><text>Vps26p is the p50 Component of the Multimeric Complex</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>41390</offset><text>To identify the p50 component of the multimeric complex,  a database search of the cloned VPS and PEP genes was  performed to identify candidate 50-kD proteins. The best  candidate was VPS26/PEP8. This gene encodes an ~40-kD  protein that migrates on SDS gels with a molecular mass  of ~50 (Bachhawat et al., 1994). The phenotype of vps26  mutants is intermediate between that of the class A mutants (vps35, vps29, and vps30) and the class B mutants  (vps5 and vps17) (Raymond et al., 1992). Therefore, a  strain in which VPS26 was deleted was generated as described in Materials and Methods, and was used in a cross-linking experiment to determine if Vps26p is p50. In Fig. 3  A, lysates were treated with cross-linker as before, and  Vps35p was immunoprecipitated. When no cross-linker  was added, only Vps35p was present (lane 1), while in lane  2, cross-linker was added to a lysate, and the pattern of  bands contained Vps5p, Vps17p, p50, and Vps29p. However, when an identical experiment was performed using  lysate from cells in which VPS26 was deleted, the p50 band  was missing (compare lanes 2 and 3). It is interesting to  note that Vps35p continues to coimmunoprecipitate with  Vps5p, Vps17p, and Vps29p, suggesting that Vps26p is not  essential for formation of the complex. More recently,  cross-linking experiments using a strain expressing an  epitope-tagged Vps26p have confirmed that Vps26p does  indeed interact with Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps5p, and Vps17p  in a large complex (data not shown). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>42903</offset><text>Assembly of the Multimeric Complex Requires both  Vps29p and Vps35p</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>42971</offset><text>To address the question of which components of the complex are essential for forming the Vps35p/Vps29p/Vps26p/ Vps5p/Vps17p complex, lysates from various [35S]methionine-labeled yeast strains were treated with cross-linker,  and either Vps35p or Vps29p was immunoprecipitated. Because the localization of the proteins is affected in the various strains tested (e.g., Vps35p is localized to the P13, vacuole-enriched fraction in a vps29Delta strain), a crude lysate  cleared of unbroken cells was used for these cross-linking  experiments. When lysates from wild-type cells treated  with cross-linker were immunoprecipitated with antibodies  against Vps35p and Vps29p (Fig. 3 B, lanes 1 and 2, respectively), the same pattern of bands was observed as seen in  Fig. 2 A. When a lysate of the vps35Delta strain was cross-linked and Vps29p was immunoprecipitated, Vps29p was  not cross-linked to Vps5p/Vps17p (Fig. 3 B, lane 3). Similarly, when the lysate from a vps29Delta strain was cross-linked  and Vps35p was immunoprecipitated, Vps35p no longer  cross-linked to Vps5p/Vps17p or Vps26p (Fig. 3 B, lane 6).  In contrast, however, deletion of VPS30 (Fig. 3 B, lanes 4  and 5) had no effect upon the ability of the complex to assemble. Deletion of either VPS17 (Fig. 3 B, lanes 7 and 8)  or VPS5 (Fig. 3 B, lane 9) results in the loss of the interaction between Vps35p and Vps5p/Vps17p (Fig. 3 B, lanes 7  and 9). Likewise, Vps29p no longer interacts with Vps5p/ Vps17p (Fig. 3 B, lane 8). Interestingly, it appears that the  interaction between Vps35p and Vps29p is unaffected in  either the vps17 or vps5 mutants (Fig. 3 B, lanes 7-9), and  Vps35p/Vps29p can still interact with Vps26p. These results hint at the possibility that two distinct subcomplexes  assemble together to form a multimeric complex. These  two subcomplexes appear to comprise a Vps35p/Vps29p/ Vps26p complex and a Vps5p/Vps17p complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>44872</offset><text>Vps26p is Required for Correct Localization of Vps10p</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44926</offset><text>VPS26/PEP8 has been shown previously to be important  for sorting CPY to the vacuole (Bachhawat et al., 1994).  The data presented here suggested that Vps26p is part of a  multimeric membrane-associated complex that also contains Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps5p, and Vps17p. If Vps26p is indeed interacting with Vps35p/Vps29p and/or Vps5p/Vps17p,  then it is reasonable to expect a vps26 mutant to have a similar phenotype(s) to either a vps35 or vps5 mutant. Therefore, cell fractionation experiments were performed in which  localization of Vps10p was investigated in both wild-type  and vps26Delta strains. It has been observed that Vps10p is mislocalized in both vps5 and vps35 mutants (Horazdovsky et  al., 1997; Seaman et al., 1997), although to a lesser extent in  vps5 mutants. In Fig. 4 the distribution of Vps10p was examined using a differential centrifugation method that separates  the smaller Golgi, endosomal, and vesicular membranes  away from larger vacuolar (and also ER, mitochondrial, and  plasma) membranes (Marcusson, et al., 1994). Wild-type  cells exhibited a normal distribution of Vps10p with ~90%  of the Vps10p residing in a P100 membrane fraction that  contains Golgi, endosomal, and vesicular membranes. In  vps26Delta cells ~90% of Vps10p is found in the vacuole-enriched P13. This means that vps26Delta cells, with respect to  the localization of Vps10p, have a phenotype very similar to  the vps29 or vps35 mutants (Seaman et al., 1997). Interestingly, a significant proportion of Vps35p becomes soluble in  vps26Delta cells (data not shown), which makes vps26 mutants  somewhat unique, as other mutants (e.g., vps29 or vps5) do  not affect the membrane association of Vps35p, but rather  cause Vps35p to shift to a different population of membranes (Seaman et al., 1997 and data not shown). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>46736</offset><text>Vps35p and Vps5p Colocalize on Sucrose Density Gradients</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46793</offset><text>Previous studies have shown that the distribution of  Vps35p on sucrose gradients can be resolved into two distinct populations of membranes (Seaman et al., 1997),  while Vps5p has been shown to cofractionate with membranes of a density similar to those of small vesicles such  as COPI-coated vesicles (Horazdovsky et al., 1997). The  cross-linking data suggest that Vps35p and Vps5p should  be present on the same population of membranes. To test  this hypothesis, a P100 membrane fraction prepared from  [35S]methionine-labeled cells was spun to equilibrium on a  sucrose density gradient. Fractions were collected, and  various proteins were immunoprecipitated to determine  their location in the gradient. Consistent with previously  published data, Vps35p is found distributed between two  populations of membranes (Fig. 5). Furthermore, there is  clear colocalization between Vps35p and Vps5p in the  denser fractions (fractions 8 and 9). Based upon the fractionation profiles of the late-Golgi protein Kex2p and the  endosomal t-SNARE Pep12p (Becherer et al., 1996), it is  possible to suggest that the lighter population of membranes with which Vps35p associates (fractions 5 and 6) is  most likely an endosomal compartment. The fractions in  which Vps35p and Vps5p colocalize (fractions 8 and 9) appear to be more dense than the fractions that contain  Kex2p, and could correspond to a population of coated  vesicles or tubules. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>48232</offset><text>Vps35p and Vps5p are Present in Vesicle-enriched  Membrane Fractions</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>48301</offset><text>The data presented here and previously (Horazdovsky et al.,  1997; Seaman et al., 1997) suggest that Vps5p and Vps35p  are associated with a dense population of membranes  whose buoyant density is similar to those of known coated  vesicles. As most vesicles also have a characteristic size in  the range of 40-80 nm (Schekman and Orci, 1996), we  have investigated the size of the membranes on which  Vps35p and Vps5p are associated by gel filtration chromatography. A yeast strain expressing an epitope-tagged  Vps10p was fractionated to generate a P100 membrane  fraction, which was then loaded onto a sephacryl S1000  column. The fractions collected were assayed for the presence of various proteins by Western blotting. We observed  that Vps10p was most abundant in fractions 60-66 (Fig. 6  A), where the late-Golgi protein Kex2p (fractions 60-62)  was also detected (data not shown). The bulk of Vps35p  and Vps5p coeluted slightly later in fractions 66-72. These  fractions also contained Vps29p (data not shown), indicating that Vps35p and Vps5p are present on membranes  somewhat smaller than the membranes that contain the  bulk of Vps10p (i.e., Golgi and endosomal membranes).  As a marker for a known coated vesicle, the distribution of  COPI/coatomer was determined. COPI-coated vesicles  have been shown to have a size of 40-60 nm (Ostermann  et al., 1993; Serafini et al., 1991), and eluted from the sizing  column in fractions 66-76, although the bulk of the signal  is detected in the later fractions 72-76. Thus, it appeared  that Vps35p and Vps5p were present on vesicular membranes slightly larger than COPI/coatomer-coated vesicles. The fractionation of Vps35p and Vps5p in fractions  smaller than Golgi or endosomes was not the result of  fragmentation of membranes during homogenization, as  P100 membranes prepared from osmotically lysed cells  fractionated in an identical fashion (data not shown). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>50239</offset><text>Fractions that contained the bulk of the Vps35p/Vps5p  signal were pooled and processed for morphological analysis by EM, and were found to contain numerous small vesicles (data not shown). Attempts to label these vesicles with  antisera against Vps35p, Vps5p, Vps17p, or Vps29p were  not successful; however, as an alternative approach, a P100  membrane fraction from cells expressing an epitope-tagged  VPS5 gene was subjected to cryoelectron microscopy.  Frozen-thin sections were labeled with anti-HA antibodies  and 5 nm anti-mouse colloidal gold. The gold particles  were found to decorate vesicular and tubulovesicular  structures of 80-120 nm (Fig. 6 B).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>50904</offset><text>The distribution of Vps5p in vivo was investigated by using an epitope-tagged VPS5 gene. This has been shown to  complement the vps5Delta mutant, and when expressed in a  class E vps mutant is observed by immunofluorescence to  associate with the exaggerated prevacuolar endosome  present in class E vps mutants (Nothwehr and Hindes,  1997). Therefore, cells expressing the tagged Vps5p were  fixed and prepared for cryoelectron microscopy. Frozenthin sections were labeled with a monoclonal anti-HA antibody, which was followed by 5-nm colloidal gold coupled  to anti-mouse antisera. In Fig. 7, an electron micrograph of  a vps4 cell expressing the HA-tagged Vps5p is shown. The  prevacuolar endosome is decorated with 5-nm gold particles denoting the presence of Vps5p (Fig. 7 A). Strikingly,  the labeling is localized to specific regions in the prevacuolar endosomal membrane, and appears most concentrated at the swollen rims of the cisternae that comprise  the prevacuolar endosome in a class E mutant (Fig. 7 B,  inset) (Babst et al., 1997; Rieder et al., 1996). This localized  distribution of Vps5p is in contrast to the localization of the  vacuolar ATPase, which is found evenly distributed throughout the membranes in a class E mutant (Rieder et al., 1996). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>52172</offset><text>Two Distinct Vps Subcomplexes are Present in a  100,000 g Membrane Fraction</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>52248</offset><text>How do the proteins (Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps26p, Vps17p,  and Vps5p) assemble onto the membrane, and what is the  nature of the membrane-associated complex? To address  this question, we have attempted to strip the complex off  membranes and then separate the components of the complex by gel filtration. Previous studies have shown that  Vps35p and Vps5p can be stripped off the membrane by  treatment with 1M NaCl (Horazdovsky et al., 1997; Paravicini et al., 1992), and in our preliminary experiments we  found that as little as 250 mM NaCl would also strip  Vps35p and Vps5p from the membrane (data not shown).  Therefore, a P100 membrane fraction was treated with a  buffer containing 250 mM NaCl to strip the membranes.  The soluble proteins were then separated away from the  stripped membranes by centrifugation, and the supernatant was loaded onto a sephacryl S300 column that had  been equilibrated in buffer containing 250 mM NaCl.  Fractions from the column were assayed for components  of the multimeric complex by Western blotting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>53290</offset><text>We observed that Vps5p coeluted with Vps17p (Fig. 8),  suggesting that they remain associated. Some proteolysis  of the Vps5 protein occurs during this procedure, resulting  in two breakdown products that migrate a little below the  intact Vps5p. Vps5p and Vps17p coeluted with a predicted  size of ~400-500 kD, which is significantly larger than a  simple dimer of Vps5p/Vps17p, which has a combined molecular mass of ~140 kD. Similarly, Vps35p coeluted with  Vps29p, consistent with the data from the cross-linking experiments (Figs. 2 and 3 B). It appears that Vps35p and  Vps29p also form a complex (~230 kD) larger than the  sum of their two respective molecular masses (110 kD +  30 kD). It is possible that Vps26p is also part of the  Vps35p/Vps29p complex, although the lack of antiserum  against Vps26p precludes direct testing of this hypothesis.  Adding 40 kD of Vps26p to the Vps35p/Vps29p complex  would bring the size of the complex closer to 230 kD. Furthermore, in double mutants of vps29Delta/vps26Delta there was  no detectable Vps35p by Western blotting, and the protein  appeared to be very unstable, with a half-life of ~30 min  (data not shown). Together with data from the cross-linking experiments, these findings support the notion that  two subcomplexes of Vps35p/Vps29p/Vps26p and Vps5p/ Vps17p, respectively, assemble together on an endosomal  membrane. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>54677</offset><text>Vps5p Exhibits Self-assembly Properties</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>54717</offset><text>So far this report has focused primarily on the membrane-associated pool of the proteins being described. It must be  noted, however, that a significant proportion of each of  the proteins is also found in the cytoplasm (Table II). For  example, ~40-60% of the cellular Vps5p is soluble  (Horazdovsky et al., 1997; Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997).  The only exception is Vps35p, of which only 5% of the total Vps35p is present in the cytoplasm (Paravicini et al.,  1992; Seaman et al., 1997). It is reasonable to suppose that  part of the function of these proteins involves cycling on  and off the membrane. We may therefore gain some insight into how these proteins assemble on the membrane  by studying their properties in the cytosol. Thus, cytosol  was prepared from wild-type cells, and was subjected to  sephacryl S300 column chromatography. Fractions collected were assayed for various proteins by Western blotting. In Fig. 9 A the graph depicts the elution profile of  Vps5p, which eluted in the void volume and appeared to  be part of a very large (&gt;106 D) complex. This profile contrasts with the data presented in Fig. 8, in which Vps5p  that had been stripped off the membrane with NaCl was  found to fractionate with a predicted size of ~400-500 kD.  However, that fractionation was performed in the presence of 250 mM NaCl, which may have disrupted protein- protein interactions. Therefore, to see if Vps5p will assemble into the &gt;106 D complex in the absence of NaCl, a  P100 membrane fraction was stripped with NaCl as before.  The membranes were spun out, and the soluble proteins  were dialyzed against Hepes lysis buffer to remove the salt  gradually. This dialyzed supernatant was then fractionated  on the sephacryl S300 column. In Fig. 9 B, dialyzed Vps5p  was found in the void volume fraction, indicating that it  can assemble into a &gt;106-D complex in the absence of salt.  Interestingly, it was found that fractionation of cytosolic  Vps5p was unchanged in any mutant tested, including a  vps17Delta mutant (data not shown), hinting that Vps5p alone  may possess this self-assembly activity.  </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>56839</offset><text>When the fractionation of Vps35p and Vps29p was investigated, it was found that they too coeluted in the void  volume fraction, and thus could be part of a large cytosolic  complex (Fig. 9, C and D, solid lines). It must be noted,  however, that the bulk of Vps29p was found in fractions  consistent with its predicted molecular weight. In vps29Delta  cells, the bulk of the cytosolic Vps35p was no longer in the  void volume fraction, but was shifted to a later fraction  (Fig. 9 C, broken line). Similarly, in the absence of Vps35p,  cytosolic Vps29p no longer eluted in the void volume fraction (Fig. 9 D, broken line). Thus, Vps35p and Vps29p associate with each other in the cytoplasm in a complex that  is &gt;106 D.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>57556</offset><text>Recombinant Vps5p Displays Self-assembly Activity</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>57606</offset><text>The experiments performed on both cytosolic Vps5p and  Vps5p that had been stripped from membranes and then  allowed to reassemble into a large complex (Fig. 9, A and  B) suggested that Vps5p may possess intrinsic self-assembly activity. This was most strongly suggested when cytosol  from vps17Delta cells was fractionated. Even though Vps5p  stably associates with Vps17p (Horazdovsky et al., 1997),  cytosolic Vps5p from vps17Delta cells continued to elute in  the void volume fraction (data not shown), suggesting a  self-assembly property intrinsic to Vps5p. This hypothesis  was tested directly by expression of Vps5p as a recombinant fusion protein. A GST-Vps5p fusion expressed in  yeast has previously been shown to be functional (Fig. 2  C), and hence an identical fusion was expressed in bacteria. The GST-Vps5p was purified by glutathione affinity  chromatography, dialyzed against Hepes lysis buffer, and  fractionated on a sephacryl S300 column. In Fig. 10 A, the  elution profile from the column is shown. GST-Vps5p  (solid line) eluted in the void volume fraction, while GST  alone (broken line) eluted in fractions consistent with its  molecular weight. Fractions from the gel filtration column  were analyzed by SDS-PAGE (Fig. 10 B). Lane M contains molecular weight markers, and lane L contains a  sample of the material loaded onto the column. It is apparent that GST-Vps5p is very susceptible to degradtion, and  that most of the protein loaded onto the column is in fact a  breakdown product of ~55 kD. However, the majority of  the protein that elutes in the void volume fraction is full-length GST-Vps5p with a molecular mass of ~120 kD. As  the breakdown products of the GST-Vps5p were not enriched in the void volume fraction, it seems unlikely that the  assembly of GST-Vps5p into the high molecular weight  complex was not the result of nonspecific aggregation. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>59495</offset><text>Furthermore, analysis of the void volume fraction by  EM revealed that the GST-Vps5p had assembled into a  homogeneous population of 15-20-nm spherical structures. In Fig. 10 C, two panels of four electron micrographs  showing the void volume fraction bound to the electron  microscope grid are shown. In the top four micrographs,  the void volume fraction was bound to the grid, and was  negatively stained with uranyl acetate, while in the lower  four micrographs the bound GST-Vps5p was labeled with  anti-Vps5p antisera followed by anti-rabbit coupled to 5-nm  colloidal gold before negative staining. Generally one or  two gold particles per structure were observed, reflecting a  probable lack of access of the antibody to the antigen. The  regular homogeneous appearance and the GST-Vps5p  particles along with the discrete antibody labeling seen  strongly argues for specific assembly of the GST-Vps5p,  and not for nonspecific aggregation. Recombinant Vps5p  therefore assembles into a high molecular weight complex  similar to the endogenous Vps5p.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>60556</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>60567</offset><text>A New Membrane Coat Complex, the Retromer for  Endosome-to-Golgi Retrieval</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>60642</offset><text>Previous studies have identified a number of vps mutants  that affect the localization of the vacuolar hydrolase receptor Vps10p, and have been proposed to act in the endosome-to-Golgi retrieval of not only Vps10p, but other late-Golgi resident proteins such as Kex2p and DPAP A  (Horazdovsky et al., 1997; Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997;  Seaman et al., 1997). These mutants could be divided into  two distinct groups based upon phenotypic analysis. The  first group comprises vps35, vps29, and vps30, all of which  cause a severe defect in trafficking of CPY to the vacuole,  even though another vacuolar hydrolase, proteinase A  (PrA), reaches the vacuole and is matured with wild-type  kinetics (Seaman, et al., 1997). The defect in the trafficking of CPY to the vacuole is the result of complete mislocalization of Vps10p to the vacuole membrane in the  vps35, vps29, and vps30 mutants. These mutants therefore  appear to affect localization of a subset of proteins, one of  which is Vps10p, and have been proposed to act in a cargo-selective manner in the endosome-to-Golgi retrieval pathway (Seaman et al., 1997). The second group comprises  vps5 and vps17 mutants. Superficially, the vps5 and vps17  mutants have quite different phenotypes from the first  group. In vps5 and vps17 mutants there is a significant defect  in PrA maturation, and the vacuoles appear fragmented.  Vps10p is mislocalized to the vacuolar membrane in vps5  and vps17 mutants; however, this mislocalization is less  dramatic than that observed in the vps35, vps29, and vps30  mutants. Thus, it was suggested that Vps5p and Vps17p  are part of a more general mechanism for endosome-to-Golgi retrieval such that the vps5 and vps17 mutants cause  a complete block in retrieval, ultimately leading to a partial defect in forward transport from the Golgi to the endosome due to lack of retrieval of factors required for forward transport (Horazdovsky et al., 1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>62581</offset><text>Here we show that five peripheral membrane proteins: Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps26p, Vps5p, and Vps17p:assemble  together to form a multimeric complex on a prevacuolar  membrane. Vps5p has been localized to the prevacuolar  membrane, and was found to be clustered at specific sites  that appear to be nascent budding vesicles. Furthermore,  Vps5p can assemble in vitro in a large macromolecular  structure. These data, along with previous studies and phenotypic characterization of the various mutants, point to a  role for these proteins as a membrane coat complex that  directs retrieval of Vps10p and other molecules from the  endosome to the Golgi. To denote its role in retrograde  transport from the endosome to the Golgi, we term this  complex the retromer.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>63342</offset><text>Assembly of the Multimeric Retromer Complex from  Two Distinct Subcomplexes</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>63418</offset><text>The behavior and properties of the individual components  of the retromer complex have been examined to understand the role that each component plays within the complex. A genetic interaction between VPS35 and VPS29  was identified through the use of a dominant negative allele of VPS35. Only overexpression of VPS29 was able to  suppress the CPY sorting defect seen in cells carrying the  vps35dn allele. This result could be interpreted two ways:  either (a) the dominant negative vps35 titrated Vps29p out  of the system into a nonfunctional complex; the resulting  loss of Vps29p would then cause the defect in CPY sorting;  or (b) Vps29p acts downstream of Vps35p, and hence  overexpression can bypass the defect observed in cells  overexpressing the vps35dn allele. We favor the former, as  no suppression of the previously described (Seaman et al.,  1997) temperature conditional allele of vps35 has been observed in cells overexpressing Vps29p (Seaman and Emr,  unpublished data), which would be expected if Vps29p  acts downstream of Vps35p. Furthermore, cell fractionation experiments clearly show that the proportion of  Vps29p that associates with a P100 (Golgi/endosome/vesicle) membrane fraction requires the presence of Vps35p  for that membrane association.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>64692</offset><text>Cross-linking of both a crude lysate and the P100 membrane fraction demonstrated a direct interaction between  Vps35p and Vps29p, and also revealed the presence of  three other proteins in a complex with Vps35p/Vps29p.  These proteins were subsequently identified as Vps26p,  Vps5p, and Vps17p, and are all peripheral membrane proteins that are found in both the cytoplasm and on P100  membranes (Table II). Cross-linking studies performed on  extracts of mutant cells indicated that the retromer complex in fact comprises two distinct subcomplexes. When lysates from vps5 or vps17 mutant cells were cross-linked, it  was found that Vps35p remained associated with both  Vps29p and Vps26p. As previous studies had reported that  Vps5p and Vps17p form a stable complex with each other  (Horazdovsky et al., 1997), the two retromer subcomplexes would then comprise Vps35p/Vps29p/Vps26p and  Vps5p/Vps17p. These data were supported by an experiment in which P100 membranes were stripped with salt to  dissociate the peripheral membrane proteins. When the  solubilized proteins were subjected to gel filtration to size  the individual components, it was observed that Vps5p remained associated with Vps17p in a complex with a predicted size of ~400-500 kD. This value is significantly  larger than the sum of the molecular masses of the individual components (~140 kD), and requires further investigation to establish the nature of this complex. One possibility, however, is that Vps5p/Vps17p can assemble into  structures containing three or possibly four copies of a  simple Vps5p/Vps17p dimer, producing a multimer of  ~400-500 kD.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>66333</offset><text>Although larger than its predicted size, the Vps35p/ Vps29p complex (~230 kD) may also contain Vps26p  (~40 kD). Association of Vps26p with the Vps35p/Vps29p  complex remains to be proven, however, and awaits production of antisera against endogenous Vps26p. Mutants  of vps26 cause Vps10p to become localized to a vacuolar  membrane fraction in a manner indistinguishable from  that of vps35 or vps29 mutants, consistent with Vps26p interacting with Vps35p and/or Vps29p. Furthermore, the  acute instability of Vps35p in a double vps29Delta/vps26Delta mutant supports the notion that Vps35p forms a subcomplex  with both Vps29p and Vps26p. Although vps30 mutants  have phenotypes almost identical to those of vps29 and  vps35 mutants, no Vps30p was detected in the retromer  complex, and the cross-linking data indicated that Vps30p  was not required for complex formation. Although untested, it seems likely that Vps30p may somehow act to  regulate complex formation, or alternatively Vps30p may  function downstream of the retromer complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>67375</offset><text>It is worth noting that the components of this cross-linkable membrane-associated retromer complex display varying degrees of membrane association. Vps35p is 80%  membrane-associated, while only 20% of Vps29p is localized to the membrane, and Vps5p/Vps17p and Vps26p fall  in between these two values (Table II). If all five proteins  were stably associated with each other all of the time, it  would be reasonable to expect them all to be equally  membrane-associated or cytosolic, which is clearly not the  case. Hence, it seems likely that formation and disassembly of the complex is a dynamic process involving cycling  on and off the membrane.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>68024</offset><text>The Self-assembly Properties Intrinsic to Vps5p  Suggest a Mechanical Role in Vesicle Formation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>68120</offset><text>As all the proteins that comprise the retromer complex are  peripheral membrane proteins, and therefore presumably  cycle between the cytoplasm and the membrane, cytosol  was size-fractionated to investigate what sort of complexes  exist in the cytoplasm. Strikingly, it was found that cytosolic Vps5p existed in a very large complex that eluted in the  void volume fraction with a predicted size &gt;106 D. As this  fractionation was performed in a buffer that did not contain high salt, it seemed possible that in the absence of the  salt, Vps5p could assemble (presumably with other proteins; for example, Vps17p) into a large complex. This possibility was tested directly by allowing the retromer complex components that had been salt-stripped from  membranes to assemble in vitro by dialyzing away the salt.  It was found that Vps5p could indeed assemble into a  large complex that was &gt;106 D. Even though Vps5p forms  a stable complex with Vps17p and requires Vps17p for its  membrane association (Horazdovsky et al., 1997), Vps17p  was not required for Vps5p to assemble into the &gt;106-D  complex. Interestingly, however, we have found that Vps17p  in vps5Delta cells is very unstable, and is rapidly degraded with a  half-life of ~30 min (Seaman and Emr, unpublished data).  These data hint that in vivo, Vps5p and Vps17p play different roles within their subcomplex. Vps17p is required for  membrane association, while Vps5p appears to have intrinsic assembly activity. To test the ability of Vps5p to assemble in vitro, a fusion protein expressed in bacteria was purified by affinity chromatography. Consistent with the  behavior of cytosolic Vps5p, the recombinant GST-Vps5p  was found to assemble into a complex that elutes in the  void volume from a gel filtration column, and forms homogenous particles 15-20 nm in diameter. These structures,  however, probably do not perfectly mirror the structures  that endogenous Vps5p forms in vivo, as Vps17p would be  expected to play a role in determining how and where  Vps5p assembles in the cell.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>70173</offset><text>It appeared from the gel filtration analysis of cytosol  that Vps35p could also assemble into a large structure.  This activity was dependent upon Vps29p, and may reflect  an oligomerization property of Vps35p. As almost all of  the Vps35p in the cell is membrane-associated (Paravicini  et al., 1992), this in vitro assembly of cytosolic Vps35p may  reflect an in vivo property of the membrane-associated  Vps35p. We can imagine that if Vps35p acts to recruit specific cargo (e.g., Vps10p) into vesicles for retrieval, a clustering of Vps35p through some sort of oligomerization  would facilitate the concentration of receptors in a specific  membrane domain. Vps29p would then serve a catalytic  role, activating Vps35p and promoting its oligomerization.  Thus, in a vps29 mutant, Vps35p may remain associated  with the membrane, and may still associate with the cytoplasmic tails of receptors such as Vps10p, but will no  longer cluster to concentrate the receptors into a vesicle.  This hypothesis is consistent with the observed behavior of  Vps35p in a vps29 mutant, in which Vps35p follows  Vps10p to a vacuolar membrane fraction (Seaman et al.,  1997).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>71334</offset><text>Localization of Vps5p In Vivo Suggests a Role in  Vesicle Budding</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>71400</offset><text>Sucrose density gradient analysis of the P100 membrane  population with which Vps35p and Vps5p are associated  suggested that Vps35p is associated with two distinct pools  of membranes; a lighter endosomal fraction and a denser  membrane fraction. Vps5p is predominantly associated with  only the denser pool of membranes, which has previously  been shown to have a buoyant density very similar to  known coat vesicles such as COPI and COPI (Horazdovsky  et al., 1997). These observations are consistent with the hypothesis that Vps35p/Vps29p (and also Vps26p) are involved in the recruitment of specific cargo into vesicles. A  proportion of Vps35p and Vps29p would logically be expected to be associated with endosomal membranes, and  not present in vesicles. Vps5p/Vps17p may then assemble  onto the membrane where the receptors are clustered, and  drive the budding of a vesicle. Size fractionation of membranes by sephacryl S1000 column chromatography shows  that Vps5p and Vps35p cofractionate on a population of  membranes smaller than Golgi membranes where Vps10p  and Kex2p reside, but slightly larger than the COPI-coated vesicles.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>72542</offset><text>When fractions from the sephacryl S1000 column were  analyzed by EM, they were found to contain numerous  small 40-100-nm vesicles. However, attempts to label  these fractions with antibodies against retromer components were unsuccessful, possibly because the membrane  association of the retromer proteins is somewhat labile,  and during the course of fractionation or possibly after  elution from the column, the proteins dissociated from the  membrane. Therefore, a cruder P100 membrane fraction  was labeled with antibodies against an epitope-tagged  VPS5, and was found to be predominately localized to vesicular and tubulovesicular structures. In vivo localization  of Vps5p was achieved using a class E mutant (vps4) that  accumulates an exaggerated endosomal compartment  (Babst et al., 1997; Rieder et al., 1996). In this instance,  Vps5p was found to be localized to the swollen rims of the  cisternal membranes that are characteristic of the class E  endosome. These structures are not dissimilar to the membranes with which the epitope-tagged Vps5p is associated  when a P100 membrane fraction is analyzed by cryoimmunogold EM. The key observation is that Vps5p is clustered  on specific regions of the prevacuolar compartment, not  evenly distributed throughout as has been shown for the  vacuolar ATPase that also accumulates in the prevacuolar  endosome in a class E mutant (Rieder et al., 1996). That  Vps5p appears localized to the swollen rims of the cisternae is consistent with its proposed role in vesicle formation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>74082</offset><text>Conservation of the Retromer Components and their  Role in Receptor Trafficking</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>74162</offset><text>Mammalian homologues of the VPS35, VPS29, VPS26, and  VPS5 genes have been identified either as ESTs, or as full-length cDNA clones. VPS35 is homologous to the mouse  gene Mem3 (Hwang et al., 1996), VPS29 has EST homologues in both mouse and humans (Seaman, et al., 1997),  and the mammalian homologue of VPS26/PEP8 (Bachhawat et al., 1994) is termed Hbeta58, and is essential for embryogenesis in the mouse (Lee et al., 1992). Interestingly,  Vps26p shares modest sequence homology (27% identity  over a stretch of 130 aas) with the Sec21 protein, a component of the yeast COPI vesicle coat. The best-characterized  mammalian homologue of the retromer components is  SNX1, which is homologous to VPS5 (Horazdovsky et al.,  1997; Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997). SNX1 has been shown  to interact with the cytoplasmic tail of the EGF receptor,  and overexpression of SNX1 causes an increase in the  turnover and degradation of the EGF receptor (Kurten et  al., 1996). It has been suggested that SNX1 is required for  endosome-to-lysosome trafficking, and may play a role in  the downregulation of activated receptor tyrosine kinases  (Kurten et al., 1996). SNX1 and Vps5p share most sequence homology in a conserved domain that has been  termed the PX domain (Ponting, 1996). The precise role  that this conserved domain plays in the function of Vps5p  and SNX1 remains to be determined, but it is interesting  to note that Vps17p also contains a PX domain, as does  Grd19p (Voos and Stevens, 1998) and Mvp1p (Ekena and  Stevens, 1995), two proteins both believed to be important  for endosome-to-Golgi retrieval in yeast. The PX domain  may therefore confer a function common to all these proteins, perhaps targeting to an endosomal membrane by  binding a specific lipid. This mechanism, however, remains  to be tested.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>75975</offset><text>A Model for the Mechanism of Retromer-mediated  Endosome-to-Golgi Retrieval</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>76051</offset><text>The data presented in this report are consistent with the  complex containing Vps35p, Vps29p, Vps26p, Vps5p, and  Vps17p acting in formation of vesicles for endosome-to-Golgi retrieval, but do not exclude the possibility that  other proteins also function in this pathway (e.g., Grd19p,  Mvp1p, Vps30p, and Vps1p). One of these candidates  (Vps1p, a dynamin-like GTPase) has been shown to be required for proper localization of Kex2p (Wilsbach and  Payne, 1993a). Furthermore, vps1 and vps26 mutants have  been classified in the same phenotypic group, implying an  interaction or action of both proteins at the same step  (Raymond et al., 1992).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>76697</offset><text>Clathrin has also been proposed to act in retrieval from  the endosome to the Golgi, and clathrin mutants also affect the localization of Kex2p (Payne and Schekman, 1989;  Seeger and Payne, 1992b; Wilsbach and Payne, 1993b). Interestingly, however, the effect of clathrin inactivation  upon the localization of Kex2p occurs independently of  the putative late-Golgi localization signal in the cytoplasmic tail of Kex2p (Redding et al., 1996). Hence, it seems  more likely that clathrin functions at the Golgi, and not in  endosome-to-Golgi retrieval.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>77248</offset><text>Thus, we propose that Vps35p acts with Vps29p and  Vps26p to select cargo for retrieval from the endosome to  the Golgi by interactions (either directly or indirectly via  accessory factors) with the cytoplasmic tails of proteins  such as Vps10p and Kex2p (Fig. 10). Aromatic amino acid- containing motifs in the tails of Vps10p and Kex2p have  been shown to be important for their retrieval to the Golgi  (Wilcox et al., 1992; Cereghino et al., 1995; Cooper and  Stevens, 1996), and these motifs are similar to a diaromatic  motif present in the tail of the M6P receptor that is important for its retrieval to the Golgi (Schweizer et al., 1997).  Vps5p/Vps17p assemble onto the clustered receptors  through interactions with Vps35p/Vps29p/Vps26p and/or  the membrane. The self-assembly activity of Vps5p may  drive the budding of the vesicle, although this function  may also be provided by a different component of the retromer complex or by an as yet unidentified protein. The  retromer complex therefore appears to display the two  key activities associated with a vesicle coat complex-cargo  recogniton and self-assembly. Further studies are required  to elucidate the precise role the retromer components play  in endosome-to-Golgi retrieval, and the regulatory mechanisms such as a docking protein and/or a small GTPase  that govern vesicle coat assembly on endosomal membranes have also yet to be revealed. However, these proteins provide the best candidate for a vesicle coat complex  functioning in endosome-to-Golgi retrieval, and a similar  complex may function in mammalian cells at an analogous  point. Cloning and characterization of the mammalian homologues of the yeast retromer components will aid the  molecular dissection of endosome-to-Golgi retrieval.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>79026</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>79045</offset><text>Yeast Stains Used in This Study </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>79078</offset><text>   Strain  Genotype  Source   SEY 6210  MATalpha leu2-3, 112 ura3-52  his 3Delta200 trp1-Delta901  lys 2-801 suc2-Delta9  Robinson et al., 1988  EMY18  SEY 6210 vps35Delta::HIS3  Seaman et al., 1997  EMY3  SEY 6210 vps10Delta::HIS3  Marcusson et al., 1994  PSY1-29  SEY 6210 vps29Delta::HIS3  Seaman et al., 1997  JCY3000  SEY 6210 vps30Delta::HIS3  Seaman et al., 1997  SEY 26-1  SEY 6210 vps26-1  Robinson et al., 1988  MSY2600  SEY6210 vps26Delta::LEU2  This study  KKY11  BHY11 vps17Delta::HIS3  Kohrer and Emr, 1993  BHY152  SEY 6210 vps5Delta::HIS3  Horazdovsky et al., 1997  MSY10-21  SEY 6210 VPS10::VPS10-myc  This study  SEY 4-1  SEY 6210 vps4-1  Robinson et al., 1988</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>79728</offset><text>Vps35p functionally interacts with Vps29p. (A) Wild-type (SEY 6210) cells expressing a dominant negative vps35 allele were transformed with multicopy (2mu) plasmids to overexpress VPS29, VPS30, or VPS35. Control cells were transformed  with empty vector. Cells were pulse-labeled with [35S]methionine  for 10 min, and were then chased in the presence of excess cold  methionine and cysteine for 30 min. The cells were then converted to spheroplasts, and intracellular and extracellular fractions were separated by centrifugation. CPY was immunoprecipitated from resulting lysates, and was subjected to electrophoresis  on an 8% SDS polyacrylamide gel. The proteins were visualized  by fluorography. (B) Wild-type (SEY 6210) and mutant strains in  which VPS29, VPS30, or VPS35 are deleted (PSY1-29, JCY3000,  and EMY18, respectively) were converted to spheroplasts and  then labeled for 15 min with [35S]methionine. After adding excess  cold methionine/cysteine, the cells were chased for 45 min to allow the labeled proteins to reach a steady state distribution. The  cells were then lysed and fractionated by differential centrifugation. Vps29p was immunoprecipitated from the resulting fractions, and was then resolved on an 8% SDS polyacrylamide gel  and visualized by fluorography. The association of Vps29p with a  100,000 g membrane fraction (P100) was found to be dependent  upon Vps35p.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>81123</offset><text>Vps35p and Vps29p are part of a  multimeric membrane associated complex.  (A) A cleared lysate from [35S]methionine-labeled wild-type cells (SEY 6210) was either  left untreated (lanes 1 and 2) or treated with  cross-linker (lanes 3 and 4) as described in  Materials and Methods. After cross-linking,  the proteins were precipitated, and either  Vps35p (lanes 1 and 3) or Vps29p (lanes 2  and 4) was immunoprecipitated. The immunoprecipitates were subjected to SDS-PAGE  on an 8% gel, and the proteins were visualized by fluorography. Strikingly, the pattern  of bands seen in the cross-linked samples (lanes 3 and 4) was very  similar, indicating that Vps35p and Vps29p interact with a common set of proteins. (B) P100 membranes were isolated from  wild-type (SEY 6210) [35S]methionine-labeled cells and resuspended into 100 mul of lysis buffer. The cross-linker DTSSP was  added, and the samples were allowed to cross-link for 30 min at  room temperature. After cross-linking, precipitation by adding  TCA, and resuspending the proteins, Vps35p (lanes 1, 2, 4, 6, and  7) or Vps29p (lane 3) was immunoprecipitated from the lysate.  These primary immunoprecipitates were then resuspended into  100 mul urea buffer, and in the case of lanes 2, 4, 6, and 7, reducing  agent was added. 900 mul of immunoprecipitation buffer was  added, and the samples were further immunoprecipitated with  antibodies against either Vps35p (lane 1), Vps29p (lanes 2, 3, and  4), Vps30p (lane 6), or Vps5 (lane 7). The supernatant from the  sample in lane 1 (after the primary immunoprecipitation) was retained, and antibodies against Vps5p were added (lane 5). Proteins were resolved on an 8% SDS polyacrylamide gel. Vps35p  could be cross-linked to Vps29p, and the proteins designated as  p95 and p70 were found to have an identical migration to Vps5p  and Vps17p. Immunoprecipitation of Vps5p from cross-linked lysates demonstrated the presence of this protein in a complex that  also contained Vps35p and Vps29p. (C) GST-Vps5p expressed in  yeast interacts with Vps17p, Vps35p, and Vps29p. vps5Delta cells  (BHY152) expressing either pMSGST-5 or pEG (KT; empty vector) (Mitchell et al., 1993) were lysed in Hepes lysis buffer containing 0.5% Triton. The lysate was cleared by centrifugation and  then incubated with glutathione-sepharose for 15 min. After several washes, the bound proteins were eluted and precipitated.  The proteins were resolubilized in SDS-PAGE sample buffer,  separated on an 8% polyacrylamide gel, and then transferred to  nitrocellulose for Western blotting. GST-Vps5p was able to associate with Vps17p, Vps35p, and Vps29p (lane 2). GST alone did  not associate with Vps17p, Vps35p, or Vps29p (lane 1).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>83831</offset><text>Identification of p50 and assembly of the multimeric complex in mutant strains. (A) Lysates from either wild-type or vps26Delta  cells that had been pulse-labeled with [35S]methionine were either  treated with cross-linker (lanes 2 and 3) or left untreated (lane 1).  After cross-linking, proteins were precipitated, washed with acetone, and resuspended into immunoprecipitation buffer. Vps35p  was immunoprecipitated, and the proteins were resolved on an 8%  SDS polyacrylamide gel. The band referred to as p50 (Vps26p) is  missing in lysates prepared from vps26Delta cells, and yet Vps35p is still  able to associate with Vps29p, Vps5p, and Vps17p. (B) Wild-type  cells (SEY 6210) or vps35 (EMY18), vps30 (JCY3000), vps29  (PSY1-29), vps17 (KKY11), or vps5 (BHY152) mutants were converted to spheroplasts, labeled with [35S]methionine, chased, and  then lysed with the Hepes lysis buffer. The lysate was cleared by  centrifugation at 2,000 rpm in a microfuge, and then cross-linker  was added to a final concentration of 2 mM. Cross-linking proceeded at room temperature for 30 min, and was then stopped by  adding 100 mul of TCA and transferring the samples to ice. The proteins were precipitated and washed with acetone, and a lysate in immunoprecipitation buffer was prepared as before. Vps35p or  Vps29p was immunoprecipitated from the lysates using double immunoprecipitations under nonreducing conditions. Interaction of  Vps35p with Vps5p/Vps17p required Vps29p, and likewise Vps29p  could not interact with Vps5p/Vps17p in a vps35 mutant.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>85374</offset><text>Vps26p is required for the correct localization of  Vps10p. Wild-type (SEY 6210) or vps26 (MSY2600) mutant cells  were converted to spheroplasts and labeled with [35S]methionine  for 15 min. Excess cold methionine/cysteine was then added, and  the cells were chased for 45 min, after which the cells were lysed  in Hepes buffer and the lysate was spun at 2,000 rpm to remove  unbroken cells. Differential centrifugation (13,000 g, then 100,000  g) was then used to separate larger membranes such as vacuoles  (P13) from small membrane compartments such as Golgi, endosomes, vesicles (P100), and cytosol (S100). The fractions were  treated with TCA to precipitate the proteins that were then  washed with acetone and resuspended into immunoprecipitation  buffer. Vps10p was recovered from the different fractions by immunoprecipitation, and was resolved by SDS-PAGE. The proteins were visualized by fluorography. Deletion of VPS26 causes  a dramatic shift in the distribution of Vps10p to a vacuolar membrane fraction.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>86392</offset><text>Colocalization of Vps35p and Vps5p in a dense membrane fraction. P100 membranes from [35S]methionine-labeled  wild-type cells (SEY 6210) were isolated by differential centrifugation. The membranes were then loaded onto a 10-60% sucrose  gradient and spun to equilibrium. Fractions collected from the  gradient were precipitated with TCA and washed with acetone,  and various proteins were recovered by immunoprecipitation.  Vps35p and Vps29p are associated with two discrete pools of  membranes. The lighter pool contains the endosomal t-SNARE  Pep12p, while the denser population of membranes appears  denser than the late-Golgi marker Kex2p. Vps35p (and Vps29p)  colocalizes with Vps5p and Vps17p in the denser fractions.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>87118</offset><text>Analysis of the size of the membranes on which Vps35p  and Vps5p associate. (A) 100,000 g membranes were prepared  from wild-type cells carrying a myc-tagged version of Vps10p on  the chromosome (MSY10-21). The membranes were resuspended into Hepes lysis buffer and loaded onto a sephacryl S1000  column preequilibrated with Hepes lysis buffer. The membranes  were eluted using the Hepes lysis buffer, and ~2.5-ml fractions  were collected. Fractions were analyzed for the presence of  Vps35p and Vps5p (and other proteins) by Western blotting. The  membranes with which Vps35p and Vps5p are associated elute  after membranes that contain Vps10p (and Kex2p), but before  COPI/coatomer-coated vesicles. (B) A collage of images of anti-HA labeled membranes. A P100 membrane fraction from wild-type cells (SEY 6210) expressing pAH31 (HA-tagged VPS5)  (Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997) was fixed with 2% paraformaldehyde and then prepared for cryosectioning. Frozen thin sections  were labeled with anti-HA monoclonal antibodies, which were  followed by anti-mouse antibodies coupled to 5-nm colloidal-gold. Labeling was predominately restricted to vesicular and tubulovesicular structures. Bar, 100 nm.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>88314</offset><text>Immunolocaliztion of Vps5p by EM. vps4  cells (SEY 4-1) harboring the plasmid pAH31 (HA-tagged VPS5) (Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997) were  fixed and prepared for cryoelectron microscopy. (A)  Frozen thin sections were labeled with the anti-HA  antibody to localize Vps5p, and were followed by 5  nm anti-mouse colloidal-gold. Labeling was found  to be restricted to discrete regions of the prevacuolar endosomal membrane (Ec), and appeared most  concentrated at the swollen rim of the cisterna (B).  Also shown are the nucleus (n) and plasma membrane (pm). Bar, 100 nm.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>88880</offset><text>Sizing the components of the multimeric complex reveals the existence of two distinct subcomplexes. P100 membranes prepared from wild-type cells (SEY 6210) were stripped  by resuspending the pellet in Hepes lysis buffer containing 250 mM  NaCl. The membranes were pelleted by centrifugation at 100,000 g.  The supernatant was loaded onto a sephacryl S300 column equilibrated with lysis buffer plus 250 mM NaCl. Fractions were precipitated with TCA and analyzed by Western blotting. The bulk  of Vps5p and Vps17p remain associated with each other and  form a complex with a predicted size of 400-500 kD. Vps35p remains associated with Vps29p in an ~230-kD complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table_caption</infon><offset>89548</offset><text>Subcellular Distribution of Components of the  Multimeric Complex </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">table</infon><offset>89615</offset><text>   Protein  P13  S100  P100  Reference     %  %  %    Vps35p  15        5      80  Paravicini et al., 1992          Seaman et al., 1997  Vps29p   0       80      20  This study  Vps26p   0            0-30       70-100  Bachhawat et al., 1994          This study (data not shown)  Vps5p   0  ~50  ~50  Horazdovsky et al., 1997          Nothwehr and Hindes, 1997  Vps17p   0  ~25  ~75  Kohrer and Emr, 1993</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>90098</offset><text>Cytosolic Vps5p assembles into a large (&gt;10 6 D) complex. (A) Cytosol (100,000 g supernatant) prepared from wild-type cells (SEY 6210) lysed in Hepes lysis buffer was fractionated  on a sephacryl S300 column. Fractions collected were precipitated and analyzed for the presence of Vps5p by Western blotting. Resulting autoradiograms were scanned and quantitated using National Institutes of Health Image (version 1.61) software.  Vps5p is found almost entirely in the void volume fraction, suggesting that it is part of a complex of &gt;106 D. (B) Vps5p that had  been stripped from P100 membranes using 250 mM NaCl (as in  Fig. 8) was dialyzed against Hepes lysis buffer to remove the salt.  The supernatant was briefly spun at 13,000 g, and was then fractionated on a sephacryl S300 column. Fractions were collected,  precipitated, and analyzed by Western blotting. The autoradiogram was quantitated as above. Vps5p is able to assemble into a  large (&gt;106-D) complex, and elutes in the void volume fraction  (solid line). This contrasts with the size of Vps5p when fractionated in the continued presence of 250 mM NaCl (broken line; this  data is the quantitation of the Vps5p signal in Fig. 8). In C, the  fractionation of cytosolic Vps35p is analyzed. Vps35p is found in  the void volume fraction in cytosol prepared from wild-type cells  (SEY 6210) (solid line). However, when cytosol is prepared from  vps29Delta cells (PSY 1-29), the bulk of Vps35p now elutes in a later  fraction (broken line), indicating that Vps29p function is required  for Vps35p to assemble into a large complex. Similarly in D,  Vps29p in wild-type (SEY 6210) cytosol will partially fractionate  in the void volume fraction (solid line), but when cytosol is prepared from vps35Delta (EMY 18) cells, all the detectable Vps29p is  found in later fractions. Thus, Vps35p and Vps29p appear to assemble together into a large complex that elutes in the void volume from a sephacryl S300 column.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>92058</offset><text>Recombinant Vps5p shows self-assembly activity. (A)  Affinity-purified recombinant GST-Vps5p and GST alone was dialyzed against the Hepes lysis buffer before being loaded onto a  sephacryl S300 gel filtration column. The elution profile of both  GST-Vps5p (solid line) or GST (broken line) is shown. (B) The  GST-Vps5p-containing fractions from the sephacryl S300 column  were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. Lane M denotes the molecular  mass markers, and lane L is the GST-Vps5p before fractionation  on the sephacryl S300 column. The void volume fraction (6) contains predominately full-length GST-Vps5p, while the abundant  breakdown products of the recombinant GST-Vps5p elute later.  (C) The void volume fraction was adsorbed to a formvar/carbon-coated grid and negatively stained with uranyl acetate for examination by electron microscopy (upper four micrographs). In the  lower four micrographs, the void volume fraction was labeled with  anti-Vps5p antisera and 5 nm anti-rabbit colloidal gold before  negative staining. The GST-Vps5p was found to have assembled  into a homogeneous population of 15-20-nm spherical particles.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>93188</offset><text>A schematic model for the mechanism of retromer-mediated vesicle formation at the endosome. (A) The proposed  sequence of events involves Vps35p interacting with cytoplasmic  tails of cargo such as Vps10p and Kex2p. Vps29p then activates  Vps35p, causing clustering of the Vps35p and cargo. Vps5p/ Vps17p then assemble onto the membrane to drive vesicle formation, possibly with Vps17p providing the membrane attachment  activity. (B) Schematic of the two subcomplexes of the retromer  that assemble together onto the endosome membrane. The inner  shell of the retromer coat would be the Vps35p/Vps29p/Vps26p  subcomplex, while Vps5p/Vps17p form the outer shell.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>93851</offset><text>Abbreviations used in this paper</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93884</offset><text>CPY</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93888</offset><text>carboxypeptidase Y</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93907</offset><text>DPAP A</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93914</offset><text>dipeptidyl amino peptidase A</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93943</offset><text>DTSSP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93949</offset><text>3,3'-dithiobis sulfosuccinimidyl-proprionate</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>93996</offset><text>GST</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>94000</offset><text>glutathione S-transferase</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>94026</offset><text>HA</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>94029</offset><text>hemagglutinin</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>94043</offset><text>M6P</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>94047</offset><text>mannose-6-phosphate</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>94067</offset><text>References</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1820</infon><infon key="lpage">1831</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Babst;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Sato;given-names:TK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Banta;given-names:LM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9155008</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur  Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>94078</offset><text>Endosomal transport function in yeast requires a novel AAA-type ATPase, Vps4p</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1379</infon><infon key="lpage">1387</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bachhawat;given-names:AK</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Suhan;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Jones;given-names:EW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7926738</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>94156</offset><text>The yeast homologue of Hbeta58, a mouse gene essential for embryogenesis performs a role in the delivery of proteins to the vacuole</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">9075</infon><infon key="lpage">9079</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bankaitis;given-names:VA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Johnson;given-names:LM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3538017</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">83</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>94286</offset><text>Isolation of yeast mutants defective in protein targeting to the vacuole</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1369</infon><infon key="lpage">1383</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Banta;given-names:LM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Robinson;given-names:JS</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Klionsky;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3049619</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">107</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><offset>94359</offset><text>Organelle assembly in yeast: characterization of yeast mutants defective in vacuolar biogenesis and protein sorting</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">579</infon><infon key="lpage">594</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Becherer;given-names:KA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Rieder;given-names:SE</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Jones;given-names:EW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8730101</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>94475</offset><text>Novel syntaxin homologue, Pep12p, required for the sorting of lumenal hydrolases to the lysosome-like vacuole in yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1089</infon><infon key="lpage">1102</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cereghino;given-names:JL</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Marcusson;given-names:EG</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8534908</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>94594</offset><text>The cytoplasmic tail domain of the vacuolar sorting receptor Vps10p and a subset of VPSgene products regulate receptor stability, function, and localization</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">529</infon><infon key="lpage">542</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Cooper;given-names:AA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8636229</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">133</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>94751</offset><text>Vps10p cycles between the late-Golgi and prevacuolar compartments in its function as the sorting receptor for multiple yeast vacuolar hydrolases</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">48</infon><infon key="lpage">51</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Damke;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8682204</infon><infon key="source">FEBS Lett</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">389</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>94896</offset><text>Dynamin and receptor-mediated endocytosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1671</infon><infon key="lpage">1678</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ekena;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7862158</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>94938</offset><text>The Saccharomyces cerevisiae MVP1 gene  interacts with VPS1and is required for vacuolar protein sorting</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">18</infon><infon key="lpage">20</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Elble;given-names:R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1503765</infon><infon key="source">Biotechniques</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>95042</offset><text>A simple and efficient procedure for transformation of yeasts</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1041</infon><infon key="lpage">1047</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Glickman;given-names:JN</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Conibear;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Pearse;given-names:BMF</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2545438</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>95104</offset><text>Specificity of binding of clathrin adaptors to signals on the mannose-6-phosphate/insulin-like growth factor II receptor</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">557</infon><infon key="lpage">580</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hanahan;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6345791</infon><infon key="source">J Mol Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">166</infon><infon key="year">1983</infon><offset>95225</offset><text>Studies on transformation of Escherchia coliwith plasmids</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Harlow, E., and D. Lane. 1988. Antibodies, A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring  Harbor Laboratory Press, Plainview, New York. pp. 55-137.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>95283</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">177</infon><infon key="lpage">194</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hille-Rehfeld;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7640295</infon><infon key="source">Biochim Biophys Acta</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1241</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>95284</offset><text>Mannose 6-phosphate receptors in sorting and transport of lysosomal enzymes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1529</infon><infon key="lpage">1541</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Horazdovsky;given-names:BF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Davies;given-names:BA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Seaman;given-names:MNJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:McLaughlin;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Yoon;given-names:S-H</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9285823</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>95360</offset><text>A sorting nexin-1 homologue, Vps5p, forms a complex with Vps17p and is required for recycling the vacuolar protein-sorting receptor</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">586</infon><infon key="lpage">590</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hwang;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Benjamin;given-names:LE</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Oh;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Rothstein;given-names:JL</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ackerman;given-names:SL</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Beddington;given-names:RSP</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Knowles;given-names:BB</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8678978</infon><infon key="source">Mamm Genome</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>95492</offset><text>Genetic mapping and embryonic expression of a novel, maternally transcribed gene, Mem3</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">23</infon><infon key="lpage">33</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Jones;given-names:EW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">320092</infon><infon key="source">Genetics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">85</infon><infon key="year">1977</infon><offset>95579</offset><text>Proteinase mutants of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">488</infon><infon key="lpage">495</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kirchhausen;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bonifacino;given-names:JS</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Riezman;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9261055</infon><infon key="source">Curr Opin Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>95628</offset><text>Linking cargo to vesicle formation: receptor tail interactions with coat proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">559</infon><infon key="lpage">569</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kohrer;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8416961</infon><infon key="source">J  Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">268</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>95710</offset><text>The yeast VPS17gene encodes a membrane-associated protein required for the sorting of soluble vacuolar hydrolases</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">307</infon><infon key="lpage">330</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kornfeld;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1323236</infon><infon key="source">Annu Rev Biochem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">61</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>95824</offset><text>Structure and function of the mannose 6-phosphate/insulin-like growth factor II receptors</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">483</infon><infon key="lpage">525</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kornfeld;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mellman;given-names:I</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2557062</infon><infon key="source">Annu Rev  Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>95914</offset><text>The biogenesis of lysosomes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1008</infon><infon key="lpage">1010</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kurten;given-names:RC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Cadena;given-names:DL</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gill;given-names:GN</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8638121</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>95942</offset><text>Enhanced degradation of EGF receptors by a sorting nexin, SNX1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">335</infon><infon key="lpage">345</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Le Borgne;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hoflack;given-names:B</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9128246</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">137</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>96005</offset><text>Mannose 6-phosphate receptors regulate the formation of clathrin-coated vesicles in the TGN</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">22552</infon><infon key="lpage">22556</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Le Borgne;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Schmidt;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Mauxion;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Griffiths;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Hoflack;given-names:B</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8226766</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">268</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>96097</offset><text>Binding of AP-1 Golgi adaptors to membranes requires phosphorylated cytoplasmic domains of the mannose-6-phosphate/insulin-like growth factor II receptor</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">277</infon><infon key="lpage">288</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lee;given-names:JJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Radice;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Perkins;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Costantini;given-names:F</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1638986</infon><infon key="source">Development</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">115</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>96251</offset><text>Identification and characterization of a novel, evolutionary conserved gene disrupted by the murine Hbeta58 embryonic lethal transgene insertion</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">579</infon><infon key="lpage">586</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Marcusson;given-names:EG</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Horazdovsky;given-names:BF</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cereghino;given-names:JL</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gharakhanian;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8187177</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">77</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>96394</offset><text>The sorting receptor for yeast vacuolar carboxypeptidase Y  is encoded by the VPS10gene</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">259</infon><infon key="lpage">279</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:McCaffery;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Farqhar;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8583929</infon><infon key="source">Methods Enzymol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">257</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>96482</offset><text>Localization of GTPases by indirect immunofluorescence and immunoelectron microscopy</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">715</infon><infon key="lpage">723</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Mitchell;given-names:DA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Marshall;given-names:TK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Deschenes;given-names:RJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8368005</infon><infon key="source">Yeast</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>96567</offset><text>Vectors for the inducible overexpression of glutathione S-transferase fusion proteins in yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2700</infon><infon key="lpage">2707</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nothwehr;given-names:SF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bryant;given-names:NJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8649377</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>96662</offset><text>The newly identified yeast  GRDgenes are required for retention of late-Golgi membrane proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">35</infon><infon key="lpage">46</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nothwehr;given-names:SF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Conibear;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7698993</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">129</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>96758</offset><text>Golgi and vacuolar membrane proteins reach the vacuole in vps1mutant yeast cells via the plasma membrane</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1063</infon><infon key="lpage">1072</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Nothwehr;given-names:SF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hindes;given-names:AH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9175702</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">110</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>96863</offset><text>The yeast VPS5/GRD2gene encodes a sorting nexin-1-like protein required for localizing membrane proteins to the late-Golgi</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1872</infon><infon key="lpage">1875</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ohno;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stewart;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Fournier;given-names:MC</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Bosshart;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Rhee;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Miyatake;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Saito;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Gallusser;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Kirchhausen;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Bonifacino;given-names:JS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7569928</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">269</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>96986</offset><text>Interaction of tyrosine-based sorting signals with clathrin-associated proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1015</infon><infon key="lpage">1025</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ostermann;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Orci;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Tani;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Amherdt;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ravazzola;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Elazar;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Rothman;given-names:JE</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8252615</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">75</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>97066</offset><text>Stepwise assembly of functionally active transport vesicles</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">415</infon><infon key="lpage">427</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Paravicini;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Horazdovsky;given-names:BF</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1498362</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>97126</offset><text>Alternative pathways for  the sorting of soluble vacuolar proteins in yeast: a vps35null mutant missorts and secretes only a subset of vacuolar hydrolases</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1358</infon><infon key="lpage">1365</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Payne;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Schekman;given-names:R</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2675311</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">245</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>97281</offset><text>Clathrin: a role in the intracellular retention of a Golgi membrane protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">151</infon><infon key="lpage">171</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pearse;given-names:BMF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Robinson;given-names:MS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2177341</infon><infon key="source">Annu Rev Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>97357</offset><text>Clathrin, adaptors, and sorting</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2353</infon><infon key="lpage">2357</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ponting;given-names:CP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8931154</infon><infon key="source">Protein Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>97389</offset><text>Novel domains in NADPH oxidase subunits, sorting nexins,  and PtdIns 3-kinases: binding partners of SH3 domains? </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1389</infon><infon key="lpage">1402</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Raymond;given-names:CK</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Howald-Stevenson;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Vater;given-names:CA</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1493335</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>97503</offset><text>Morphological classification of the yeast vacuolar protein sorting mutants:  evidence for a prevacuolar compartment in class E vpsmutants</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1667</infon><infon key="lpage">1677</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Redding;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Seeger;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Payne;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Fuller;given-names:RS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8930891</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>97641</offset><text>The effects of clathrin inactivation on localization of Kex2 protease are independent of the TGN localization signal in the cytosolic tail of Kex2p</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">985</infon><infon key="lpage">999</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rieder;given-names:SE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Banta;given-names:LM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kohrer;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:McCaffrey;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8817003</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>97789</offset><text>Multilamellar endosome-like compartment accumulates in the yeast vps28vacuolar protein sorting mutant</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">573</infon><infon key="lpage">582</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Riederer;given-names:MA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Soldati;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Shapiro;given-names:AD</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Lin;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Pfeffer;given-names:SR</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7909812</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1994</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>97891</offset><text>Lysosome biogenesis requires Rab9 function and receptor recycling from endosomes to the trans-Golgi network</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4936</infon><infon key="lpage">4948</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Robinson;given-names:JS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Klionsky;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Banta;given-names:LM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3062374</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><offset>97999</offset><text>Protein sorting  in Saccharomyces cerevisiae: isolation of mutants defective in the delivery and processing of multiple vacuolar hydrolases</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">409</infon><infon key="lpage">415</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rothman;given-names:JE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Orci;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1734280</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">355</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>98139</offset><text>Molecular dissection of the secretory pathway</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">227</infon><infon key="lpage">234</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rothman;given-names:JE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wieland;given-names:FT</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8602507</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>98185</offset><text>Protein sorting by transport vesicles</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1063</infon><infon key="lpage">1074</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rothman;given-names:JH</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Raymond;given-names:CK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gilbert;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:O'Hara;given-names:PJ</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2112425</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">61</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>98223</offset><text>A putative GTP binding protein homologous to interferon-inducible Mx proteins performs an essential function in yeast protein sorting</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1041</infon><infon key="lpage">1051</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rothman;given-names:JH</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3536126</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">47</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>98357</offset><text>Protein sorting in yeast: mutants defective in vacuole biogenesis mislocalize vacuolar proteins into the late secretory pathway</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sambrook, J., E.F. Fritsch, and T. Maniatis. 1989. Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual-Second Edition. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, Plainview, NY.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>98485</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1526</infon><infon key="lpage">1533</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schekman;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Orci;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8599108</infon><infon key="source">Science</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>98486</offset><text>Coat proteins and vesicle budding</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">14471</infon><infon key="lpage">14476</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schweizer;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kornfeld;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Rohrer;given-names:J</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9405637</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">94</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>98520</offset><text>Proper sorting of the cation- dependent mannose 6-phosphate receptor in endosomes depends on a pair of aromatic amino acids in its cytoplasmic tail</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">79</infon><infon key="lpage">92</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Seaman;given-names:MNJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Marcusson;given-names:EG</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Cereghino;given-names:J-L</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9105038</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">137</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>98668</offset><text>Endosome-to-Golgi retrieval of the vacuolar protein sorting receptor, Vps10p, requires the function of VPS29, VPS30 and VPS35gene products</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2811</infon><infon key="lpage">2818</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Seeger;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Payne;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1639056</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">1992a</infon><offset>98807</offset><text>A role for clathrin in the sorting of vacuolar proteins in the Golgi complex of yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">531</infon><infon key="lpage">540</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Seeger;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Payne;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1322413</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">118</infon><infon key="year">1992b</infon><offset>98893</offset><text>Selective and immediate effects of clathrin  heavy chain Mutations on Golgi membrane protein retention in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">248</infon><infon key="lpage">251</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Serafini;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stenbeck;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Brecht;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Lottspeich;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Orci;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Rothman;given-names:JE</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Weiland;given-names:FT</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1898986</infon><infon key="source">Nature</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">349</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>99026</offset><text>A coat subunit of Golgi-derived non clathrin-coated vesicles with homology to the clathrin-coated vesicle protein beta-adaptin</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Sherman, F., G.R. Fink, and L.W. Lawrence. 1979. Methods in Yeast Genetics:  A Laboratory Manual. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory, Plainview, NY.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>99151</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">31</infon><infon key="lpage">40</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Smith;given-names:DB</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Johnson;given-names:KS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3047011</infon><infon key="source">Gene</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">67</infon><infon key="year">1988</infon><offset>99152</offset><text>Single-step purification of polypeptides  expressed in Escherichia colias fusions with glutathione S-transferase</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1237</infon><infon key="lpage">1250</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Takei;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mundigl;given-names:O</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Daniell;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:De Camilli;given-names:P</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8682861</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">133</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>99265</offset><text>The synaptic vesicle cycle: a single vesicle budding step involving clathrin and dynamin</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">527</infon><infon key="lpage">533</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Traub;given-names:LM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kornfeld;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9261049</infon><infon key="source">Curr Opin Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>99354</offset><text>The trans-Golgi network: a late secretory sorting station</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">773</infon><infon key="lpage">786</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Vater;given-names:CA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Raymond;given-names:CK</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ekena;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Howald-Stevenson;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1429836</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">119</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>99412</offset><text>The VPS1protein, a homologue of dynamin required for vacuolar protein sorting in Saccharomyces cerevisiae, is a GTPase with two functionally separable domains</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">577</infon><infon key="lpage">590</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Voos;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Stevens;given-names:TH</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9456318</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">140</infon><infon key="year">1998</infon><offset>99571</offset><text>Retrieval of resident late-Golgi membrane  proteins from the prevacuolar compartment of Sacchormyces cerevisiaeis dependent upon the function of Grd19p</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">885</infon><infon key="lpage">893</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Warnock;given-names:DE</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Schmid;given-names:SL</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8939066</infon><infon key="source">Bioessays</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>99723</offset><text>Dynamin GTPase, a force-generating molecular switch</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">11865</infon><infon key="lpage">11870</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Westphal;given-names:V</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Marcusson;given-names:EG</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Winther;given-names:JR</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Emr;given-names:SD</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:van den Hazel;given-names:HB</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8662642</infon><infon key="source">J  Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>99775</offset><text>Multiple pathways for vacuolar sorting of yeast proteinase A</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1353</infon><infon key="lpage">1371</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wilcox;given-names:CA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Redding;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Wright;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Fuller;given-names:RS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1493334</infon><infon key="source">Mol Biol  Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>99836</offset><text>Mutation of a tyrosine localization signal in the cytosolic tail of yeast Kex2 protease disrupts Golgi retention and results in default transport to the vacuole</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3049</infon><infon key="lpage">3059</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wilsbach;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Payne;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8344247</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">1993a</infon><offset>99997</offset><text>Vps1p, a member of the dynamin GTPase  family, is necessary for Golgi membrane protein retention in Saccharomyces  cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">426</infon><infon key="lpage">432</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wilsbach;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Payne;given-names:GS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14731888</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">3</infon><infon key="year">1993b</infon><offset>100125</offset><text>Dynamic retention of TGN membrane  proteins in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>100199</offset><text>We are very grateful to the Immunoelectron Microscopy Core B (program project grant CA 58689) headed by Marilyn Farquhar for outstanding assistance with the EM. The authors wish to thank Dr. Elizabeth Jones  for plasmid p8HA22, and Dr. Steve Nothwehr for plasmid pAH31 and for  many valuable discussions. Thanks are also due to members of the Emr  lab for critical reading of the manuscript; in particular, Dr. Beverly Wendland, Dr. Markus Babst, Dr. Jon Gary, and Dr. Greg Odorizzi, and also to  Dr. Chris Burd for invaluable discussions and Dr. Stephanie Rieder for  suggesting the term retromer. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>100799</offset><text>The present address of Matthew N.J. Seaman is Department of Clinical  Biochemistry, University of Cambridge, Addenbrookes Hospital, Hills  Road, Cambridge, CB2 2QR, United Kingdom.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>100980</offset><text>Address all correspondence to Scott D. Emr, Division of Cellular and  Molecular Medicine, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, UCSD School of  Medicine, 9500 Gilman Drive, La Jolla, CA 92093-0668. Tel.: 619-534-6462; Fax: 619-534-6414; E-mail: semr@ucsd.edu</text></passage></document></collection>
