<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd">
<collection><source>PMC</source><date>20140719</date><key>ascii.key</key><document><id>2139951</id><passage><infon key="article-id_pmc">2139951</infon><infon key="article-id_pmid">9214382</infon><infon key="fpage">65</infon><infon key="issue">1</infon><infon key="journal-title">The Journal of Cell Biology</infon><infon key="lpage">80</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gorlich;given-names:Dirk</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Dabrowski;given-names:Marylena</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Bischoff;given-names:F. Ralf</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kutay;given-names:Ulrike</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Bork;given-names:Peer</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Hartmann;given-names:Enno</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Prehn;given-names:Siegfried</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Izaurralde;given-names:Elisa</infon><infon key="type">front</infon><infon key="volume">138</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>0</offset><text>A Novel Class of RanGTP Binding Proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>41</offset><text>The importin-alpha/beta complex and the GTPase  Ran mediate nuclear import of proteins with a classical  nuclear localization signal. Although Ran has been implicated also in a variety of other processes, such as cell  cycle progression, a direct function of Ran has so far  only been demonstrated for importin-mediated nuclear  import. We have now identified an entire class of ~20  potential Ran targets that share a sequence motif related to the Ran-binding site of importin-beta. We have  confirmed specific RanGTP binding for some of them,  namely for two novel factors, RanBP7 and RanBP8, for  CAS, Pse1p, and Msn5p, and for the cell cycle regulator  Cse1p from Saccharomyces cerevisiae. We have studied  RanBP7 in more detail. Similar to importin-beta, it prevents the activation of Ran's GTPase by RanGAP1 and  inhibits nucleotide exchange on RanGTP. RanBP7  binds directly to nuclear pore complexes where it competes for binding sites with importin-beta, transportin, and  apparently also with the mediators of mRNA and U  snRNA export. Furthermore, we provide evidence for  a Ran-dependent transport cycle of RanBP7 and demonstrate that RanBP7 can cross the nuclear envelope  rapidly and in both directions. On the basis of these results, we propose that RanBP7 might represent a nuclear transport factor that carries an as yet unknown  cargo, which could apply as well for this entire class of  related RanGTP-binding proteins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>1471</offset><text>The nuclear pore complexes (NPC)1 are the sites  where the exchange of macromolecules between  nucleus and cytoplasm occurs (Feldherr et al., 1984).  Transport through the NPCs is bidirectional and comprises a multitude of substrates. Small molecules can passively diffuse through the NPC. The transport of proteins  and RNAs &gt;40-60 kD is, however, generally an active  process, i.e., it is energy dependent (Newmeyer et al., 1986)  and mediated by saturable transport receptors (Goldfarb  et al., 1986; Michaud and Goldfarb, 1991; Jarmolowski et al.,  1994). To accomplish multiple rounds of transport, these  transport receptors are thought to shuttle between nucleus  and cytoplasm (Goldfarb et al., 1986). An import receptor,  for example, has to bind its import substrate initially in the  cytoplasm, release it after NPC passage into the nucleus,  and return to the cytoplasm without the cargo. Conversely, an export factor has to bind the export substrate  only in the nucleus and on the way out. This model predicts asymmetry in these transport cycles and implies that  the binding of the transport receptor to its cargo is regulated by the different environments of nucleus and cytoplasm.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>2671</offset><text>The nuclear import of proteins with a classical nuclear  localization signal (NLS) is to date the best characterized  nucleocytoplasmic transport pathway (for reviews see Gorlich and Mattaj, 1996; Koepp and Silver, 1996; Schlenstedt,  1996). The signal contains one or more clusters of basic  amino acids (for review see Dingwall and Laskey, 1991)  and is recognized by the importin-alpha/beta complex (for references see Sweet and Gerace, 1995; Pante and Aebi, 1996).  The alpha subunit provides the NLS binding site (Imamoto et al.,  1995; Weis et al., 1995) and is therefore also called the  NLS receptor (Adam and Gerace, 1991). The beta subunit  accounts for the interaction with the NPC (Gorlich et al.,  1995; Moroianu et al., 1995) and carries importin-alpha with the  NLS substrate into the nucleus. The translocation into the  nucleus is terminated by the disassembly of the importin  complex, and both subunits are returned probably separately to the cytoplasm. Importin-alpha interacts with -beta via its  importin-beta binding domain (IBB domain; Gorlich et al.,  1996a; Weis et al., 1996a). Binding to importin-beta with an  IBB domain is sufficient for nuclear entry, and the IBB  domain can therefore be regarded as the nuclear targeting  signal of importin-alpha. The export domain of importin-alpha has  not yet been identified, but it is distinct from the IBB domain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>4034</offset><text>The small GTPase Ran (Drivas et al., 1990; Bischoff and  Ponstingl, 1991b; Belhumeur et al., 1993) plays a key role  in NLS-dependent protein import (Melchior et al., 1993;  Moore and Blobel, 1993). GTP hydrolysis by Ran is absolutely essential for import (Melchior et al., 1993; Moore  and Blobel, 1993; Schlenstedt et al., 1995a; Palacios et al.,  1996) and is possibly even its sole source of energy (Weis  et al., 1996b). Although the molecular mechanism of import is far from being understood, it appears that Ran fulfils at least two distinct functions in this process: first, Ran's  GTP cycle probably drives translocation into the nucleus  (Melchior et al., 1993; Moore and Blobel, 1993; Weis et al.,  1996b), which appears to involve the binding of (cytoplasmic) RanGDP to the NPC, followed by nucleotide exchange and GTP hydrolysis, but it does not involve binding  of RanGTP to importin-beta (Gorlich et al., 1996b). Unfortunately, nothing is known of how Ran's GTP cycle would  translate into a directed movement through the NPC. Secondly, Ran regulates the interaction between importin-alpha  and -beta (Rexach and Blobel, 1995; Chi et al., 1996; Gorlich  et al., 1996b). Binding of RanGTP to importin-beta disassembles the importin-alpha/beta complex at the nuclear side of the  NPC, thereby terminating translocation (Gorlich et al.,  1996b). The asymmetric distribution of Ran's principal  GDP/GTP exchange factor (RCC1; Bischoff and Ponstingl, 1991a) and GTPase activating protein (RanGAP1,  or RNA1 in yeast; Bischoff et al., 1995a; Becker et al.,  1995) crucially determines where the importin heterodimer  can form and where it is forced to dissociate. RCC1 is a  nuclear, chromatin-bound protein (Ohtsubo et al., 1987,  1989) that generates RanGTP in the nucleus, whereas free  RanGTP is depleted from the cytoplasm by RanGAP1,  which is excluded from the nucleoplasm (Hopper et al.,  1990; Matunis et al., 1996; Mahajan et. al, 1997). Thus, low  RanGTP levels in the cytoplasm allow importin-alpha to bind -beta,  and the high RanGTP concentration in the nuclear compartment dissociates the importin complex. The concentration of free RanGTP can, in this model, be regarded as  a marker for cytoplasmic identity (low RanGTP) and nuclear identity (high RanGTP), which is &quot;sensed&quot; by the  Ran-binding site in importin-beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>6364</offset><text>It is likely that at least some properties of importin-beta are  shared by the mediators of the other nucleocytoplasmic  transport pathways. This is emphasized by the recent identification of the importin-beta-related transportin (Pollard et al.,  1996) as an import receptor recognizing the M9 domain,  the nuclear targeting signal in hnRNP A1 (Michael et al.,  1995), and of yeast transportin (Kap 104p) as an import receptor for mRNA binding proteins (Aitchison et al., 1996).  Furthermore, importin-beta or its NPC-binding domain cross-compete with other pathways, such as M9-dependent import, NES-mediated nuclear export, and the export of  mRNA and U snRNA (Kutay et al., 1997). This would suggest that these other transport receptors share at least some  binding sites at the NPC and take a similar path through  the nuclear pore complex as importin-beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>7221</offset><text>In addition to importin-beta, a number of other Ran-binding proteins are detectable in eukaryotic cells, e.g., in overlay blots using Ran gamma-[32P]GTP as a probe. These can be  grouped into two classes (Lounsbury et al., 1994, 1996): first, those with a RanBP1 homology domain including the  Ran binding protein 1 (RanBP1) itself (Coutavas et al.,  1993; Bischoff et al., 1995b) and the nuclear pore protein  RanBP2, which has four RanBP1 homology domains (Wu  et al., 1995; Yokoyama et al., 1995). Their binding to Ran  can be competed by RanBP1. Second, importin-beta and so  far unidentified protein(s) of ~120 kD whose Ran-binding  is competed by importin-beta but not by excess of RanBP1  (Lounsbury et al., 1994, 1996). Both RanBP1 and importin-beta inhibit the nucleotide exchange on RanGTP (Coutavas et al., 1993; Lounsbury et al., 1994, 1996; Bischoff et al.,  1995b; Gorlich et al., 1996b). However, they do not cross-compete with each other for Ran binding but instead bind  to different, nonoverlapping sites on Ran (Chi et al., 1996;  Kutay et al., 1997; Lounsbury and Macara, 1997). Another  striking difference is that RanBP1 facilitates the activation  of Ran's GTPase by RanGAP1 (Beddow et al., 1995; Bischoff et al., 1995b), whereas the importin-beta/RanGTP complex is entirely GAP resistant (Floer and Blobel, 1996;  Gorlich et al., 1996b).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>8574</offset><text>Although a direct involvement of Ran has so far only  been demonstrated in the importin-dependent transport  pathway, perturbations in the Ran system have severe effects on a great variety of cellular functions, such as RNA  processing, RNA export, regulation of chromosome structure, cell cycle progression, initiation of replication, microtubule structure, etc. (for review see Dasso, 1993; Sazer,  1996). One could argue that these effects are all secondary  consequences from an impaired NLS-dependent protein  import. However, it is also possible that these defects are  more direct and that eukaryotic cells contain many immediate targets of Ran function.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>9236</offset><text>Here we describe a novel superfamily of Ran-binding  proteins, which includes about a dozen factors in yeast and  probably even more in higher eukaryotes. The members of  this superfamily share with importin-beta an NH2-terminal  sequence motif that appears to account for RanGTP binding. Indeed we could confirm the interaction with Ran for  the following factors: RanBP7 and RanBP8, two novel, related proteins described here, Cse1p, a cell cycle regulator  in yeast, CAS, which is required for apoptosis in cultured  human cells, and for Msn5p and Pse1p from yeast. Of these  we have characterized RanBP7 and RanBP8 in more detail.  Both resemble closely importin-beta in their interaction with  Ran, and both bind directly to nuclear pore complexes.  RanBP7 can cross the nuclear membrane rapidly and in  both directions. We provide evidence for a transport cycle  in which RanBP7 first enters the nucleus, binds RanGTP  inside the nucleus as a prerequisite for rapid re-export to  the cytoplasm, after which the RanBP7/RanGTP complex  becomes finally disassembled by the concerted action of  RanBP1 and RanGAP1 in the cytoplasm. We propose that  during these transport cycles, RanBP7 would normally  carry an as yet unidentified cargo. This means, RanBP7  and possibly also the other members of the RanBP7/Cse1p/ importin-beta superfamily could function as transport receptors that shuttle between nucleus and cytoplasm. RanBP7  and importin-beta form an abundant, heterodimeric complex  in the cytoplasm that appears to have a function different  from nuclear import of proteins with a classical NLS. It  might be a way to regulate either RanBP7 or importin-beta  function. Alternatively, the RanBP7/importin-beta complex  might constitute an import receptor with a substrate specificity different from that of the importin-alpha/beta complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>11069</offset><text>Materials and Methods</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>11091</offset><text>Purification of RanBP7 and Binding Assays</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>11133</offset><text>For small scale purification, 100 mul of a Xenopus egg extract (plus energy-regenerating system) was diluted 10-fold in binding buffer (50 mM Tris/ HCl, pH 7.5, 200 mM NaCl, 10 mM magnesium acetate), and a post-ribosomal supernatant was prepared. This was rotated overnight with 20 mul  IgG Sepharose to which a z-tagged IBB domain (Gorlich et al., 1996a) had  been prebound. The nonbound fraction was removed, and the beads were  washed six times in binding buffer plus 0.005% digitonin, including a 1-h  wash step. Bound proteins were eluted with 1 M magnesium chloride plus  50 mM Tris/HCl, pH 7.5, and precipitated with 90% isopropanol (final).  For sequence analysis, the purification was scaled up 50 times and performed in a column mode. The bound proteins were separated on an SDS  gel and visualized by Coomassie staining. The RanBP7 band was excised  and digested with trypsin. Peptides were separated by HPLC, and several  peaks were sequenced. Analysis of human RanBP7 was essentially the same,  except that a 50 mug/ml digitonin extract from HeLa cells (for small scale)  or a HeLa extract prepared by mild sonication (large scale) was used as the  starting material. The binding to the BSA-NLS conjugate has been described previously (Gorlich et al., 1996a). The other analytical binding assays  were performed analogous to the small-scale binding described above. Material bound to z-importin-beta or z-RanBP7 was eluted with SDS instead of  magnesium chloride. Additional modifications are described in the legends.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>12667</offset><text>Antibodies</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>12678</offset><text>Antibodies were raised in rabbits against recombinant Xenopus RanBP7.  Affinity purification was on sulfo-Link (Pierce, Rockford, IL) to which  RanBP7 had been coupled. The anti-RanBP7 antibody is monospecific on  blots with total Xenopus egg extract (not shown). Antibodies against importin-alpha, importin-beta, and Ran have been described before (Gorlich et al.,  1995b).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>13049</offset><text>Molecular Cloning</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>13067</offset><text>Based on the partial peptide sequences obtained from RanBP7, two degenerate oligonucleotides AA(AG)ATGAT(TCA)GA(AG)AA(AG)CA  (TC)GG and AA(AG)GCNAT(TCA)TT(TC)CA(AG)AA(AG) were  synthesized and used to identify full length cDNA clones in a Xenopus oocyte cDNA library. For expression and in vitro translation, RanBP7 was  cloned into the pQE70 (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany), zz70, and T7-70 vectors (see below). Comparison of the Xenopus RanBP7 sequence with the  GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ database identified a similar cDNA-clone (IMAGE  Consortium clone ID34250; ACC 360021; Lennon et al., 1996) that was  subsequently shown to code for the NH2 terminus of human RanBP8. The  sequence information of the complete coding region of RanBP8 was obtained by 3' race (Primer: GGATGAAGAGCTGTGGCAAGAAGATCC and Oligo dT18) using KlenTaq enzyme (Clontech Laboratories, Palo  Alto, CA) and a human cDNA as a template. The human cDNA was prepared from HeLa cell mRNA using the direct mRNA kit (OligoTex; Qiagen)  and a cDNA synthesis kit (Great Length cDNA Kit; Clontech Laboratories).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>14132</offset><text>The complete coding sequence of human RanBP8, human CAS, and  human transportin were amplified by PCR from HeLa cDNA and cloned  into the NcoI/BamH1 sites of pQE60 or zz60. The zz60 vector was generated by an in-frame insertion into the NcoI site of pQE60 of a BspHI/  NcoI fragment containing two z domains from protein A. The DNAs encoding Cse1p, Pse1p, Pdr6p, or the NH2-terminal 682 amino acids of  Msn5p were obtained by PCR amplification from genomic Saccharomyces  cerevisiae DNA, using primers containing the appropriate restriction sites  for subsequent cloning into expression vectors. Cse1p was cloned into the  NcoI/BamHI sites of z60, Pdr6p, and the Msn5p fragment, and the Pse1p  fragments were cloned into SphI/BamHI sites of zz70 (a pQE70 derivative  in which two z domains are fused in front of the multi-cloning site).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>14969</offset><text>Sequence Analysis and Homology Searches</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>15009</offset><text>RanBP7 was subjected to a variety of sequence analysis tools (Bork and  Gibson, 1996). Database searches with the Blast series of programs (Altschul et al., 1994) revealed significant similarity with RanBP8 (described  in this paper), Nmd5p, D9509.15p, HRC1004p (an open reading frame from  S. cerevisiae), CAS (Brinkmann et al., 1995), Cse1p (Xiao et al., 1993), and  Lph2p. These were aligned using Clustal W (Thompson et al., 1994) and  Macaw (Schuler et al., 1991). The most significant blocks accumulated in  the first 150 residues of these proteins. To identify more distant members  of this new family, iterative profile searches (Birney et al., 1996; Bork and  Gibson, 1996) were performed based on an alignment of the conserved  NH2-terminal region. New members of this emerging family were accepted and incorporated into the profile for the next iteration when (a)  their scores were higher than 5,000, (b) they were clearly separated from  the first false positive, and (c) when the profile matched the NH2 terminus  of the respective sequence. Each newly identified member was subjected  to reciprocal database searches (Bork and Gibson, 1996). This procedure  left several putative homologues in the &quot;twilight zone&quot; of the profile  search method applied (Birney et al., 1996) and the superfamily described  here might be even larger.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>16360</offset><text>The sequence data for the following aligned proteins are available from  GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession numbers given: Xenopus RanBP7,  U71082; human RanBP8, U77494; human CAS, U33268; S. cerevisiae Cse1p,  P33307; S. cerevisiae Lph2p, U43503; S. cerevisiae Nmd5p, P46970; S. cerevisiae D9509.15p, U32274; S. cerevisiae Yrb4p, P40069; human importin-beta,  L38951; S. cerevisiae importin-beta, U19028; S. cerevisiae HRC1004, S53939;  human RanBP5, Y08890; S. cerevisiae Pse1p, P32337; S. cerevisiae Crm1p,  P30822; S. cerevisiae Mtr10p, U55020; C. elegans C49h3.7, U42436; S.  cerevisiae Los1p, P33418; S. cerevisiae Msn5p, X93302; C. elegans T16g12.3,  Z30317; S. cerevisiae Pdr6p, P32767, Schizosaccharomyces pombe Crm1p,  p14068, S. pombe HRC1004, z69730.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>17118</offset><text>In Vitro Translation</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17139</offset><text>Importin-beta and human transportin were cloned into the T7-60 vector, Xenopus RanBP7 into T7-70. T7-60 and -70 are pQE60 and pQE70 derivatives, respectively, in which the promoter/RBS elements were replaced by  a T7 promoter and the 5' untranslated region from Xenopus beta globin to  enhance translation efficiency. Labeled proteins were generated by coupled transcription/translation in the reticulocyte TNT system (Promega  Biotech, Madison, WI) for 2 h at 30 C.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>17605</offset><text>Oocyte Injections</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>17623</offset><text>To study nuclear export, RanBP7 was translated in vitro and injected  into nuclei of Xenopus oocytes as described (Kambach and Mattaj, 1992).  Two internal injection controls for nuclear integrity were used: the hemoglobin from the reticulocyte lysate, and 14C-labeled BSA (Amersham  Buchler, Braunschweig, Germany) which was coinjected. The distribution  of endogenous proteins in total oocytes, nuclear, and cytoplasmic fractions was determined by SDS-PAGE followed by Coomassie staining or  Western blotting.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18135</offset><text>Microinjection of RNA and analysis by denaturing gel electrophoresis  and autoradiography were performed as described (Jarmolowski et al.,  1994). The concentration of the recombinant importin-beta and RanBP7 in  the injected samples was ~40 muM. The mutant RNAs used (U1DeltaSm,  U5DeltaSm) lack protein binding sites required for the nuclear reimport of  these RNAs and thus remain in the cytoplasm after export from the nucleus. U6Deltass RNA is not exported and is used as an internal control for  nuclear injection.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>18647</offset><text>Expression and Purification of Recombinant Proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>18699</offset><text>The expression and purification of the following factors was as described  previously: importin-beta, nucleoplasmin core domain, z-tagged IBB domain  from Xenopus importin-alpha (Gorlich et al., 1996a), NTF2 (Kutay et al., 1997),  Ran, RanBP1, and S. pombe Rna1p (Bischoff et al., 1995a,b). z-Tagged  RanBP1 was expressed from the zz60 vector and purified via a COOH-terminal his-tag. RanQ69L was expressed from pQE32 (Qiagen) and purified on nickel-NTA agarose (Qiagen), and after nucleotide exchange for  GTP, RanQ69L was concentrated on SP Sepharose FF (Pharmacia,  Uppsala, Sweden). For transport studies, S. pombe Rna1p was expressed  from pQE60 or zz60, and its enzymatic activity was verified by a GAP assay. For some experiments, importin-beta was expressed with an NH2-terminal z-tag and purified on an IBB domain coupled to sulfoLink, followed  by gel filtration on Superdex 200 (Pharmacia). RanBP7 and RanBP8 were  expressed with COOH-terminal his-tags from the pQE70 and pQE60 vectors, respectively. For some experiments two z-domains were fused to  their NH2 termini. Expression of RanBP7 and RanBP8 was in the BLR/ Rep4 strain at 15 C, and purification was on nickel agarose followed by  chromatography on MonoQ. Pse1p, Cse1p, CAS, Msn5p, and Pdr6p were  expressed with NH2-terminal z-tags.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>19999</offset><text>Transportin was expressed at 15 C with a COOH-terminal his-tag, with  or without an NH2-terminal z-tag. Purification was with nickel agarose followed by chromatography on MonoQ (Pharmacia). Activity was verified  in an import assay using a fluorescent nucleoplasmin core-M9 fusion as a  substrate.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>20298</offset><text>Fluorescence Labeling</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>20320</offset><text>Labeling of importin-beta has been described before (Kutay et al., 1997).  RanBP7 and transportin were labeled with fluorescein 5' maleimide as  follows: the recombinant proteins were purified on nickel agarose and  MonoQ, omitting DTT and mercaptoethanol during the MonoQ step. The  protein concentration was estimated from the UV absorbance at 280 nm  (Edelhoch, 1967) and fluorescein 5' maleimide, dissolved in dimethylformamide, and was added at a 1:1 molar ratio. The reaction was allowed to  proceed for 4 h on ice, quenched with 50 mM mercaptoethanol, and the labeled proteins were purified on a Superdex 200 HR column equilibrated  in 20 mM Hepes/KOH, 80 mM potassium acetate, 3 mM magnesium acetate. Human IgG was labeled with Fluos (Boehringer Mannheim, Mannheim, Germany) and purified on Superdex 200.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>21135</offset><text>NPC Binding Assay</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21153</offset><text>The binding assay was essentially performed as an import assay with permeabilized cells as described earlier (Gorlich et al., 1996a,b). The binding  buffer contained 20 mM Hepes/KOH, pH 7.5, 140 mM potassium acetate,  4 mM magnesium acetate, 1 mM DTT, 250 mM sucrose, and 2 mg/ml nucleoplasmin core, 2 mg/ml BSA, plus 1 mg/ml aprotinin to block nonspecific binding, 1.5 muM Ran (GDP form), 150 nM RanBP1, 150 nM Rna1p,  150 nM NTF2, and an energy-regenerating system containing 0.5 mM  GTP and ATP, 10 mM creatine phosphate, and 50 mug/ml creatine kinase.  Binding to the NPC was allowed for 10 min at room temperature. The  other details are given in the legend. The nuclei were fixed with paraformaldehyde/glutaraldehyde, spun onto coverslips, and analyzed by confocal microscopy.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>21937</offset><text>Enzymatic Assays</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>21954</offset><text>Labeling of Ran with gamma-[32P]GTP, GTPase, and nucleotide exchange assays were performed as described (Bischoff et al., 1994, 1995b; Gorlich  et al., 1996b; Kutay et al., 1997). The reactions were performed in 20 mM  Hepes/KOH, pH 7.4, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl2, 1 mM sodium azide,  0.05% hydrolyzed gelatin.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>22261</offset><text>Overlay Blots</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>22275</offset><text>The basic method followed a published protocol (Lounsbury et al., 1994,  1996) with some modifications. Briefly, proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred onto nitrocellulose. The blot was then incubated  for 1 h at 4 C in renaturation buffer containing 20 mM MOPS, pH 7.1,  100 mM sodium acetate, 5 mM magnesium acetate, 5 mM dithiothreitol,  0.5% bovine serum albumin, 0.05% Tween 20, and subsequently for 30  min at 25 C in renaturation buffer plus 100 muM unlabeled GTP (10 ml total volume). After 10 min, 100 mul of 1 nM Ran gamma-[32P]GTP was added  alone or with either 5 muM RanBP1 or importin-beta. After a further 10 min  the blot was washed five times in renaturation buffer and subjected to autoradiography at -70 C. Overlays with Gsp1p were performed the same  way as with Ran.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>23076</offset><text>Results</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>23084</offset><text>Identification of RanBP7 as Copurifying with Importin-beta</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>23141</offset><text>The IBB domain is that part of importin-alpha to which the beta  subunit binds with high affinity. At high salt concentrations, importin-beta appears to bind from a complete cytosol  as a single polypeptide to an immobilized IBB domain  (Gorlich et al., 1996a,b). At more physiological ionic  strength (200 mM), however, a second band of 120 kD  copurifies reproducibly (Fig. 1 A, lane 2). The binding of  importin-beta and the 120-kD protein to the IBB domain is  highly specific by a number of criteria. First, binding requires a functional IBB domain (not shown). Second, the  binding of both polypeptides is sensitive to RanGTP.  RanGTP binds to importin-beta and thereby prevents interaction with importin-alpha or the IBB domain. We used here  the GTPase-deficient RanQ69L mutant which remains in  its GTP-bound form, even in the presence of the cytoplasmic RanGAP1 (Klebe et al., 1995). If 10 muM RanQ69L  GTP was added to the starting material, neither importin-beta  nor the 120-kD protein was recovered in the bound fraction (Fig. 1 A, lane 3). Third, binding is competed by excess  of the nonimmobilized IBB domain (Fig. 1 B, lane 4). For  reasons detailed below, we will refer to the 120-kD protein  as Ran binding protein 7 (RanBP7). To facilitate further  analysis, we obtained partial peptide sequences from  RanBP7, used this information to clone the corresponding  gene from a Xenopus oocyte cDNA library, and expressed  RanBP7 in Escherichia coli. The RanBP7 sequence and its  homologies to other proteins are discussed below. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>24672</offset><text>The finding that RanBP7 copurifies with importin-beta on  an IBB column can be explained in two ways. First, importin-beta and RanBP7 could each bind independently to the  IBB domain, or, secondly, RanBP7 could bind via importin-beta. To distinguish between these possibilities, we subjected a lysate from E. coli expressing RanBP7 to binding  to an IBB column. As seen from Fig. 1 B, RanBP7 was recovered in the bound fraction only when importin-beta was  added. Thus, RanBP7 binds to the IBB domain via importin-beta and is therefore an importin-beta binding protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25230</offset><text>To find out whether the expression of RanBP7 is restricted to Xenopus oocytes or also common to other tissues, we raised antibodies against recombinant RanBP7  and found them to cross-react with a 120-kD protein in a  variety of cells, including HeLa cells. Furthermore, the complex of RanBP7 and importin-beta can be purified on an immobilized IBB domain from a HeLa cell extract in the same  way as from an egg extract (Fig. 1 C). The identity of the  copurifying 120-kD polypeptide was verified in two ways:  by Western blotting using affinity purified anti-RanBP7  antibodies and by peptide sequencing of the 120-kD band,  where all 52 residues of obtained partial sequence  matched human RanBP7 (not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>25941</offset><text>RanBP7 Is a Novel Ran-Binding Protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>25979</offset><text>Mammalian cells contain a number of Ran-binding proteins that can be detected by overlay blots using Ran  loaded with [32P]GTP as a probe (Coutavas et al., 1993;  Lounsbury et al., 1994, 1996). These Ran-binding proteins  fall into two classes. The first class includes those containing a RanBP1 homology domain whose Ran binding is  competed by RanBP1, i.e., RanBP1 itself (23 kD; Coutavas et al., 1993), and RanBP2 (358 kD; Wu et al., 1995;  Yokoyama et al., 1995). In contrast, the signals of the second class comprising 90- and 120-kD bands cannot be competed with RanBP1. The signal is even further enhanced  when the blot is probed with the RanBP1/RanGTP complex (Lounsbury et al., 1996; Kutay et al., 1997). The 90-kD  band corresponds to importin-beta and is recovered in the  IBB-bound fraction (Fig. 1 D). The 120-kD protein which  copurifies with importin-beta, also gives a significant signal in  the overlay. It is therefore RanGTP binding and referred  to as Ran binding protein 7.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>26971</offset><text>It should be noted that the 120-kD band in the total  HeLa extract actually represents a mixture of different  Ran-binding proteins (RanBPs) of similar size. Besides  RanBP7, it includes at least one additional protein called  RanBP5 (Deane et al., 1997) and probably also RanBP8  (see below). Further candidates are RanBP4 and RanBP6  (Hartmann, E., unpublished observations), which are human homologues to the S. cerevisiae proteins Yrb4p  (Schlenstedt, G., E. Smirnova, R. Deane, J. Solsbacher, U.  Kutay, D. Gorlich, H. Ponstingl, and F.R. Bischoff, manuscript submitted for publication) and Pse1p, respectively.  However, of these, only RanBP7 appears to be recovered  in the IBB-bound fraction, as judged by microsequencing  of the 120-kD band (not shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>27735</offset><text>The RanBP7-Importin-beta Interaction Appears  Unrelated to NLS-mediated Protein Import</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>27822</offset><text>Because importin-beta is a key mediator of NLS-mediated  nuclear protein import, we wanted to know if it interacts  with RanBP7 to promote this process. In this case, a quaternary NLS/importin-alpha/beta/RanBP7 complex should be the  active species. However, the experiment shown in Fig. 2 A  makes this assumption unlikely: only importin-alpha and -beta,  but hardly any RanBP7, copurify on an immobilized BSA-NLS conjugate. Consistent with that, RanBP7 does not stimulate import of nucleoplasmin into nuclei of permeabilized  cells (not shown). One possibility would be that importin-beta  binds RanBP7 to modify its substrate specificity. This could  then allow the transport of cargoes that carry signals other  than a classical NLS. Alternatively, the heterodimer might  form to regulate importin-beta and/or RanBP7 function. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>28638</offset><text>The RanBP7/Importin-beta Complex Is Dissociated by RanGTP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>28694</offset><text>The RanBP7/importin-beta heterodimer can be formed by  binding importin-beta from a Xenopus egg extract to z-tagged  RanBP7 (Fig. 2 B). In this case, binding of Ran is not observed, probably because the extract contains Ran only in  its GDP-bound form for which RanBP7 has no detectable  affinity (see below). If RanQ69L GTP that is stabilized in  the GTP-bound form is added to the starting material,  then two effects are observed. First, Ran is now recovered  in the RanBP7-bound fraction, confirming RanBP7 as a  RanGTP-binding protein. Second, the formation of the  RanBP7/importin-beta complex is prevented.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29302</offset><text>To show that RanGTP can also dissociate a preformed  RanBP7/importin-beta complex, we performed the experiment  shown in Fig. 2 C. RanBP7 was expressed in E. coli and  bound to importin-beta that was immobilized on IgG Sepharose  via a z-tag. SDS elutes both RanBP7 and z-importin-beta  from the column. When the elution was performed with  RanGTP, z-importin-beta remained matrix bound, however  RanBP7 was dissociated from importin-beta and recovered in  the eluate (Fig. 2 C). Thus, the RanBP7/importin-beta complex does not form in the presence of RanGTP. Furthermore, a preformed complex is dissociated by RanGTP addition.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>29922</offset><text>Sequence and Homologies of RanBP7</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>29956</offset><text>The Xenopus RanBP7 cDNA codes for a protein of 119 kD.  The peptide sequences from HeLa RanBP7 and a human  RanBP7 sequence tag (Acc R49703) indicate that human  RanBP7 is ~95% identical to the Xenopus protein. On the  basis of an expressed sequence tag we have also cloned another relative, RanBP8, which is a human protein with  61% identity to RanBP7 (Fig. 3). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30323</offset><text>Database searches with the Blast series of programs (Altschul et al., 1994) revealed significant similarity of RanBP7  and RanBP8 to S. cerevisiae Nmd5p (26% identity; Fig. 3),  S. cerevisiae D9509.15p, and a number of further proteins  of similar length, i.e., 95-130 kD. In the multiple alignment  of these sequences (Schuler et al., 1991; Thompson et al.,  1994) the most significant blocks were found within the  NH2-terminal 150 residues of each protein.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>30785</offset><text>RanBP7 Shares a Common NH2-terminal Sequence Motif with a Protein Superfamily that  Includes Importin-beta</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>30890</offset><text>To identify more distant members of this new family, iterative profile searches (Birney et al., 1996; Bork and Gibson, 1996) were performed based on an alignment of the  conserved NH2-terminal region (for details see Materials  and Methods section). The results of the procedure are  shown in Fig. 4 A. They included more than 20 sequences  from different eukaryotes, such as human and yeast importin-beta, S. cerevisiae Cse1p, human CAS, S. cerevisiae  Crm1p, Nmd5p, etc. This protein superfamily consists of  several subgroups, as indicated in Fig. 4 B. The cellular  functions attributed to these proteins appear very diverse,  but it is possible that all relate to nuclear function. For example, importin-beta is the key mediator of NLS-dependent  nuclear protein import, while Cse1p has been shown to be  required for the destruction of B-type cyclins in the yeast  nucleus (Irniger et al., 1995), and human CAS appears to  be required for cell proliferation and apoptosis (Brinkmann et al., 1995). Mtr10 was found in a genetic screen for  mutants defective in mRNA export from the yeast nucleus  (Kadowaki et al., 1994). We reasoned that the common sequence motif in these proteins might relate to a common  function.  </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>32112</offset><text>The Conserved NH2-terminal Motif Appears to Account  for Interaction with RanGTP</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>32193</offset><text>The region of high similarity comprises residues 1-150 in  importin-beta. We recently mapped the Ran binding domain  in importin-beta to the NH2-terminal 364 residues (Kutay et al.,  1997). The NH2-terminal region from the profile search appears to constitute the conserved core of this domain. That  the experimentally found Ran binding domain is larger  than the stretch of conserved amino acids can be explained  with the need for folding to bring the key residues into the  proper spatial position. The conservation profile suggests  that these proteins might be targets of Ran function. In  this case one would not only predict that proteins like Pse1p  and Cse1p bind Ran (or Gsp1p, the yeast Ran, respectively; Belhumeur et al., 1993) but also that the interaction  is mediated by the NH2 termini of these proteins. To test  the predictions for at least some of the candidates, we expressed human CAS and the yeast proteins Pse1p, Cse1p,  Msn5p, and Pdr6p in E. coli, separated the lysates by SDS-PAGE, transferred the proteins onto nitrocellulose, and  probed for Ran interaction using Ran (or yeast Gsp1p)  charged with labeled GTP as a probe.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33344</offset><text>The first protein tested for Ran binding is human CAS.  We probed this blot with Ran gamma-[32P]GTP in the presence  of a 5,000-fold excess of RanBP1. This procedure detects  Ran-binding proteins of the importin-beta type but not Ran  binding proteins like RanBP1 or RanBP2. As seen from  Fig. 5 A, a control lysate expressing importin-alpha which does  not bind Ran, is negative, but the recombinantly expressed  CAS protein gives a positive signal, just as importin-beta. The  CAS-RanGTP interaction is strongly competed by importin-beta (not shown). Thus, human CAS binds RanGTP in a  similar way as importin-beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>33950</offset><text>We next tested Ran binding to full length Pse1p (Chow  et al., 1992) and NH2-terminal fragments of Pse1p from S.  cerevisiae using gamma-[32P]GTP loaded Gsp1p, the Ran homologue of S. cerevisiae. Fig. 5 B shows that full length Pse1p  and its 409 NH2-terminal amino acids are positive in this  Ran-binding assay. The binding is specific, as it is only observed with the GTP form of Gsp1p and is competed by  yeast importin-beta (not shown). The NH2-terminal 257 residues, however, are not sufficient to give a significant signal. Thus, the Gsp1 (Ran)-binding domain of yeast Pse1p  maps approximately as the Ran binding domain of importin-beta (the NH2-terminal 364 amino acids are required for  Ran binding). The same figure also demonstrates the  Gsp1p binding activity of S. cerevisiae Cse1p (Xiao et al.,  1993) and Msn5p (ACC X93302), whereas Pdr6p (Chen  et al., 1991), which also came up in the profile search (Fig.  4), and the control lysates gave no signal.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>34911</offset><text>Effects of RanBP7 and RanBP8 on the RanGTPase</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>34957</offset><text>Having identified an entire class of novel targets for Ran  function, we wanted to investigate the interaction of a representative of this class with Ran in more detail. Ran can  cycle between a GDP and GTP-bound state, where the intrinsic rates of nucleotide exchange and GTP hydrolysis  are very low. Catalysis by specific factors can increase  these rates up to 105-fold (Bischoff and Ponstingl, 1991a;  Bischoff et al., 1994, 1995a; Becker et al., 1995; Klebe et al.,  1995). The major GTPase activating protein is cytoplasmic  RanGAP1 (Rna1p in yeast); the principal GTP/GDP exchange factor is RCC1.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>35562</offset><text>Fig. 6 A shows that RanBP7 and RanBP8 inhibit, like  importin-beta (Floer and Blobel, 1996; Gorlich et al., 1996b),  the GAP stimulation of the Ran GTPase. From the dose  dependence one can estimate the affinities of these factors  for RanGTP. The dissociation constant from RanGTP is ~25  nM for RanBP7, 4 nM for RanBP8, and 0.8 nM for importin-beta, measured under identical conditions. It should be  noted that RanBP7 and RanBP8 also inhibit the intrinsic  GTPase activity of Ran (not shown). </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36058</offset><text>Fig. 6 B shows that RanBP8 inhibits the RCC1-mediated nucleotide exchange on RanGTP (RanBP7 has the  same effect, not shown). The effect is specific for the GTP  form; RanGDP is not affected. RanBP8 and RanBP7 thus  behave like importin-beta (Gorlich et al., 1996b) in this assay.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>36338</offset><text>Like importin-beta, RanBP7 and RanBP8 can each form a  trimeric complex with RanGTP and RanBP1. These complexes are evident by gel filtration (not shown) or by affinity  chromatography. For example, Fig. 6 C shows that RanBP7  can bind via RanGTP to immobilized RanBP1. RanBP1  has a striking effect on both the RanBP7/RanGTP and the  RanBP8/RanGTP complex in that it relieves their GAP  resistance (Fig. 6 D). RanBP1 is thus a cofactor for the disassembly of these complexes. This might well be one in  vivo function of RanBP1. It should be noted that the one  clear difference between importin-beta and RanBP7/8 is that  the RanBP1/RanGTP/importin-beta complex is still GAP resistant (Gorlich et al., 1996b), and its disassembly requires  at least one additional factor (Bischoff, F.R., unpublished  results).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>37145</offset><text>RanBP7 Can Shuttle between Nucleus and Cytoplasm</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>37194</offset><text>RanBP7 is, at steady state, a predominantly cytoplasmic  protein (see below). To test if it can cross the nuclear envelope like importin-beta, we translated RanBP7 in vitro in the  presence of [35S]methionine and injected the mixture into  nuclei of Xenopus oocytes. We used two internal controls  for nuclear integrity, the hemoglobin from the reticulocyte  lysate, which is not exported and clearly visible in the injected nuclei (not shown), and 14C-labeled BSA (&quot;injection  control&quot;). After 5 or 90 min, the oocytes were dissected  into nuclear and cytoplasmic fractions, which were analyzed for the presence of the labeled proteins. As seen from  Fig. 7 A, RanBP7 is rapidly exported from the nuclei, and  a significant proportion reached the cytoplasm already after 5 min. After 90 min the steady state distribution was  reached in which 90-95% of RanBP7 is cytoplasmic. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>38076</offset><text>We next wanted to know if the nuclear export of  RanBP7 is active and dependent on specific factors. As  RanBP7 is a Ran-binding protein, we reason that its interaction with Ran might be crucial for its transport across  the nuclear envelope. As detailed in the introduction, there  is a strikingly asymmetric distribution of the Ran system.  The GDP/GTP exchange factor RCC1, which loads Ran with  GTP, is exclusively nuclear. Its antagonist, the GTPase-activating protein RanGAP1 is excluded from the nucleoplasm and depletes RanGTP from the cytoplasm. As a  consequence, the RanGTP concentration should be high  in the nucleus and very low in the cytoplasm. We wanted  to know if the breakdown of this RanGTP gradient would  affect the nuclear export of RanBP7. To deplete the nuclear RanGTP pool, we injected Rna1p (RanGAP1 from  S. pombe) into nuclei of Xenopus oocytes. As seen from  Fig. 7 A, this treatment severely reduced the rate of RanBP7  export. Strikingly, export was restored if the Rna1p-resistant RanQ69L mutant (GTP form) was prebound to  RanBP7 before nuclear injection. Two conclusions are  suggested from this experiment. First, RanBP7 requires  nuclear RanGTP for export, and second, RanBP7 is exported out of the nucleus as a complex with RanGTP. This  also excludes the possibility that RanBP7 leaves the nucleus by simple diffusion. Because RanGTP dissociates  RanBP7 from importin-beta (Fig. 2, B and C), we can also exclude that RanBP7 is exported by importin-beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>39566</offset><text>At a steady state, RanBP7 is 90-95% cytoplasmic, and  5-10% are found in the nuclear fraction (Fig. 7 B, control).  If this distribution reflects the dynamics of import and export, then endogenous RanBP7 should shift to the nucleus  if its re-export from the nucleus is inhibited by a nuclear  injection of Rna1p (S. pombe RanGAP1). As seen from  Fig. 7 B this treatment does not change the localization of  any of the major cytoplasmic proteins (Fig. 7 B, Coomassie), however, ~50% of the total RanBP7 are indeed  chased into the nucleus. Considering that the nucleus has  only 1/10 of the volume of the cytoplasm, this is not just  equilibration between nucleus and cytoplasm but rather is  a 10-fold accumulation in the nuclei. The treatment also  causes an increase in nuclear importin-alpha. This is consistent  with data in S. cerevisiae (Koepp et al., 1996) showing that  SRP1p (yeast importin-alpha) accumulates in the nucleus if  Prp20p (yeast nucleotide exchange factor for Ran) is defective, which probably also causes a decrease in the nuclear RanGTP concentration. This would suggest that the  export of importin-alpha and RanBP7 requires a higher nuclear RanGTP concentration than their import.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_2</infon><offset>40772</offset><text>RanBP7 and RanBP8 Bind to Nuclear Pore Complexes</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>40821</offset><text>Having shown that RanBP7 can cross the nuclear envelope, we wanted to know whether RanBP7 makes a direct  contact to nuclear pores. To test this, permeabilized cells  were incubated with z-tagged importin-beta (as a positive  control) or with z-RanBP7. The binding of the z-tagged  proteins was visualized with fluorescent IgG added to the  import reaction. Fig. 8 shows the fluorescent staining as recorded with a confocal microscope. Strikingly, when z-importin-beta or z-RanBP7 were present, the typical NPC staining  pattern was observed. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>41363</offset><text>RanBP7 could bind directly to NPCs or only in a complex with importin-beta. In the latter case, the RanBP7-NPC  interaction should be importin-beta dependent. Permeabilized cells still contain endogenous importin-beta, however  only 10-20% of the available importin-beta binding sites at  the NPC are occupied by the endogenous protein (Gorlich  et al., 1995). If RanBP7 binding to the NPC would be strictly  importin-beta dependent, it should be stimulated by exogenous importin-beta. However, NPC binding of z-RanBP7 was  not increased but even lower if a 1:1 complex with nontagged importin-beta was preformed and completely competed by a 10-fold excess of importin-beta. Fig. 8 also shows  that RanBP8 is NPC binding, and again, this binding is  competed by excess of importin-beta.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>42137</offset><text>The data already suggest that RanBP7 binds to NPC not  via importin-beta but directly and to the same sites as importin-beta. However, the interpretation of the competition is  somewhat complicated by the fact that at least 3 species have  to be considered, RanBP7, importin-beta, and the dimeric  complex of the two. We therefore wanted to know if a  transport receptor with no affinity for RanBP7 would also  compete with RanBP7 for NPC binding.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>42579</offset><text>Fig. 9 shows that importin-beta does not bind to itself or to  transportin but binds strongly to RanBP7 and about four  times less efficiently to RanBP8. Transportin, in turn, has  no detectable affinity for either importin-beta or RanBP7. We  therefore chose transportin for the next competition experiment, in which importin-beta, transportin, and RanBP7  were each directly fluorescein labeled and subjected at 30 nM  to NPC binding. Importin-beta was the positive control in this  experiment. Transportin also showed a clear NPC binding  (it should be noted that transportin accumulates inside the  nuclei if added at a higher concentration, probably because it then saturates its own export out of the nucleus).  Strikingly, the transportin signal at the nuclear envelope  could be competed by unlabeled RanBP7. Fluorescent  RanBP7 gave a very clear nuclear pore staining, which could  be competed by unlabeled RanBP7 itself or by transportin. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>43521</offset><text>As a consequence of the competition for NPC binding  between the different transport mediators, excess of one  transport receptor should compete the transport mediated  by another one. Indeed, we have previously shown that  dominant-negative importin-beta mutants or excess of wild-type importin-beta inhibit mRNA and U snRNA export, probably by saturating common binding sites at the nuclear  pore complex (Kutay et al., 1997). Fig. 11 shows that RanBP7  also competes mRNA and U snRNA export, most likely at  the level of NPC binding. As for importin-beta, the export of  tRNA is not affected at this concentration. </text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>44134</offset><text>Discussion</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>44145</offset><text>The small GTPase Ran has been implicated in a variety of  cellular functions, such as transport into and out of the nucleus, regulation of cell cycle progression, and chromatin  structure (for reviews see Dasso, 1993; Sazer, 1996). However, with the exception of the importin-dependent transport pathway, no immediate targets of Ran function have  been reported so far. We have now identified a novel class  of RanGTP binding proteins, which includes to date about  20 proteins from various eukaryotes. The members of this  protein superfamily share the following structural features: (a) a common NH2-terminal sequence motif; (b) a  similar large size of 90-130 kD; (c) a similar isoelectric  point ~4.6 (ranging from 4.3-5.4); and (d) predicted secondary structures with extensive helical regions. In addition, at least some of them have a clear internal repeat  structure (Andrade and Bork, 1995). Whether or not this  applies to all members is currently under investigation.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>45130</offset><text>The members of the RanBP7/Cse1p/importin-beta proteins  superfamily (Fig. 4, and Fornerod et al., 1997) can be  grouped roughly into families as follows: (a) importin-beta-like  proteins including Yrb4p and Pse1p from yeast and RanBP5  from human. (b) A family represented by Los1p and (c)  Crm1p from yeast and human. (d) A family including Msn5p,  Mtr10p, and HRC1004p, and finally (e) Cse1p-like proteins such as CAS, RanBP7, RanBP8, D95009.15p, and  Nmd5p. Except for the NH2-terminal sequence motif, there  is not much homology between these groups of proteins.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>45695</offset><text>In importin-beta, the conserved NH2-terminal region is essential for RanGTP binding (Gorlich et al., 1996b; Kutay  et al., 1997). The presence of this motif in the other members of the superfamily would suggest that they interact  with RanGTP as well. This is indeed the case for at least  RanBP7, RanBP8, CAS, Pse1p, Msn5p, Cse1p (Figs. 1, 2  B, 5, and 6), RanBP5 (Deane et al., 1997), and Yrb4p  (Schlenstedt, G., E. Smirnova, R. Deane, J. Solsbacher, U.  Kutay, D. Gorlich, H. Ponstingl, and F.R. Bischoff, manuscript submitted for publication). From the tested proteins  in Fig. 5, only Pdr6p (Chen et al., 1991) appears negative  for Ran interaction. This might indicate a limitation in the  assays employed, or it might mark the border line for the  significance of the profile in Fig. 4 A. On the other hand,  not all Ran-binding proteins of this kind are covered by  the consensus in Fig. 4 A. For example, transportin does  not match the consensus, although it shows otherwise good  overall homology with importin-beta, functions similarly as  importin-beta (Pollard et al., 1996), and also binds Ran (Bischoff, F.R., S. Nakielny, and G. Dreyfuss, unpublished results).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>46870</offset><text>It should be emphasized that the RanBP7/Cse1p/importin-beta protein superfamily is distinct from the family of Ran-binding proteins with a RanBP1 homology domain. The  two Ran-binding motifs are unrelated in sequence, their  effects on the GTPase are different, and their binding sites  on Ran are distinct and nonoverlapping (Fig. 6, and Introduction).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>47222</offset><text>The interaction with the nuclear pore complex appears  to be a second characteristic of the RanBP7/Cse1p/importin-beta superfamily. This has been well established for importin-beta and is shown here for RanBP7 and RanBP8. In  addition, binding to the NPC or an NPC-like cellular distribution has been demonstrated for RanBP5 (Deane et  al., 1997), Yrb4p (Schlenstedt, G., E. Smirnova, R. Deane,  J. Solsbacher, U. Kutay, D. Gorlich, H. Ponstingl, and F.R.  Bischoff, manuscript submitted for publication), human  Crm1p (Fornerod et al., 1997), Los1p (Simos et al., 1996),  and Cse1p (cited in Irniger et al., 1995). The potential to  interact with both Ran and the NPC would suggest that  transport across the nuclear envelope might be a common  function of this superfamily of proteins. Each of the candidates might represent one distinct transport pathway, and  the task for the future will be to identify their cargoes.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>48142</offset><text>We have previously observed that importin-beta and importin-beta fragments cross-compete with other major nucleocytoplasmic transport pathways such as M9-mediated import and the export of NES containing proteins, mRNA,  and U snRNA (Kutay et al., 1997). This supports the view  that the mediators of these pathways function similarly to  importin-beta, probably take a similar path through the NPC,  and share at least some of the intermediate binding sites.  Here we show that RanBP7 cross-competes with mediators of mRNA and U snRNA export as well. Furthermore,  we observed a direct competition for binding to the nuclear pore complex between RanBP7, importin-beta, and  transportin. Thus, also by this criterion, RanBP7 behaves  like a shuttling transport receptor.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>48904</offset><text>RanBP7 and RanBP8 are Ran-binding proteins with  similar properties as importin-beta. Although the affinity of  RanBP7 for RanGTP is lower than that of importin-beta, it  is still in a physiological range. The KD of the RanBP7/ RanGTP complex is, with ~25 nM, still far below the cellular Ran concentration of several muM. RanBP7 binds specifically, the GTP-bound form of Ran. As free RanGTP  should be available only inside the nucleus, the RanBP7/ RanGTP complex should assemble only in this compartment. Once the RanBP7/RanGTP complex is formed, it is  remarkably stable. The offrate is ~2 h, and the low intrinsic GTPase activity of Ran is even further reduced (not  shown). Furthermore, a GTPase activation by RanGAP1  (RNA1p) is prevented, and the bound GTP is protected  against nucleotide exchange (Fig. 6).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>49720</offset><text>The disassembly of the RanBP7/RanGTP requires the  concerted action of RanBP1 and RanGAP1 (Fig. 6). We suggest the following working model for this process: the intermediate of disassembly is the trimeric RanBP7/RanGTP/ RanBP1 complex (Fig. 6 C), which appears to be in a fast  equilibrium with free RanBP7 and the dimeric RanGTP/ RanBP1 complex (Bischoff, F.R., and D. Gorlich, manuscript in preparation). The latter is an excellent substrate  for RanGAP1, which triggers GTP hydrolysis and thereby  makes the disassembly of the complex irreversible. RanBP1  is essential for nuclear transport in yeast (Schlenstedt et  al., 1995b), but at which step it functions had been obscure  so far. It is therefore an attractive possibility to assume the  physiological function of RanBP1 in the recycling of transport factors like RanBP7.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>50553</offset><text>The RanBP7/RanGTP complex should form only in the  nucleus; however, its disassembly is most likely cytoplasmic because the two factors required for disassembly,  RanGAP1 and RanBP1, are excluded from the nucleoplasm (Hopper et al., 1990; Matunis et al., 1996; Richards  et al., 1996; Mahajan et al., 1997). Assuming that RanBP7  shuttles between nucleus and cytoplasm, one therefore  would predict that RanBP7 leaves the nucleus as a complex with RanGTP. In fact, RanBP7 becomes rapidly exported when injected into nuclei of Xenopus oocytes. Already after 5 min, ~20% of RanBP7 has reached the  cytoplasm. Considering the large size of a Xenopus oocyte,  this is exceedingly fast, in fact much faster than the export  of a BSA-NES conjugate and even faster than tRNA export. The export rate is significantly reduced if nuclear  RanGTP is depleted by nuclear injection of Rna1p  (RanGAP1). The block is not complete, but this is understandable considering that only 25 nM RanGTP is required for half-maximal binding to RanBP7, compared to  at least 10 muM present normally in the nucleus. Thus, to  have a significant effect, the nuclear RanGTP concentration probably has to be lowered by three orders of magnitude, counteracting the continuous RanGTP production  by RCC1. RanGTP depletion from the nucleus inhibits  RanBP7 export probably by preventing the RanBP7/ RanGTP complex formation because the export can be restored by prebinding of RanQ69L GTP (a GAP-resistant  Ran mutant) to RanBP7. This further supports the model  that RanBP7 is indeed exported as a complex with  RanGTP.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>52144</offset><text>RanBP7 is at a steady state predominantly cytoplasmic,  and only ~5% is found in the nuclear fraction. However,  this situation becomes strikingly different if nuclear export  of RanBP7 is inhibited, and then ~50% of RanBP7 can be  shifted to the nucleus. Considering that the nucleus accounts for only 1/10 of the volume of the oocyte, RanBP7  has become 10-fold concentrated in the nucleus compared  to the cytoplasm. This accumulation cannot be explained  by simple diffusion. Taken together, RanBP7 can cross the  nuclear envelope rapidly and in both directions. Although  we have not yet identified a cargo, RanBP7's properties  resemble those of a shuttling transport receptor. We do not  know if RanBP7 would confer import or export. In analogy to importin-beta, however, we would expect the RanGTP- RanBP7 interaction to regulate substrate binding. This  would ensure that the substrate is transported in one direction only, even though RanBP7 shuttles.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>53110</offset><text>In Xenopus eggs or HeLa cells, RanBP7 and importin-beta  form an abundant, cytoplasmic heterodimer. A weaker interaction was found also between RanBP8 and importin-beta  but so far not between other members of the protein superfamily. A complex between importin-beta and an unidentified 120-kD protein has been reported before (Chi et al.,  1995), which was probably identical with RanBP7 or  RanBP8. The RanBP7/importin-beta heterodimer appears  not to be involved in the import of proteins with a classical  NLS. It might be a way to regulate either RanBP7 or importin-beta function, to lower the concentration of free importin-beta if there is only a little substrate in the cytoplasm  and therefore no need for import. Alternatively, the  RanBP7/importin-beta complex might constitute an import  receptor with a substrate specificity different from that of  the importin-alpha/beta complex. Both possibilities are currently  being tested.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>54034</offset><text>The members of the RanBP7/Cse1p/importin-beta superfamily have been implicated in a variety of cellular functions. For example, mtr10 was identified in a screen for defects in RNA export from the yeast nucleus (Kadowaki et al.,  1994). Crm1p is an essential protein in yeast and has been  implicated in the maintenance of chromosome structure  (Toda et al., 1992; Funabiki et al., 1993). Human CAS appears to be required for cell proliferation, but lowering its  cellular levels by the moderate expression of anti-sense  RNA renders cultured cells resistant to TNF-triggered apoptosis (Brinkmann et al., 1995). One of the most interesting proteins is, however, S. cerevisiae Cse1p. It is encoded  by an essential gene and was originally found in a screen  for mutants defective in chromosome segregation (Xiao  et al., 1993). Subsequently, it was shown that Cse1p is essential for the destruction of the B-type cyclin CLB2 and  thus required for progression through mitosis (Irniger et al.,  1995). In yeast, the nuclear envelope does not break down  during mitosis and cyclin CLB2 degradation takes place in  the nucleus. Our data suggest that Cse1p might be a Ran-binding transport factor that could define a novel nuclear  transport pathway. In this model, Cse1p would function in  the timely nuclear transport of a regulator or a mediator of  cyclin CLB2 degradation. At high copy number, SRP1 (yeast  importin-alpha) can partially suppress the phenotype of the  cold-sensitive cse1-1 allele (Xiao et al., 1993), suggesting  that some of the Cse1p function can be taken over by the  &quot;standard&quot; import pathway. Interestingly, the srp1-31 mutant allele also has a cell cycle phenotype, arresting at nonpermissive temperature in G2/M (Loeb et al., 1995). CLB2  is stabilized also in this strain compared to wild-type cells.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">paragraph</infon><offset>55858</offset><text>Taken together, yeast might use about a dozen independent nuclear transport pathways. From expressed, sequenced tags in the data base it appears there might be  considerably more in higher organisms. This probably enables eukaryotes to make full use of their compartmentalization and to use specific regulated nuclear pathways to  control key cellular events.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title_1</infon><offset>56218</offset><text>Figures and Tables</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>56237</offset><text>A 120-kD Ran-binding protein copurifies with importin-beta. (A) A Xenopus egg extract (high speed supernatant, lane 1)  was subjected to binding to an immobilized IBB domain at 200 mM  NaCl. The starting material (lane 1) and the bound fractions (lanes  2-4) were analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by Coomassie staining. Two bands are specifically recovered in the IBB-bound fraction, importin-beta, and a copurifying 120-kD protein that is referred to here as RanBP7. Note, the addition of 10 muM RanQ69L  GTP or nonimmobilized IBB competitor (50 muM) prevent binding of both importin-beta and RanBP7 (lanes 3 and 4, respectively).  (B) RanBP7 was expressed in E. coli. A lysate was prepared and  subjected to binding to an IBB column or to an IBB column to  which importin-beta had been prebound. The starting material and  the bound fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by  Coomassie staining. Note, binding of RanBP7 to the IBB domain  is via importin-beta. (C) A digitonin (50 mug/ml) extract from HeLa  cells was prepared and bound to an immobilized IBB domain as  in A. Analysis was by Coomassie staining and by immunoblotting  with affinity purified antibodies raised against RanBP7, importin-beta,  importin-alpha (Rch1p), and Ran. Again, two bands were recovered  specifically in the bound fraction: importin-beta and a 120-kD protein that cross-reacts with the anti-Xenopus RanBP7 antibody. (D)  A blot of HeLa cell extract and the corresponding IBB-bound  fraction (as in C) was probed with a RanBP1/Ran gamma-[32P]GTP complex, followed by autoradiography. In the IBB-bound fraction,  both importin-beta and RanBP7 give a strong signal. In the crude lysate, importin-beta and a double band of 120 kD is detected. The  latter consists probably of several Ran-binding proteins, in addition to RanBP7.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>58032</offset><text>The RanBP7-importin-beta interaction is regulated by  Ran and appears unrelated to NLS-mediated nuclear protein import. (A) A Xenopus egg extract (high speed supernatant) was  bound either to an immobilized BSA-NLS conjugate or an IBB  domain. The starting material and the bound fractions were analyzed by immunoblots against RanBP7, importin-beta, and -alpha. Note,  whereas equal amounts of importin-beta were found in both bound  fractions, RanBP7 was recovered only with IBB column but hardly  at all with the NLS conjugate. (B) z-Tagged RanBP7 was prebound to IgG Sepharose and used to bind importin-beta out of a Xenopus egg extract (z is an IgG binding domain from Straphylococcus aureus protein A). Binding was with or without the addition of  10 muM RanQ69L GTP. Starting material and bound fractions were  analyzed by immunoblotting against Ran and importin-beta, but the  z-tag is also detected by this procedure. Note that importin-beta but  no Ran bound to RanBP7 in the absence of RanQ69L. If however, the Ran mutant was added, importin-beta binding was abolished, and instead, Ran (Q69L) was recovered in the bound fraction. (C) RanBP7 was expressed in E. coli. A lysate was prepared  and subjected to binding to z-tagged importin-beta that had been  preabsorbed to IgG Sepharose. Elution from the beads was either with SDS, which also releases z-importin-beta from the column,  or with RanQ69L GTP which dissociates RanBP7 from importin-beta.  *, dimerized Ran; **, IgG light chain.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>59515</offset><text>Molecular cloning of Xenopus RanBP7 and human  RanBP8 and their similarities to S. cerevisiae Nmd5p. Xenopus  RanBP7 was cloned from an oocyte library using partial peptide  sequence information from the purified protein. RanBP8 was  found in the data base as an expressed human sequence tag similar to RanBP7 and was subsequently cloned from HeLa cDNA.  Shown are the aligned amino acid sequences from Xenopus  RanBP7, human RanBP8, and S. cerevisiae Nmd5p. Residues  identical in all three proteins are indicated by #, and similar  amino acids by *. The sequence data for Xenopus RanBP7 and  human RanBP8 are available from GenBank/EMBL/DDBJ under accession numbers U71082 and U77494, respectively.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>60216</offset><text>The RanBP7/importin-beta/Cse1p superfamily. (A) Multiple alignment of amino acids 6-141 from RanBP7 with the NH2 termini  of other proteins that have a similar NH2-terminal sequence motif. Positions in red match the consensus. The consensus was defined by  the two most frequent amino acids in each position. Proteins named in blue have been shown to bind Ran (see main text and Fig. 5). S.  pombe Crm1p and HRC1004 also match the motif but are not shown in the figure. (For accession numbers see Materials and Methods.)  (B) Relationship between the proteins shown in A. The tree was calculated from the entire coding sequences and not just from the NH2  termini. Proteins named in red have been shown to bind RanGTP (see also below).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>60952</offset><text>Human CAS and the yeast proteins Pse1p, Cse1p, and  Msn5p are Ran (Gsp1p) binding. Indicated proteins were expressed in E. coli, and the total lysates were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred onto nitrocellulose. The blot in A was  probed with 10 pM Ran gamma-[32P]GTP in the presence of a 5,000-fold molar excess of RanBP1, followed by autoradiography. The  negative control was a lysate from E. coli expressing importin-alpha.  The blots in B were probed with 10 pM Gsp1p gamma-[32P]GTP  (Gsp1p is Ran from S. cerevisiae). The negative control was importin-alpha, as in A. Pse1p 1-257 and Pse1p 1-409 are fragments of  Pse1p comprising of the NH2-terminal 257 or 409 residues.  Msn5p was expressed as an NH2-terminal fragment comprised of  the NH2-terminal 682 residues.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>61719</offset><text>Enzymatic interactions of RanBP7 and  RanBP8 with Ran. (A)  RanBP7 and RanBP8 inhibit  GAP induction of GTPase  activity of Ran. 50 pM Ran  gamma-[32P]GTP was preincubated for 30 min with the indicated concentrations of importin-beta, RanBP7, and  RanBP8. 5 nM Rna1p (RanGAP from S. pombe) was  added, and GTP hydrolysis  was allowed for 5 min. Hydrolysis of Ran-bound GTP  was measured as released  gamma-[32P]phosphate. When using a very low Ran concentration as in this experiment, the  method can be used to estimate the KD of the Ran-binding proteins for RanGTP.  These are ~0.8, 25, and 3 nM  for importin-beta, RanBP7, and  RanBP8, respectively. (B)  Effect of RanBP8 on guanine  nucleotide exchange on Ran.  30 pM Ran alpha-[32P]GDP or 50  pM Ran alpha-[32P]GTP were  preincubated for 30 min with  indicated concentrations of  RanBP8. The exchange reaction was started by addition  of 0.2 mM unlabeled GDP  plus 2 nM of the exchange  factor RCC1. After 5 min,  Ran-bound 32P-labeled nucleotide was measured in a  filter binding assay. Note,  RanBP8 inhibits nucleotide  exchange on RanGTP but not on RanGDP. (C) RanBP7 can form a trimeric RanBP7/RanGTP/RanBP1 complex. z-Tagged RanBP1 was  prebound to IgG Sepharose. A RanBP7 lysate was subjected to binding to either immobilized RanBP1 alone or to an immobilized  RanBP1/RanGTP complex. Elution was with SDS, which also releases the z-RanBP1 from the IgG Sepharose. Note, RanBP7 does not  bind to RanBP1 alone, but it is specifically recovered with the RanBP1/RanGTP complex. *, IgG light chain that leaked from the column. (D) The GAP resistance of the RanBP7/RanGTP and the RanBP8/RanGTP complex is relieved by RanBP1. 100 nM RanGTP  was preincubated for 30 min with indicated concentrations of RanBP7 or RanBP8. Buffer or 200 nM RanBP1 were added, followed immediately by 200 nM Rna1p. GTP hydrolysis was allowed for 5 min and measured as in A.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>63612</offset><text>Characterization of RanBP7 transport between nucleus  and cytoplasm. (A) RanBP7 was translated in the reticulocyte  system in the presence of [35S]methionine and mixed with  [14C]BSA, which served as an injection control. The mixture was  then injected into Xenopus laevis oocyte nuclei either alone or together with 40 muM Rna1p, or with Rna1p and 80 muM RanQ69L.  Proteins were extracted 5 or 90 min after injection. T, C, and N,  indicate proteins extracted from total oocytes or after dissection  from cytoplasmic or nuclear fractions, respectively. Proteins were  analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by fluorography. (B) Nuclei  of Xenopus oocytes were injected either with buffer (control), or  10 muM Rna1p. Oocytes were dissected 6 h later, and the distribution of endogenous proteins was analyzed by SDS-PAGE followed by Coomassie staining, or by Western blotting with  RanBP7 and importin-alpha antibodies. In the control, RanBP7 and  importin-alpha are predominantly cytoplasmic. Nearly 50% of RanBP7  and ~20% of importin-alpha accumulated in the nucleus, after nuclear Rna1p injection that inhibits re-export of RanBP7 and importin-alpha. *, Hemoglobin from the injection control. Rna1p stays  nuclear after nuclear injection as judged by Western blotting (not  shown).</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>64879</offset><text>RanBP7 and RanBP8 bind to nuclear pore complexes.  (A) Permeabilized cells were incubated as indicated with 300 nM  z-tagged importin-beta, RanBP7, or RanBP8 and with 300 nM or  ~3 muM untagged importin-beta. z-Tagged proteins were visualized  with 300 nM fluorescein-labeled human IgG added to the import  assay. Ran and an energy mix were also added. Shown are confocal sections through the equators of the fixed nuclei. Note, z-importin-beta, z-RanBP7, and z-RanBP8 give the typical nuclear pore  staining pattern of narrow, punctate rims. NPC binding of RanBP7  and RanBP8 is competed by untagged importin-beta, and a fluorescent signal is only observed in the cytoplasmic remnants surrounding the nuclei.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>65585</offset><text>Interactions between RanBP7, RanBP8, importin-beta, and transportin. Importin-beta and transportin  were translated in a reticulocyte lysate in the presence of  [35S]methionine. 200 nM  z-tagged importin-beta, RanBP7,  RanBP8, or transportin were  added as indicated, and complexes were allowed to form,  which were subsequently recovered with IgG Sepharose.  The control binding was  without a z-tagged protein.  An immobilized M9 domain  (the import substrate of transportin) was the positive control for transportin binding.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>66107</offset><text>mRNA and U snRNA export are competed by importin-beta or RanBP7. Xenopus laevis oocyte nuclei were injected with  buffer or 40 muM of importin-beta or RanBP7 (as indicate above the  lanes) together with a mixture of the following radioactively labeled  RNAs: DHFR mRNA, histone H4 mRNA, U1DeltaSm, U5DeltaSm,  U6Deltass, and human initiator methionyl tRNA. U6Deltass does not  leave the nucleus and is an internal control for nuclear integrity.  Synthesis of DHFR, histone H4, U1DeltaSm, and U5DeltaSm RNAs was  primed with the m7GpppG cap dinucleotide, whereas synthesis of  U6Deltass RNA was primed with gamma-mGTP. RNA was extracted either 5 or 150 min after injection and detected by electrophoresis,  followed by autoradiography.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">fig_caption</infon><offset>66814</offset><text>Transportin and  RanBP7 compete with each  other for NPC binding. Importin-beta, transportin, and  RanBP7 were labeled directly with fluorescein and incubated at a concentration of  50 nM with permeabilized  cells in the presence of Ran  and an energy-regenerating  system. Where indicated, the  NPC binding was competed  with 2 muM of unlabeled  RanBP7 or transportin. For  analysis, the samples were  fixed, and nuclei were spun  onto coverslips and examined by confocal fluorescence microscopy.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">title</infon><offset>67310</offset><text>References</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">837</infon><infon key="lpage">847</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Adam;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Gerace;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1653647</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">66</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>67321</offset><text>Cytosolic proteins that specifically bind nuclear location signals are receptors for nuclear import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">624</infon><infon key="lpage">627</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Aitchison;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Rout;given-names:MP</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8849456</infon><infon key="source">Science  (Wash DC)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">274</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>67421</offset><text>Kap104: a karyopherin involved in the nuclear transport of messenger RNA binding proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">119</infon><infon key="lpage">129</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Altschul;given-names:SF</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Boguski;given-names:MS</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gish;given-names:W</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Wootton;given-names:JC</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8162065</infon><infon key="source">Nat Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>67511</offset><text>Issues in searching molecular sequence databases</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">115</infon><infon key="lpage">116</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Andrade;given-names:MA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bork;given-names:P</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7550332</infon><infon key="source">Nat Genet</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">11</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>67560</offset><text>HEAT repeats in the Huntington's disease protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">11860</infon><infon key="lpage">11865</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Becker;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Melchior;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gerke;given-names:V</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Wittinghofer;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7744835</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">270</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>67609</offset><text>RNA1 encodes a GTPase-activating protein specific for Gsp1p,  the Ran/TC4 homologue of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3328</infon><infon key="lpage">3332</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Beddow;given-names:AL</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Richards;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Orem;given-names:NR</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Macara;given-names:IG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7724562</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci  USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>67723</offset><text>The Ran/TC4 GTPase-binding domain: identification by expression by expression cloning and characterizaiton of a conserved sequence motif</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2152</infon><infon key="lpage">2161</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Belhumeur;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lee;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Tam;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:DiPaolo;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Fortin;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Clark;given-names:MW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8455603</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>67860</offset><text>GSP1 and GSP2, genetic suppressors of the prp20-1 mutant in Saccharomyces cerevisiae: GTP-binding proteins involved in the maintenance of nuclear organization</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2730</infon><infon key="lpage">2739</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Birney;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Thompson;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gibson;given-names:TJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8759004</infon><infon key="source">Nucleic Acids Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">24</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>68019</offset><text>PairWise and SearchWise: finding the optimal alignment in a simultaneous comparison of a protein profile against all DNA translation frames</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">80</infon><infon key="lpage">82</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1944575</infon><infon key="source">Nature (Lond)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">354</infon><infon key="year">1991a</infon><offset>68159</offset><text>Catalysis of guanine nucleotide exchange on Ran by the mitotic regulator RCC1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">10830</infon><infon key="lpage">10834</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1961752</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">88</infon><infon key="year">1991b</infon><offset>68237</offset><text>Mitotic regulator protein RCC1 is complexed with a nuclear ras-related polypeptide</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2587</infon><infon key="lpage">2591</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Klebe;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kretschmer;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Wittinghofer;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8146159</infon><infon key="source">Proc  Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">91</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>68320</offset><text>RanGAP1 induces GTPase activity of nuclear ras-related Ran</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1749</infon><infon key="lpage">1753</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Krebber;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kempf;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Hermes;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7878053</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci  USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995a</infon><offset>68379</offset><text>Human RanGTPase activating protein RanGAP1 is a homolog of yeast RNA1p involved in messenger RNA processing and transport</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">705</infon><infon key="lpage">715</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Krebber;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Smirnova;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Dong;given-names:WH</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7882974</infon><infon key="source">EMBO J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">1995b</infon><offset>68501</offset><text>Coactivation of RanGTPase and inhibition of GTP dissociation by Ran GTP binding protein RanBP1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">162</infon><infon key="lpage">184</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Bork;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Gibson;given-names:T</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8743684</infon><infon key="source">Methods  Enzymol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">266</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>68596</offset><text>Applying motif and profile searches</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">10427</infon><infon key="lpage">10431</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Brinkmann;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Brinkmann;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gallo;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Pastan;given-names:I</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7479798</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad  Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>68632</offset><text>Cloning and characterization of a cellular apoptosis susceptibility gene, the human homologue to the yeast chromosome segregation gene CSE1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">287</infon><infon key="lpage">299</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chen;given-names:WN</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Balzi;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Capieaux;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Choder;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Goffeau;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1882553</infon><infon key="source">Yeast</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">7</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>68772</offset><text>The  DNA sequencing of the 17 kb HindIII fragment spanning the LEU1 and  ATE1 loci on chromosome VII from Saccharomyces cerevisiaereveals the PDR6 gene, a new member of the genetic network controlling pleiotropic drug resistance</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">265</infon><infon key="lpage">274</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chi;given-names:NC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Adam;given-names:EJH</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Adam;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7615630</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">130</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>69001</offset><text>Sequence and characterization of cytoplasmic nuclear import factor p97</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">559</infon><infon key="lpage">569</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chi;given-names:NC</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Adam;given-names:EJH</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Visser;given-names:GD</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Adam;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8909533</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">135</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>69072</offset><text>RanBP1 stabilizes the interaction of Ran with p97 in nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">709</infon><infon key="lpage">719</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Chow;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ash;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Dignard;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Thomas;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1522152</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">101</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>69148</offset><text>Screening and identification of a gene, PSE-1, that affects protein secretion in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">585</infon><infon key="lpage">587</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Coutavas;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ren;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Oppenheim;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:D'Eustachio;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Rush;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8255297</infon><infon key="source">Nature (Lond)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">366</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>69256</offset><text>Characterization of proteins that interact with the cell-cycle regulatory protein Ran/TC4</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">96</infon><infon key="lpage">101</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Dasso;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8480369</infon><infon key="source">Trends Biochem Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">18</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>69346</offset><text>RCC1 in the cell cycle: the regulator of chromosome condensation takes on new roles</text></passage><passage><infon key="citation">Deane, R., W. Schafer, H.-P. Zimmerman, L. Mueller, D. Gorlich, S. Prehn, H.  Ponstingl, and F.R. Bischoff. 1997. Ran-binding protein 5 (RanBP5) is related to the nuclear transport factor importin-beta but interacts differently with  RanBP1. Mol. Cell. Biol. In press.</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><offset>69430</offset></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">478</infon><infon key="lpage">481</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Dingwall;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Laskey;given-names:RA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1664152</infon><infon key="source">Trends Biochem Sci</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>69431</offset><text>Nuclear targeting sequences:a consensus? </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1793</infon><infon key="lpage">1798</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Drivas;given-names:GT</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shih;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Coutavas;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Rush;given-names:MG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2108320</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">10</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>69475</offset><text>Characterization of four novel ras-like genes expressed in a human teratocarcinoma cell line</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1948</infon><infon key="lpage">1954</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Edelhoch;given-names:H</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6049437</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1967</infon><offset>69568</offset><text>Spectroscopic determination of tryptophan and tyrosine in proteins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2216</infon><infon key="lpage">2222</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Feldherr;given-names:CM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kallenbach;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Schultz;given-names:N</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">6501421</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">99</infon><infon key="year">1984</infon><offset>69635</offset><text>Movement of karyophilic protein through the nuclear pores of oocytes</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5313</infon><infon key="lpage">5316</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Floer;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8621381</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>69704</offset><text>The nuclear transport factor karyopherin beta binds stoichiometrically to Ran-GTP and inhibits the Ran GTPase activating protein</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">807</infon><infon key="lpage">816</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Fornerod;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:van Deursen;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:van Baal;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Reynolds;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Davis;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Murti;given-names:KG</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Fransen;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Grosveld;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9049309</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>69831</offset><text>The human homologue of yeast CRM1 is in a dynamic subcomplex with CAN/Nup214 and a novel nuclear pore component Nup88</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">961</infon><infon key="lpage">976</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Funabiki;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hagan;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Uzawa;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Yanagida;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8388878</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">121</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>69949</offset><text>Cell cycle-dependent specific positioning and clustering of centromeres and telomeres in fission yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">641</infon><infon key="lpage">644</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Goldfarb;given-names:DS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Gariepy;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Schoolnik;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kornberg;given-names:RD</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3638500</infon><infon key="source">Nature (Lond)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">322</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>70052</offset><text>Synthetic peptides as nuclear localization signals</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1513</infon><infon key="lpage">1518</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gorlich;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mattaj;given-names:IW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8599106</infon><infon key="source">Science  (Wash DC)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>70103</offset><text>Nucleocytoplasmic transport</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">246</infon><infon key="lpage">248</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gorlich;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Vogel;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Mills;given-names:AD</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Hartmann;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Laskey;given-names:RA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7675110</infon><infon key="source">Nature (Lond)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">377</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>70131</offset><text>Distinct functions for the two importin subunits in nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1810</infon><infon key="lpage">1817</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gorlich;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Henklein;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Laskey;given-names:RA</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Hartmann;given-names:E</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8617226</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1996a</infon><offset>70206</offset><text>A 41 amino acid motif in importin alpha confers binding to importin beta and hence transit into the nucleus</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5584</infon><infon key="lpage">5594</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Gorlich;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Pante;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kutay;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Aebi;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8896452</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1996b</infon><offset>70314</offset><text>Identification of different roles for RanGDP and RanGTP in nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">309</infon><infon key="lpage">321</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Hopper;given-names:AK</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Traglia;given-names:HM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Dunst;given-names:RW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2116418</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">111</infon><infon key="year">1990</infon><offset>70396</offset><text>The yeast RNA1 gene product necessary for RNA processing is located in the cytosol and apparently excluded from the nucleus</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">3617</infon><infon key="lpage">3626</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Imamoto;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shimamoto;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Takao;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Tachibana;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kose;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Matsubae;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Sekimoto;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Shimonishi;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Yoneda;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7641681</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>70520</offset><text>In vivo evidence for involvement of a 58kDa component of nuclear pore targeting complex in nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">269</infon><infon key="lpage">278</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Irniger;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Piatti;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Michaelis;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Nasmyth;given-names:K</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7736579</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">81</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>70634</offset><text>Genes involved in sister chromatid separation are needed for B-type cyclin proteolysis in budding yeast</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">627</infon><infon key="lpage">635</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Jarmolowski;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Boelens;given-names:WC</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Izaurralde;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Mattaj;given-names:IW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7509815</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">124</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>70738</offset><text>Nuclear export of different classes of RNA is mediated by specific factors</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">649</infon><infon key="lpage">659</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kadowaki;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Chen;given-names:SP</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Hitomi;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Jacobs;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Kumagai;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Liang;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Schneiter;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Singleton;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Wisniewska;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Tartakoff;given-names:AM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8045930</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">126</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>70813</offset><text>Isolation  and characterization of Saccharomyces cerevisiaemRNA transport-defective mtr mutants</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">11</infon><infon key="lpage">21</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kambach;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mattaj;given-names:IW</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1618898</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">118</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>70909</offset><text>Intracellular distribution of the U1A protein depends on active transport and nuclear binding to U1 snRNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">639</infon><infon key="lpage">647</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Klebe;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Ponstingl;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Wittinghofer;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7819259</infon><infon key="source">Biochemistry</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">34</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>71015</offset><text>Interaction of the nuclear GTP-binding protein Ran with its regulatory proteins RCC1 and RanGAP1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1</infon><infon key="lpage">4</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Koepp;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Silver;given-names:PA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8858141</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">87</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71112</offset><text>A GTPase controlling nuclear trafficking:  running the right way or walking randomly? </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1163</infon><infon key="lpage">1176</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Koepp;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wong;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Corbett;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Silver;given-names:PA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8682856</infon><infon key="source">J Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">133</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71199</offset><text>Dynamic localization of the nuclear import receptor and its interactions with transport factors</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1153</infon><infon key="lpage">1163</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Kutay;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Izaurralde;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Bischoff;given-names:FR</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Mattaj;given-names:IW</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Gorlich;given-names:D</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9135132</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol  Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">16</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>71295</offset><text>Dominant-negative mutants of importin-beta block multiple pathways of import and export through the nuclear pore complex</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">151</infon><infon key="lpage">152</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lennon;given-names:GG</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Auffray;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Polymeropoulos;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Soares;given-names:MB</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8617505</infon><infon key="source">Genomics</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">33</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71414</offset><text>The I.M.A.G.E. Consortium: an integrated molecular analysis of genomes and their expression</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">7647</infon><infon key="lpage">7651</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Loeb;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Schlenstedt;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Pellman;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Kornitzer;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Silver;given-names:PA</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Fink;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7644471</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl  Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>71506</offset><text>The yeast nuclear import receptor is required for mitosis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">551</infon><infon key="lpage">555</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lounsbury;given-names:KM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Macara;given-names:IG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8995296</infon><infon key="source">J Biol  Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">272</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>71564</offset><text>Ran-binding protein 1 (RanBP1) forms a ternary complex with Ran and karyopherin beta and reduces Ran GTPase-activating Protein (RanGAP) inhibition by karyopherin beta</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">11285</infon><infon key="lpage">11290</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lounsbury;given-names:KM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Beddow;given-names:AL</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Macara;given-names:IG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8157660</infon><infon key="source">J Biol  Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">269</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>71727</offset><text>A family of proteins that stabilize the Ran/TC4 GTPase in its GTP-bound conformation</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2357</infon><infon key="lpage">2360</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Lounsbury;given-names:KM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Richards;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Perlungher;given-names:RR</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Macara;given-names:IG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8576188</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">271</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>71812</offset><text>Ran binding domains promote the interaction of ran with p97/beta-karyopherin, linking the docking and translocation steps of nuclear import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">97</infon><infon key="lpage">107</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Mahajan;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Delphin;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Guan;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gerace;given-names:L</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Melchior;given-names:F</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9019411</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">88</infon><infon key="year">1997</infon><offset>71950</offset><text>A small ubiquitin-related polypeptide involved in targeting RanGAP1 to nuclear pore complex protein RanBP2</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1457</infon><infon key="lpage">1470</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Matunis;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Coutavas;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8978815</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">135</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>72057</offset><text>A novel ubiquitin-like modification modulates the partitioning of the Ran-GTPase-activating protein between cytosol and nuclear pore complex</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1649</infon><infon key="lpage">1659</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Melchior;given-names:F</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Paschal;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Evans;given-names:E</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Gerace;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8276887</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">123</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>72200</offset><text>Inhibition of nuclear protein import by nonhydrolyzable analogs of GTP and identification of the small GTPase Ran/TC4 as an essential transport factor</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">415</infon><infon key="lpage">422</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Michael;given-names:WM</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Choi;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Dreyfuss;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8521471</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">83</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>72351</offset><text>A nuclear export signal in hnRNP A1: a signal-mediated, temperature-dependent nuclear protein export pathway</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">215</infon><infon key="lpage">223</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Michaud;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Goldfarb;given-names:DS</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1824847</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">112</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>72460</offset><text>Multiple pathways in nuclear transport: the import of U2 snRNP occurs by a novel kinetic pathway</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">661</infon><infon key="lpage">663</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Moore;given-names:MS</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8413630</infon><infon key="source">Nature (Lond)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">365</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>72557</offset><text>The GTP-binding protein Ran/TC4 is required for protein import into the nucleus</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">6532</infon><infon key="lpage">6536</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Moroianu;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hijikata;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Radu;given-names:A</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7604027</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>72637</offset><text>Mammalian karyopherin a1b and a2b heterodimers: a1 or a2 subunit binds nuclear localization sequence and b subunit interacts with peptide repeat containing nucleoporins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">501</infon><infon key="lpage">510</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Newmeyer;given-names:DD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lucocq;given-names:JM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Burglin;given-names:TR</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:De Robertis;given-names:EM</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3709518</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol  Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">1986</infon><offset>72806</offset><text>Assembly in vitro of nuclei active in nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">585</infon><infon key="lpage">593</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ohtsubo;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Kai;given-names:R</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Furuno;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Sekiguchi;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Sekiguchi;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Hayashida;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Kuma;given-names:K-I</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Miyata;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Fukushige;given-names:S</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Murotsu;given-names:T</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">3678831</infon><infon key="source">Genes Dev</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">1</infon><infon key="year">1987</infon><offset>72867</offset><text>Isolation and characterization of the active cDNA of the human cell cycle gene RCC1 involved in the regulation of onset of chromosome condensation</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1389</infon><infon key="lpage">1397</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Ohtsubo;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Okazaki;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Nishimoto;given-names:T</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2677018</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">109</infon><infon key="year">1989</infon><offset>73014</offset><text>The RCC1 protein, a regulator for the onset of chromosome condensation locates in the nucleus and binds to DNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">397</infon><infon key="lpage">406</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pante;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Aebi;given-names:U</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8743893</infon><infon key="source">Curr Opin Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">8</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>73125</offset><text>Towards the molecular dissection of protein import into nuclei</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">485</infon><infon key="lpage">494</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Palacios;given-names:I</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Weis;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Klebe;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Dingwall;given-names:C</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8636225</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">133</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>73188</offset><text>Ran/TC4 mutants identify a common requirement for snRNP and protein import into the nucleus</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">985</infon><infon key="lpage">994</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Pollard;given-names:VW</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Michael;given-names:WM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Naldalny;given-names:B</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Slomi;given-names:MC</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Wang;given-names:P</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Dreyfuss;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8808633</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">88</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>73280</offset><text>A novel receptor mediated nuclear protein import pathway</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">683</infon><infon key="lpage">692</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Rexach;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8521485</infon><infon key="source">Cell</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">83</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>73337</offset><text>Protein import into nuclei: association and dissociation reactions involving transport substrate, transport factors, and nucleoporins</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1157</infon><infon key="lpage">1168</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Richards;given-names:SA</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Lounsbury;given-names:KM</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Carey;given-names:KL</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Macara;given-names:IG</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8794858</infon><infon key="source">J Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">134</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>73471</offset><text>A nuclear export signal is essential for the cytosolic localization of the Ran binding protein, RanBP1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">81</infon><infon key="lpage">85</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sazer;given-names:S</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">15157482</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">6</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>73574</offset><text>The search for the primary function of the Ran GTPase continues</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">75</infon><infon key="lpage">79</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schlenstedt;given-names:G</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8682210</infon><infon key="source">FEBS (Fed Eur Biochem Sci) Lett</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">389</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>73638</offset><text>Protein import into the nucleus</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">225</infon><infon key="lpage">229</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schlenstedt;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Saavedra;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Loeb;given-names:JDJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Cole;given-names:CN</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Silver;given-names:PA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7816822</infon><infon key="source">Proc Natl  Acad Sci USA</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">92</infon><infon key="year">1995a</infon><offset>73670</offset><text>The GTP-bound form of the yeast Ran/TC4 homologue blocks nuclear protein import and appearance of polyA+RNA in the cytoplasm</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5367</infon><infon key="lpage">5378</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schlenstedt;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Wong;given-names:DH</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Koepp;given-names:DM</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Silver;given-names:PA</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7489726</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur  Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">14</infon><infon key="year">1995b</infon><offset>73795</offset><text>Mutants in a yeast Ran binding protein are defective in nuclear transport</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">180</infon><infon key="lpage">190</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Schuler;given-names:GD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Altschul;given-names:SF</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lipman;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">2006136</infon><infon key="source">Proteins</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">9</infon><infon key="year">1991</infon><offset>73869</offset><text>A workbench for multiple alignment construction and analysis</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">444</infon><infon key="lpage">447</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Sweet;given-names:DJ</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Gerace;given-names:L</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">14732023</infon><infon key="source">Trends Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">5</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>73930</offset><text>Taking from the cytoplasm and giving to the pore: soluble transport factors in nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">2270</infon><infon key="lpage">2284</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Simos;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Tekotte;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Grosjean;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Segref;given-names:A</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Sharma;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Tollervey;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Hurt;given-names:EC</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8641292</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1996</infon><offset>74032</offset><text>Nuclear pore proteins are involved in the biogenesis of functional tRNA</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4673</infon><infon key="lpage">4680</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Thompson;given-names:JD</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Higgins;given-names:DG</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Gibson;given-names:TJ</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7984417</infon><infon key="source">Nucleic Acids Res</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">22</infon><infon key="year">1994</infon><offset>74104</offset><text>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">5474</infon><infon key="lpage">5484</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Toda;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Shimanuki;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Saka;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Yamano;given-names:H</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Adachi;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Shirakawa;given-names:M</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Kyogoku;given-names:Y</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Yanagida;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">1448080</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell  Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">12</infon><infon key="year">1992</infon><offset>74269</offset><text>Fission yeast pap1-dependent transcription is negatively regulated by an essential nuclear protein, crm1</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1049</infon><infon key="lpage">1053</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Weis;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Mattaj;given-names:IW</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lamond;given-names:AI</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7754385</infon><infon key="source">Science (Wash DC)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">268</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>74374</offset><text>Identification of hSRP1alpha as a functional receptor for nuclear localization sequences</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">7120</infon><infon key="lpage">7128</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Weis;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Dingwall;given-names:C</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lamond;given-names:AI</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">9003787</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1996a</infon><offset>74460</offset><text>Characterization of the nuclear protein import mechanism using Ran mutants with altered binding specificities</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">1818</infon><infon key="lpage">1825</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Weis;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Ryder;given-names:U</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Lamond;given-names:AI</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8617227</infon><infon key="source">EMBO (Eur  Mol Biol Organ) J</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">15</infon><infon key="year">1996b</infon><offset>74570</offset><text>The conserved amino terminal domain of hSRP1alpha is essential for nuclear protein import</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">14209</infon><infon key="lpage">14213</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Wu;given-names:J</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Matunis;given-names:MJ</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Kraemer;given-names:D</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Blobel;given-names:G</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Coutavas;given-names:E</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7775481</infon><infon key="source">J Biol Chem</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">270</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>74657</offset><text>Nup358, a cytoplasmically exposed nucleoporin with peptide repeats, Ran-GTP binding sites, zinc fingers, a cyclophilin A homologous domain, and a leucine-rich region</text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">4691</infon><infon key="lpage">4702</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Xiao;given-names:Z</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:McGrew;given-names:JT</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Schroeder;given-names:AJ</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Fitzgerald-Hayes;given-names:M</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">8336709</infon><infon key="source">Mol Cell Biol</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">13</infon><infon key="year">1993</infon><offset>74823</offset><text>CSE1  and CSE2, two new genes required for accurate mitotic chromosome segregation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. </text></passage><passage><infon key="fpage">184</infon><infon key="lpage">188</infon><infon key="name_0">surname:Yokoyama;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_1">surname:Hayashi;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_2">surname:Seki;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_3">surname:Pante;given-names:N</infon><infon key="name_4">surname:Ohba;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_5">surname:Nishii;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_6">surname:Kuma;given-names:K</infon><infon key="name_7">surname:Hayashida;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_8">surname:Miyata;given-names:T</infon><infon key="name_9">surname:Aebi;given-names:U</infon><infon key="pub-id_pmid">7603572</infon><infon key="source">Nature (Lond)</infon><infon key="type">ref</infon><infon key="volume">376</infon><infon key="year">1995</infon><offset>74936</offset><text>A giant nucleopore protein that binds Ran/TC4</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>74982</offset><text>1.  Abbreviations used in this paper: GAP, GTPase activating protein; IBB,  importin beta binding; NLS, nuclear localization signal; NPC, nuclear pore  complex.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">footnote</infon><offset>75143</offset><text>Please address all correspondence to Dirk Gorlich, Zentrum fur Molekulare Biologie der Universitat Heidelberg, Im Neuenheimer Feld 282, 69120  Heidelberg, Germany. Tel.: (49) 6221-546862; Fax: (49) 6221-545892; E-mail:  dg@mail.zmbh.uni-heidelberg.de</text></passage></document></collection>
